<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % dummy22 SYSTEM "../entities/global.ent">
%dummy22;
]>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="compatibility-chapt"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title xml:id="compatibility-title">Compatibility With Other DBMS</title>

  <info>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <personname><firstname>Fred</firstname><surname>Toussi</surname></personname>

        <affiliation>
          <orgname>The HSQL Development Group</orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <releaseinfo>$Revision: 3096 $</releaseinfo>

    <pubdate>&timestamp;</pubdate>

    <keywordset>
      <keyword>HSQLDB</keyword>

      <keyword>HyperSQL</keyword>

      <keyword>SQL</keyword>
    </keywordset>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Copyright 2010-2019 Fred Toussi. Permission is granted to
      distribute this document without any alteration under the terms of the
      HSQLDB license. Additional permission is granted to the HSQL Development
      Group to distribute this document with or without alterations under the
      terms of the HSQLDB license.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </info>

  <section xml:id="coc_compatibility_other">
    <title>Compatibility Overview</title>

    <para>HyperSQL is used more than any other database engine for application
    testing and development targeted at other databases. Over the years, this
    usage resulted in developers finding and reporting many obscure bugs and
    opportunities for enhancements in HyperSQL. The bugs were all fixed
    shortly after the reports and enhancements were added in later
    versions.</para>

    <para>HyperSQL 2.x has been written to the SQL Standard and avoids the
    traps caused by superficial imitation of the Standard by some other RDBMS.
    The SQL Standard has existed since 1989 and has been expanded over the
    years in several revisions. HyperSQL follows SQL:2016, which still stays
    almost fully compatible with SQL-92. The X-Open specification has also
    defined a number of SQL functions which are implemented by most
    RDBMS.</para>

    <para>HyperSQL has many property settings that relax conformance to the
    Standard in order to allow compatibility with other RDBMS, without
    breaking the core integrity of the database. These properties are modified
    with SET DATABASE SQL statements described in the SQL Conformance Settings
    section of Management chapter.</para>

    <para>HyperSQL is very flexible and provides some other properties which
    define a preference among various valid choices. For example, the ability
    to set the transaction model of the database, or the ability to define the
    scale of the data type of the result of integer division or average
    calculation (<literal>SET DATABASE SQL AVG SCALE</literal>).</para>

    <para>Each major RDBMS supports additional functions that are not covered
    by the Standard. Some RDBMS use non-standard syntax for some operations.
    Although most popular RDBMS products have introduced better compatibility
    with the Standard in their recent versions, there are still some
    portability issues. HyperSQL overcomes the potability issues using these
    strategies</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>An extensive set of functions cover the SQL Standard, X-Open,
        and most of the useful functions that other RDBMS support.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Database properties, which can be specified on the URL or as SQL
        statements, relax conformance to the Standard in order to allow
        non-standard comparisons and assignments allowed by other
        RDBMS.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Specific SQL syntax compatibility modes allow syntax and type
        names that are supported by some popular RDBMS.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>User-defined types and functions, including aggregate functions,
        allow any type or function that is supported by some RDBMS to be
        defined and used.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Support for compatibility with other RDBMS has been extended with
    each version of HyperSQL. This chapter lists some of the non-standard
    features of database servers, their SQL Standard equivalents or the
    support provided by HyperSQL for those features.</para>

    <section xml:id="coc_compatibility_postgres">
      <title>PostgreSQL Compatibility</title>

      <para>PostgreSQL is fairly compatible with the Standard, but uses some
      non-standard features.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use <literal>SET DATABASE SQL SYNTAX PGS TRUE</literal> or the
          equivalent URL property <literal>sql.syntax_pgs=true</literal> to
          enable the PostgreSQL's non-standard features. References to SERIAL,
          BIGSERIAL, TEXT and UUID data types, as well as sequence functions,
          are translated into HyperSQL equivalents.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Use <literal>SET DATABASE TRANSACTION CONTROL MVCC</literal>
          if your application is multi-user.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>PostgreSQL functions are generally supported.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>For identity columns, PostgreSQL uses a non-standard linkage
          with an external identity sequence. In most cases, this can be
          converted to <literal>GENERATED BY DEFAULT AS IDENTITY</literal>. In
          those cases where the identity sequence needs to be shared by
          multiple tables, you can use a new HyperSQL feature,
          <literal>GENERATED BY DEFAULT AS SEQUENCE &lt;sequence
          name&gt;</literal>, which is the equivalent of the PostgreSQL
          implementation.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>In CREATE TABLE statements, the SERIAL and BIGSERIAL types are
          translated into INTEGER or BIGINT, with <literal>GENERATED BY
          DEFAULT AS IDENTITY</literal>. Usage of <literal>DEFAULT
          NEXTVAL(&lt;sequence name&gt;)</literal> is supported so long as the
          <literal>&lt;sequence name&gt;</literal> refers to an existing
          sequence. This usage is translated into <literal>GENERATED BY
          DEFAULT AS SEQUENCE &lt;sequence name&gt;</literal>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>In SELECT and other statements, the
          <literal>NEXTVAL(&lt;sequence name&gt;)</literal> and
          <literal>LASTVAL()</literal> functions are supported and translated
          into HyperSQL's <literal>NEXT VALUE FOR &lt;sequence
          name&gt;</literal> and <literal>IDENTITY()</literal>
          expressions.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>PostgreSQL uses a non-standard expression, <literal>SELECT 'A
          Test String'</literal> to return a single row table. The standard
          form is <literal>VALUES('A Test String')</literal>. In PGS syntax
          mode, this type of SELECT is supported.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>HyperSQL supports SQL Standard ARRAY types. PostgreSQL also
          supports this, but not entirely according to the Standard.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>SQL routines are portable, but some syntax elements are
          different and require changes.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You may need to use <literal>SET DATABASE SQL TDC { DELETE |
          UPDATE } FALSE</literal> statements, as PostgreSQL does not enforce
          the subtle rules of the Standard for foreign key cascading deletes
          and updates. PostgreSQL allows cascading operations to update a
          field value multiple times with different values, the Standard
          disallows this.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="coc_compatibility_mysql">
      <title>MySQL Compatibility</title>

      <para>HyperSQL version 2.5 is highly compatible with MySQL and supports
      most of its non-standard syntax. The latest versions of MySQL have
      introduced better Standard compatibility but some of these features have
      to be turned on via properties. You should therefore check the current
      Standard compatibility settings of your MySQL database and use the
      available HyperSQL properties to achieve closer results. If you avoid
      the few anti-Standard features of MySQL, you can port your databases to
      HyperSQL.</para>

      <para>Using HyperSQL during development and testing of MySQL apps helps
      to avoid data integrity issues that MySQL may ignore.</para>

      <para>HyperSQL does not have the following non-standard limitations of
      MySQL.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>With HyperSQL, an UPDATE statement can update UNIQUE and
          PRIMARY KEY columns of a table without causing an exception due to
          temporary violation of constraints. These constraints are checked at
          the end of execution, therefore there is no need for an ORDER BY
          clause in an UPDATE statement.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>MySQL foreign key constraints are not enforced by the default
          MyISAM engine. Be aware of the possibility of data being rejected by
          HyperSQL due to these constraints.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>With HyperSQL INSERT or UPDATE statements either succeed or
          fail due to constraint violation. MySQL has the non-standard IGNORE
          override to ignore violations and alter the data, which is not
          accepted by HyperSQL.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Unlike MySQL, HyperSQL allows you to modify a table with an
          INSERT, UPDATE or DELETE statement which selects from the same table
          in a subquery.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Follow the guidelines below for converting MySQL databases and
      applications.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use <literal>SET DATABASE SQL SYNTAX MYS TRUE</literal> or the
          equivalent URL property <literal>sql.syntax_mys=true</literal> to
          enable support for AUTO_INCREMENT and TEXT data types and several
          other types. These type definitions are translated into HyperSQL
          equivalents.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Use MVCC with <literal>SET DATABASE TRANSACTION CONTROL
          MVCC</literal> if your application is multi-user.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Avoid storing invalid values, for example invalid dates such
          as '0000-00-00' or '2001-00-00' which are rejected by
          HyperSQL.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Avoid the MySQL feature that trims spaces at the end of CHAR
          values.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>In MySQL, a database is the same as a schema. In HyperSQL
          several schemas can exist in the same database and accessed
          transparently. In addition, a HyperSQL server supports multiple
          separate databases.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>In MySQL, older, non-standard, forms of database object name
          case-sensitivity make is difficult to port applications. Use the
          latest form which encloses case-sensitive names in double
          quotes.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Almost all MySQL functions are supported, including
          GROUP_CONCAT.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>For fine control over type conversion, check the settings for
          <literal>SET DATABASE SQL CONVERT TRUNCATE FALSE</literal></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Avoid using concatenation of possibly NULL values in your
          select statements. If you have to, change the setting with the
          <literal>SET DATABASE SQL CONCAT NULLS FALSE</literal></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If your application relies on MySQL behaviour for ordering of
          nulls in SELECT statements with ORDER BY, use both <literal>SET
          DATABASE SQL NULLS FIRST FALSE</literal> and <literal>SET DATABASE
          SQL NULLS ORDER FALSE</literal> to change the defaults.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>In CREATE TABLE, MySQL syntax for KEYS, INDEX, COMMENT and
          some other features is supported.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>MySQL supports most SQL Standard types (except INTERVAL
          types), as well as non-standard types, which are also supported by
          HyperSQL. Supported types include SMALLINT, INT, BIGINT, DOUBLE,
          FLOAT, DECIMAL, NUMERIC, VARCHAR, CHAR, BINARY, VARBINARY, BLOB,
          DATE, TIMESTAMP (all Standard SQL) and TINYINT, DATETIME (non
          Standard). UNSIGNED types are converted to signed.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>In MYS syntax compatibility mode, HyperSQL translates MySQL's
          ENUM data type to VARCHAR with a check constraint on the enum
          values. Data types such as TEXT, TINYTEXT, TINYLOB, MEDIUMLOB are
          translated to Standard VARCHAR or BINARY types.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>In MYS syntax compatibility mode, HyperSQL supports MySQL's
          non-standard version of INTERVAL symbols such as DAY_HOUR and
          DAY_SECOND in DATEADD and DATESUB functions. The SQL Standard form
          is DAY TO HOUR or DAY TO SECOND.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>MySQL uses a non-standard expression, <literal>SELECT 'A Test
          String'</literal> to return a single row table. The standard form is
          <literal>VALUES('A Test String')</literal>. In MYS syntax mode, this
          type of SELECT is supported.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Indexes defined inside CREATE TABLE statements are accepted
          and created. The index names must be unique within the
          schema.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>HyperSQL supports ON UPDATE CURRENT_TIMESTAMP for column
          definitions.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>HyperSQL supports and translates INSERT IGNORE, REPLACE and ON
          DUPLICATE KEY UPDATE variations of INSERT into predictable and
          error-free operations.</para>

          <para>When INSERT IGNORE is used, if any of the inserted rows would
          violate a PRIMARY KEY or UNIQUE constraint, that row is not
          inserted. With multi-row inserts, the rest of the rows are then
          inserted only if there is no other violation such as long strings or
          type mismatch, otherwise the appropriate error is returned.</para>

          <para>When REPLACE or ON DUPLICATE KEY UPDATE is used, the rows that
          need replacing or updating are updated with the given values. This
          works exactly like an UPDATE statement for those rows. Referential
          constraints and other integrity checks are enforced and update
          triggers are activated. The row count returned is simply the total
          number of rows inserted and updated.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>MySQL user-defined function and procedure syntax is very
          similar to SQL Standard syntax supported by HSQLDB. A few changes
          may still be required.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="coc_compatibility_firebird">
      <title>Firebird Compatibility</title>

      <para>Firebird generally follows the SQL Standard. Applications can be
      ported to HyperSQL without difficulty.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="coc_compatibility_derby">
      <title>Apache Derby Compatibility</title>

      <para>Apache Derby supports a smaller subset of the SQL Standard
      compared to HyperSQL. Applications can be ported to HyperSQL without
      difficulty.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use MVCC with <literal>SET DATABASE TRANSACTION CONTROL
          MVCC</literal> if your application is multi-user.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>HyperSQL supports Java language functions and stored
          procedures with the SQL Standard syntax, which is similar to the way
          Derby supports these features.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="coc_compatibility_oracle">
      <title>Oracle Compatibility</title>

      <para>Recent versions of Oracle support Standard SQL syntax for outer
      joins and many other operations. In addition, HyperSQL features a
      setting to support Oracle syntax and semantics for the most widely used
      non-standard features.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use <literal>SET DATABASE SQL SYNTAX ORA TRUE</literal> or the
          equivalent URL property <literal>sql.syntax_ora=true</literal> to
          enable support for some non-standard syntax of Oracle.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Use MVCC with <literal>SET DATABASE TRANSACTION CONTROL
          MVCC</literal> if your application is multi-user.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Fine control over MVCC deadlock avoidance is provided by the
          <literal>SET DATABASE TRANSACTION ROLLBACK ON CONFLICT
          FALSE</literal> and the corresponding
          <literal>hsqldb.tx_conflict_rollback</literal> connection
          property.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If your application relies on Oracle behaviour for nulls in
          multi-column UNIQUE constraints, use <literal>SET DATABASE SQL
          UNIQUE NULLS FALSE</literal> to change the default.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If your application relies on Oracle behaviour for ordering of
          nulls in SELECT statements with ORDER BY, but without NULLS FIRST or
          NULLS LAST, use both <literal>SET DATABASE SQL NULLS FIRST
          FALSE</literal> and <literal>SET DATABASE SQL NULLS ORDER
          FALSE</literal> to change the defaults.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you use the non-standard concatenation of possibly NULL
          values in your select statements, you may need to change the setting
          for <literal>SET DATABASE SQL CONCAT NULLS FALSE</literal>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You may want to use <literal>SET DATABASE COLLATION SQL_TEXT
          NO PAD</literal> to take into account differences in trailing spaces
          in string comparisons.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Many Oracle functions are supported, including no-arg
          functions such as SYSDATE and SYSTIMESTAMP and more complex ones
          such as TO_DATE and TO_CHAR.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Non-standard data type definitions such as NUMBER, VARCHAR2,
          NVARCHAR2, BINARY_DOUBLE, BINARY_FLOAT, LONG, RAW are translated
          into the closest SQL Standard equivalent in ORA mode.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Non-standard column DEFAULT definitions in CREATE TABLE, such
          as the use of DUAL with a SEQUENCE function are supported and
          translated in ORA syntax mode.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The DATE type is interpreted as TIMESTAMP(0) in ORA syntax
          mode.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The DUAL table and the expressions, ROWNUM, CURRVAL, NEXTVAL
          are supported in ORA syntax mode.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>HyperSQL natively supports operations involving datetime and
          interval values. These features are based on the SQL
          Standard.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Many subtle automatic type conversions, syntax refinements and
          other common features are supported.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>SQL routines in PL/SQL are generally portable, but some
          changes are required.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>More advanced compatibility is offered by HyperXtremeSQL,
          which is a product based on HyperSQL. It supports more function
          compatibility, the PL/HXSQL language with a similar syntax to
          PL/SQL, extensive support for additional aggregate functions, window
          analytic functions with OVER(PARTITION ... ORDER ... ROWS | RANGE
          ...) and WITHIN GROUP (ORDER BY).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="coc_compatibility_db2">
      <title>DB2 Compatibility</title>

      <para>DB2 is highly compatible with the SQL Standard (except for its
      lack of support for the INFORMATION_SCHEMA). Applications can be ported
      to HyperSQL without difficulty.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use <literal>SET DATABASE SQL SYNTAX DB2 TRUE</literal> or the
          equivalent URL property <literal>sql.syntax_db2=true</literal> to
          enable support for some non-standard syntax of DB2.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Use MVCC with <literal>SET DATABASE TRANSACTION CONTROL
          MVCC</literal> if your application is multi-user.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>HyperSQL supports almost the entire syntax of DB2 together
          with many of the functions. Even local temporary tables using the
          SESSION pseudo schema are supported.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The DB2 binary type definition FOR BIT DATA, as well as empty
          definition of column default values are supported in DB2 syntax
          mode.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Many DB2 functions are supported.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The DUAL table and the expressions, ROWNUM, CURRVAL, NEXTVAL
          are supported in DB2 syntax mode.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>SQL routines are highly portable with minimal change.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>More advanced compatibility is offered by HyperXtremeSQL,
          which is a product based on HyperSQL. It has extensive support for
          additional aggregate functions, window analytic functions with
          OVER(PARTITION ... ORDER BY ... ROWS | RANGE ...) and WITHIN GROUP
          (ORDER BY ...).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="coc_compatibility_mssql">
      <title>MS SQLServer and Sybase Compatibility</title>

      <para>SQLServer has some incompatibilities with the Standard syntax. The
      most significant is the use of square brackets instead of double quotes
      for case-sensitive column names.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use <literal>SET DATABASE SQL SYNTAX MSS TRUE</literal> or the
          equivalent URL property <literal>sql.syntax_mss=true</literal> to
          enable support for the <literal>CONVERT(&lt;type definition&gt;,
          &lt;expression)</literal> function with switched order of
          arguments</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Use MVCC with <literal>SET DATABASE TRANSACTION CONTROL
          MVCC</literal> if your application is multi-user.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you use the non-standard concatenation of possibly NULL
          values in your select statements, you may need to change the setting
          for <literal>SET DATABASE SQL CONCAT NULLS FALSE</literal>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>HyperSQL supports + for string concatenation.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>SQLServer uses a non-standard expression, <literal>SELECT 'A
          Test String'</literal> to return a single row table. The standard
          form is <literal>VALUES('A Test String')</literal>. In MSS syntax
          mode, this type of SELECT is supported.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>SQLServer's non-standard data types, MONEY, UNIQUEIDENTIFIER,
          DATETIME2, DATETIMEOFFSET, IMAGE, TEXT, NTEXT, are translated to
          their SQL Standard equivalents.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>HyperSQL 2.5 supports several datetime functions in MSS
          compatibility mode. These include DATEPART, DATENAME, EOMONTH and
          compatible DATEADD and DATEDIFF behaviour.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>SQL routines need quite a lot of changes.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>More advanced compatibility is offered by HyperXtremeSQL,
          which is a product based on HyperSQL. It has extensive support for
          additional aggregate functions, window analytic functions with
          OVER(PARTITION ... ORDER BY ... ROWS | RANGE ...) and WITHIN GROUP
          (ORDER BY ...).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
