<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % dummy22 SYSTEM "../entities/global.ent">
%dummy22;
]>
<appendix version="5.0" xml:id="openoffice-app"
          xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
          xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
          xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
          xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
          xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
          xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <!-- We declare the default namespace + those for prefixes xlink: and xi: in
       the root element, so we can use them anywhere in this file. -->

  <info>
    <title xml:id="openoffice-title">HyperSQL with OpenOffice.org</title>

    <subtitle>How to use HyperSQL with OpenOffice.org</subtitle>

    <author>
      <personname><firstname>Fred</firstname>
      <surname>Toussi</surname></personname>

      <affiliation>
        <orgname>The HSQL Development Group</orgname>
      </affiliation>
    </author>

    <releaseinfo>$Revision$</releaseinfo>

    <pubdate>&timestamp;</pubdate>

    <keywordset>
      <keyword>HSQLDB</keyword>

      <keyword>HyperSQL</keyword>

      <keyword>OpenOffice</keyword>

      <keyword>OpenOfficeOrg</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </info>

  <section xml:id="ooa_overview">
    <title>HyperSQL with OpenOffice.org</title>

    <simpara>OpenOffice.org includes HyperSQL and uses it for embedded
    databases. Our collaboration with OpenOffice.org developers over the last
    few years has benefited the development and maturity of HyperSQL. Before
    integration into OOo, HSQLDB was intended solely for application-specific
    database access. The application developer was expected to resolve any
    integration issues. Because OpenOffice.org is used by a vast range of
    users, from schoolchildren to corporate developers, a much higher level of
    quality assurance has been required and we have achieved it with constant
    help and feedback from OOo users and developers.</simpara>

    <simpara>Apart from embedded use, you may want to use OpenOffic.org with a
    HyperSQL server instance. The typical use for this is to allow multiple
    office users accessing the same database. There is, however, a strong case
    for using OOo to develop your database schema and application, even if the
    database is intended for your own application.</simpara>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="ooa_database_tool">
    <title>Using OpenOffice.org as a Database Tool</title>

    <simpara>OpenOffice.org is a very powerful database front end. If you want
    to create schemas, edit tables, edit the database contents manually,
    design and produce well-formatted reports, then OpenOffice.org is probably
    the best open source tools currently available.</simpara>

    <simpara>To connect from OpenOffice.org to your database, first run a
    local server instance for the database. This is describes in the Network
    Listeners chapter of this guide.</simpara>

    <simpara>When you connect from OpenOffice.org, you must specify connection
    to an external database and use the URL property "default_schema=true".
    For example, the URL to connect the local database may be like</simpara>

    <programlisting> jdbc;hsqldb:hsql://localhost/mydb;default_schema=true </programlisting>

    <simpara>The only current limitation is that OpenOffice.org only works
    with the PUBLIC schema. This limitation will hopefully removed in the
    future versions of OOo.</simpara>

    <simpara>When using of HyperSQL with OOo, you must use the HyperSQL jar
    that is supplied with OOo. This wil hopefuly be a version 2.0 jar in the
    future versions of OOo.</simpara>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="ooa_db_files_convert">
    <title>Converting .odb files to use with HyperSQL Server</title>

    <simpara>You may already have an OOo database file, which you want to use
    outside OOo, or as a server database. The file is in fact in the standard
    ZIP format and contains the normal HyperSQL database files. Just use a
    utility such as 7Zip to expand the .odb file. In the /db directory, there
    are files such as .script, .data, etc. Just rename these files into
    mydb.script, mydb.data, etc. You can now open the mydb database directly
    with HyperSQL as an embedded database or as a server instance.</simpara>
  </section>
</appendix>
