<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % dummy22 SYSTEM "../entities/global.ent">
%dummy22;
]>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="sessions-chapt"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns6="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title xml:id="sessions-title">Sessions and Transactions</title>

  <info>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <personname><firstname>Fred</firstname><surname>Toussi</surname></personname>

        <affiliation>
          <orgname>The HSQL Development Group</orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <releaseinfo>$Revision$</releaseinfo>

    <pubdate>&timestamp;</pubdate>

    <keywordset>
      <keyword>Hsqldb</keyword>

      <keyword>HyperSQL</keyword>

      <keyword>SQL</keyword>
    </keywordset>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Copyright 2010-2012 Fred Toussi. Permission is granted to distribute
      this document without any alteration under the terms of the HSQLDB
      license. Additional permission is granted to the HSQL Development Group
      to distribute this document with or without alterations under the terms
      of the HSQLDB license.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </info>

  <section xml:id="snc_overview">
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>All SQL statements are executed in sessions. When a connection is
    established to the database, a session is started. The authorization of
    the session is the name of the user that started the session. A session
    has several properties. These properties are set by default at the start
    according to database settings.</para>

    <para>SQL Statements are generally transactional statements. When a
    transactional statement is executed, it starts a transaction if no
    transaction is in progress. If SQL Data is modified during a transaction,
    the change can be undone with a ROLLBACK statement. When a COMMIT
    statement is executed, the transaction is ended. If a single statement
    fails, the transaction is not normally terminated. However, some failures
    are caused by execution of statements that are in conflict with statements
    executed in other concurrent sessions. Such failures result in an implicit
    ROLLBACK, in addition to the exception that is raised.</para>

    <para>Schema definition and manipulation statements are also transactional
    according to the SQL Standard. HyperSQL 2.0 performs automatic commits
    before and after the execution of such transactions. Therefore,
    schema-related statements cannot be rolled back. This is likely to change
    in future versions.</para>

    <para>Some statements are not transactional. Most of these statements are
    used to change the properties of the session. These statements begin with
    the SET keyword.</para>

    <para>If the AUTOCOMMIT property of a session is TRUE, then each
    transactional statement is followed by an implicit COMMIT.</para>

    <simpara>The default isolation level for a session is READ COMMITTED. This
    can be changed using the JDBC <classname>java.sql.Connection</classname>
    object and its <methodname>setTransactionIsolation(int level)</methodname>
    method. The session can be put in read-only mode using the
    <methodname>setReadOnly(boolean readOnly)</methodname> method. Both
    methods can be invoked only after a commit or a rollback, but not during a
    transaction.</simpara>

    <simpara>The isolation level and / or the readonly mode of a transaction
    can also be modified using an SQL statement. You can use the statement to
    change only the isolation mode, only the read-only mode, or both at the
    same time. This command can be issued only after a commit or
    rollback.</simpara>

    <simpara><literal>SET TRANSACTION &lt;transaction characteristic&gt; [
    &lt;comma&gt; &lt;transaction characteristic&gt; ]</literal></simpara>

    <para>Details of the statement is described later in this chapter.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="snc_session_attr_vars">
    <title>Session Attributes and Variables</title>

    <para>Each session has several system attributes. A session can also have
    user-defined session variables.</para>

    <section xml:id="snc_session_attr">
      <title>Session Attributes</title>

      <para>The system attributes reflect the current mode of operation for
      the session. These attributes can be accessed with function calls and
      can be referenced in queries. For example, they can be returned using
      the <literal>VALUES &lt;attribute function&gt;, ...</literal>
      statement.</para>

      <para>The named attributes such as CURRENT_USER, CURRENT_SCHEMA, etc.
      are SQL Standard functions. Other attributes of the session, such as
      auto-commit or read-only modes can be read using other built-in
      functions. All these functions are listed in the <link
      endterm="builtinfunctions-title"
      ns6:href="#builtinfunctions-chapt"></link> chapter.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="snc_session_vars">
      <title>Session Variables</title>

      <para>Session variables are user-defined variables created the same way
      as the variables for stored procedures and functions. Currently, these
      variables cannot be used in general SQL statements. They can be assigned
      to IN, INOUT and OUT parameters of stored procedures. This allows
      calling stored procedures which have INOUT or OUT arguments and is
      useful for development and debugging. See the example in the <link
      endterm="sqlroutines-title" ns6:href="#sqlroutines-chapt"></link>
      chapter, under Formal Parameters.</para>

      <example>
        <title>User-defined Session Variables</title>

        <screen>  DECLARE counter INTEGER DEFAULT 3;
  DECLARE result VARCHAR(20) DEFAULT NULL;
  SET counter=15;
  CALL myroutine(counter, result)
</screen>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="snc_session_tables">
      <title>Session Tables</title>

      <para>With necessary access privileges, sessions can access all table,
      including GLOBAL TEMPORARY tables, that are defined in schemas. Although
      GLOBAL TEMPORARY tables have a single name and definition which applies
      to all sessions that use them, the contents of the tables are different
      for each session. The contents are cleared either at the end of each
      transaction or when the session is closed.</para>

      <para>Session tables are different because their definition is visible
      only within the session that defines a table. The definition is dropped
      when the session is closed. Session tables do not belong to
      schemas.</para>

      <para><literal>&lt;temporary table declaration&gt; ::= DECLARE LOCAL
      TEMPORARY TABLE &lt;table name&gt; &lt;table element list&gt; [ ON
      COMMIT { PRESERVE | DELETE } ROWS ]</literal></para>

      <para>The syntax for declaration is based on the SQL Standard. A session
      table cannot have FOREIGN KEY constraints, but it can have PRIMARY KEY,
      UNIQUE or CHECK constraints. A session table definition cannot be
      modified by adding or removing columns, indexes, etc.</para>

      <para>It is possible to refer to a session table using its name, which
      takes precedence over a schema table of the same name. To distinguish a
      session table from schema tables, the pseudo schema names, MODULE or
      SESSION can be used. An example is given below:</para>

      <para><example>
          <title>User-defined Temporary Session Tables</title>

          <screen>  DECLARE LOCAL TEMPORARY TABLE buffer (id INTEGER PRIMARY KEY, textdata VARCHAR(100)) ON COMMIT PRESERVE ROWS
  INSERT INTO module.buffer SELECT id, firstname || ' ' || lastname FROM customers
  -- do some more work
  DROP TABLE module.buffer
  -- or use alternative pseudo schema name
  DROP TABLE session.buffer
</screen>
        </example>Session tables can be created inside a transaction.
      Automatic indexes are created and used on session tables when necessary
      for a query or other statement. By default, session table data is held
      in memory. This can be changed with the <literal>SET SESSION RESULT
      MEMORY ROWS</literal> statement.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="snc_tx_tx_cc">
    <title>Transactions and Concurrency Control</title>

    <para>HyperSQL 2.0 has been fully redesigned to support different
    transaction isolation models. It no longer supports the old 1.8.x model
    with "dirty read". Although it is perfectly possible to add an
    implementation of the transaction manager that supports the legacy model,
    we thought this is no longer necessary. The new system allows you to
    select the transaction isolation model while the engine is running. It
    also allows you to choose different isolation levels for different
    simultaneous sessions.</para>

    <para>HyperSQL 2.0 supports three concurrency control models,
    two-phase-locking (2PL), which is the default, multiversion concurrency
    control (MVCC) and a hybrid model, which is 2PL plus multiversion rows.
    Within each model, it supports some of the 4 standard levels of
    transaction isolation: READ UNCOMMITTED, READ COMMITTED, REPEATABLE READ
    and SERIALIZABLE. The concurrency control model is a strategy that governs
    all the sessions and is set for the database, as opposed for individual
    sessions. The isolation level is a property of each SQL session, so
    different sessions can have different isolation levels. In the new
    implementation, all isolation levels avoid the "dirty read" phenomenon and
    do not read uncommitted changes made to rows by other transactions.</para>

    <para>HyperSQL is fully multi threaded in all transaction models. Sessions
    continue to work simultaneously and can fully utilise multi-core
    processors.</para>

    <para>To concurrency control model of a live database can be changed. The
    <literal>SET DATABASE TRANSACTION CONTROL { LOCKS | MVLOCKS | MVCC
    }</literal> can be used by a user with the DBA role.</para>

    <section xml:id="snc_tx_2pl">
      <title>Two Phase Locking</title>

      <para>The two-phase locking model is the default mode. It is referred to
      by the keyword, LOCKS. In the 2PL model, each table that is read by a
      transaction is locked with a shared lock (read lock), and each table
      that is written to is locked with an exclusive lock (write lock). If two
      sessions read and modify different tables then both go through
      simultaneously. If one session tries to lock a table that has been
      locked by the other, if both locks are shared locks, it will go ahead.
      If either of the locks is an exclusive lock, the engine will put the
      session in wait until the other session commits or rolls back its
      transaction. In some cases the engine will invalidate the transaction of
      the current session, if the action would result in deadlock.</para>

      <para>HyperSQL also supports explicit locking of a group of tables for
      the duration of the current transaction. Use of this command blocks
      access to the locked tables by other sessions and ensures the current
      session can complete the intended reads and writes on the locked
      tables.</para>

      <para>If a table is read-only, it will not be locked by any
      transaction.</para>

      <para>The READ UNCOMMITTED isolation level can be used in 2PL modes for
      read-only operations. It is the same as READ COMMITTED plus read
      only.</para>

      <para>The READ COMMITTED isolation level is the default. It keeps write
      locks on tables until commit, but releases the read locks after each
      operation.</para>

      <para>The REPEATABLE READ level is upgraded to SERIALIZABLE. These
      levels keep both read and write locks on tables until commit.</para>

      <para>It is possible to perform some critical operations at the
      SERIALIZABLE level, while the rest of the operations are performed at
      the READ COMMITTED level.</para>

      <para>Note: two phase locking refers to two periods in the life of a
      transaction. In the first period, locks are acquired, in the second
      period locks are released. No new lock is acquired after releasing a
      lock.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="snc_tx_2pl_si">
      <title>Two Phase Locking with Snapshot Isolation</title>

      <para>This model is referred to as MVLOCKS. It works the same way as
      normal 2PL as far as updates are concerned.</para>

      <para>SNAPSHOT ISOLATION is a multiversion concurrency strategy which
      uses the snapshot of the whole database at the time of the start of the
      transaction. In this model, read only transactions use SNAPSHOT
      ISOLATION. While other sessions are busy changing the database, the read
      only session sees a consistent view of the database and can access all
      the tables even when they are locked by other sessions for
      updates.</para>

      <para>There are many applications for this mode of operation. In heavily
      updated data sets, this mode allows uninterrupted read access to the
      data.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="snc_tx_locks_2pl">
      <title>Lock Contention in 2PL</title>

      <para>When multiple connections are used to access the database, the
      transaction manager controls their activities. When each transaction
      performs only reads or writes on a single table, there is no contention.
      Each transaction waits until it can obtain a lock then performs the
      operation and commits. All contentions occur when transactions perform
      reads and writes on more than one table, or perform a read, followed by
      a write, on the same table.</para>

      <para>For example, when sessions are working at the SERIALIZABLE level,
      when multiple sessions first read from a table in order to check if a
      row exists, then insert a row into the same table when it doesn't exist,
      there will be regular contention. Transaction A reads from the table,
      then does Transaction B. Now if either Transaction A or B attempts to
      insert a row, it will have to be terminated as the other transaction
      holds a shared lock on the table. If instead of two operations, a single
      MERGE statement is used to perform the read and write, no contention
      occurs because both locks are obtained at the same time.</para>

      <para>Alternatively, there is the option of obtaining the necessary
      locks with an explicit LOCK TABLE statement. This statement should be
      executed before other statements and should include the names of all the
      tables and the locks needed. After this statement, all the other
      statements in the transaction can be executed and the transaction
      committed. The commit will remove all the locks.</para>

      <para>HyperSQL detects deadlocks before attempting to execute a
      statement. When a lock is released after the completion of the
      statement, the first transaction that is waiting for the lock is allowed
      to continue.</para>

      <para>HyperSQL is fully multi threaded. It therefore allows different
      transactions to execute concurrently so long as they are not waiting to
      lock the same table for write.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="snc_tx_locks_routines">
      <title>Locks in SQL Routines and Triggers</title>

      <para>In both LOCKS and MVLOCKS models, SQL routines (functions and
      procedures) and triggers obtain all the read and write locks at the
      beginning of the routine execution. SQL statements contained in the
      routine or trigger are all executed without deadlock as all the locks
      have already been obtained. At the end of execution of the routine or
      trigger, read locks are released if the session isolation level is READ
      COMMITTED.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="snc_tx_mvcc">
      <title>MVCC</title>

      <para>In the MVCC model, there are no shared, read locks. Exclusive
      locks are used on individual rows, but their use is different.
      Transactions can read and modify the same table simultaneously,
      generally without waiting for other transactions. The SQL Standard
      isolation levels are used by the user's application, but these isolation
      levels are translated to the MVCC isolation levels READ CONSISTENCY or
      SNAPSHOT ISOLATION.</para>

      <para>When transactions are running at READ COMMITTED level, no conflict
      will normally occur. If a transaction that runs at this level wants to
      modify a row that has been modified by another uncommitted transaction,
      then the engine puts the transaction in wait, until the other
      transaction has committed. The transaction then continues automatically.
      This isolation level is called READ CONSISTENCY.</para>

      <para>Deadlock is completely avoided. In theory conflict is possible if
      each transaction is waiting for a different row modified by the other
      transaction. In this case, one of the transactions is immediately
      terminated (rolled back) unless the setting has been changed with the
      <literal>&lt;set database transaction rollback on conflict
      statement&gt;</literal>. When this setting is changed to FALSE, the
      session that avoided executing the deadlock-causing statement returns an
      error, but without rolling back the previous actions. This will cause
      the other transaction to wait for the current transaction. The property
      should not be changed unless the application can quickly perform an
      alternative statement to continue or roll back the transaction. This
      allows maximum flexibility and compatibility with other database engines
      which do not roll back the transaction upon deadlock.</para>

      <para>When transactions are running in REPEATABLE READ or SERIALIZABLE
      isolation levels, conflict is more likely to happen. There is no
      difference in operation between these two isolation levels. This
      isolation level is called SNAPSHOT ISOLATION.</para>

      <para>In this mode, when the duration of two transactions overlaps, if
      one of the transactions has modified a row and the second transaction
      wants to modify the same row, the action of the second transaction will
      fail. The engine will invalidate the second transaction and roll back
      all its changes. If the setting is changed to false with the
      <literal>&lt;set database transaction rollback on conflict
      statement&gt;</literal>, then the second transaction will just return an
      error without rolling back. The application must perform an alternative
      statement to continue or roll back the transaction.</para>

      <para>In the MVCC model, READ UNCOMMITTED is promoted to READ COMMITTED,
      as the new architecture is based on multi-version rows for uncommitted
      data and more than one version may exist for some rows.</para>

      <para>With MVCC, when a transaction only reads data, then it will go
      ahead and complete regardless of what other transactions may do. This
      does not depend on the transaction being read-only or the isolation
      modes.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="snc_tx_choosing">
      <title>Choosing the Transaction Model</title>

      <para>The SQL Standard defines the isolation levels as modes of
      operation that avoid the three unwanted phenomena, "dirty read", "fuzzy
      read" and "phantom row". The "dirty read" phenomenon occurs when a
      session can read a row that has been changed by another session. The
      "fuzzy read" phenomenon occurs when a row that was read by a session is
      modified by another session, then the first session reads the row again.
      The "phantom row" phenomenon occurs when a session performs an operation
      that affects several rows, for example, counts the rows or modifies them
      using a search condition, then another session adds one or more rows
      that fulfil the same search condition, then the first session performs
      an operation that relies on the results of its last operation. According
      to the Standard, the SERIALIZABLE isolation level avoids all three
      phenomena and also ensures that all the changes performed during a
      transaction can be considered as a series of uninterrupted changes to
      the database without any other transaction changing the database at all
      for the duration of these actions. The changes made by other
      transactions are considered to occur before the SERIALIZABLE transaction
      starts, or after it ends. The READ COMMITTED level avoids "dirty read"
      only, while the REPEATABLE READ level avoids "dirty read" and "fuzzy
      read", but not "phantom row".</para>

      <para>The Standard allows the engine to return a higher isolation level
      than requested by the application. HyperSQL promotes a READ UNCOMMITTED
      request to READ COMMITTED and promotes a REPEATABLE READ request to
      SERIALIZABLE.</para>

      <para>The MVCC model is not covered directly by the Standard. Research
      has established that the READ CONSISTENCY level fulfils the
      requirements of (and is stronger than) the READ COMMITTED level. The
      SNAPSHOT ISOLATION level is stronger than the READ CONSISTENCY level. It
      avoids the three anomalies defined by the Standard, and is therefore
      stronger than the REPEATABLE READ level as defined by the Standard. When
      operating with the MVCC model, HyperSQL treats a REPEATABLE READ or
      SERIALIZABLE setting for a transaction as SNAPSHOT ISOLATION.</para>

      <para>All modes can be used with as many simultaneous connections as
      required. The default 2PL model is fine for applications with a single
      connection, or applications that do not access the same tables heavily
      for writes. With multiple simultaneous connections, MVCC can be used for
      most applications. Both READ CONSISTENCY and SNAPSHOT ISOLATION levels
      are stronger than the corresponding READ COMMITTED level in the 2PL
      mode. Some applications require SERIALIZABLE transactions for at least
      some of their operations. For these applications, one of the 2PL modes
      can be used. It is possible to switch the concurrency model while the
      database is operational. Therefore, the model can be changed for the
      duration of some special operations, such as synchronization with
      another data source.</para>

      <para>All concurrency models are very fast in operation. When data
      change operations are mainly on the same tables, the MVCC model may be
      faster, especially with multi-core processors.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="snc_tx_schema_change">
      <title>Schema and Database Change</title>

      <para>There are a few SQL statements that must access a consistent state
      of the database during their executions. These statements, which include
      CHECKPOINT and BACKUP, put an exclusive lock on all the tables of the
      database when they start.</para>

      <para>Some schema manipulation statements put an exclusive lock on one
      or more tables. For example changing the columns of a table locks the
      table exclusively.</para>

      <para>In the MVCC model, all statements that need an exclusive lock on
      one or more tables, put an exclusive lock on the database catalog until
      they complete.</para>

      <para>The effect of these exclusive locks is similar to the execution of
      data manipulation statements with write locks. The session that is about
      to execute the schema change statement waits until no other session is
      holding a lock on any of the objects. At this point it starts its
      operation and locks the objects to prevents any other session from
      accessing the locked objects. As soon as the operation is complete, the
      locks are all removed.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="snc_tx_access_tables">
      <title>Simultaneous Access to Tables</title>

      <para>It was mentioned that there is no limit on the number of sessions
      that can access the tables and all sessions work simultaneously in multi
      threaded execution. However there are internal resources that are
      shared. Simultaneous access to these resources can reduce the overall
      efficiency of the system. MEMORY and TEXT tables do not share resources
      and do not block multi threaded access. With CACHED tables, each row
      change operation blocks the file and its cache momentarily until the
      operation is finished. This is done separately for each row, therefore a
      multi-row INSERT, UPDATE, or DELETE statement will allow other sessions
      to access the file during its execution. With CACHED tables, SELECT
      operations do not block each other, but selecting from different tables
      and different parts of a large table causes the row cache to be updated
      frequently and will reduce overall performance.</para>

      <para>The new access pattern is the opposite of the access pattern of
      version 1.8.x. In the old version, even when 20 sessions are actively
      reading and writing, only a single session at a time performs an SQL
      statement completely, before the next session is allowed access. In the
      new version, while a session is performing a SELECT statement and
      reading rows of a CACHED table to build a result set, another session
      may perform an UPDATE statement that reads and writes rows of the same
      table. The two operations are performed without any conflict, but the
      row cache is updated more frequently than when one operation is
      performed after the other operation has finished.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="snc_viewing_sessions">
      <title>Viewing Sessions</title>

      <para>As HyperSQL is multithreaded, you can view the current sessions
      and their state from any admin session. The
      <literal>INFORMATION_SCHEMA.SYSTEM_SESSIONS</literal> table contains the
      list of open sessions, their unique ids and the statement currently
      executed or waiting to be executed by each session. For each session, it
      displays the list of sessions that are waiting for it to commit, or the
      session that this session is waiting for.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="snc_statements">
    <title>Session and Transaction Control Statements</title>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>ALTER SESSION</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">ALTER SESSION</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>alter session statement</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;alter session statement&gt; ::= ALTER SESSION
    &lt;numeric literal&gt; { CLOSE | RELEASE }</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;alter current session statement&gt; ::= ALTER
    SESSION RESET { ALL | RESULT SETS | TABLE DATA }</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>The &lt;alter session statement&gt; is used by an administrator
    to close another session or to release the transaction in another session.
    When a session is released, its current transaction is terminated with a
    failure. The session remains open. This statement is different from the
    other statements discussed in this chapter as it is not used for changing
    the settings of the current session.</simpara>

    <simpara>The session ID is used as a <literal>&lt;numeric
    literal&gt;</literal> in this statement. The administrator can use the
    <literal>INFORMATION_SCHEMA.SYSTEM_SESSIONS</literal> table to find the
    session IDs of other sessions.</simpara>

    <simpara>The &lt;alter current session statement&gt; is used to clear and
    reset different states of the current session. When ALL is specified, the
    current transaction is rolled back, the session settings such as time
    zone, current schema etc. are restored to their original state at the time
    the session was opened and all open result sets are closed and temporary
    tables cleared. When RESULT SETS is specified, all currently open result
    sets are closed and the resources are released. When TABLE DATA is
    specified, the data in all temporary tables is cleared.</simpara>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>SET AUTOCOMMIT</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET AUTOCOMMIT</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>set autocommit command</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;set autocommit statement&gt; ::= SET AUTOCOMMIT {
    TRUE | FALSE }</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>When an SQL session is started by creating a JDBC connection, it
    is in AUTOCOMMIT mode. In this mode, after each SQL statement a COMMIT is
    performed automatically. This statement changes the mode. It is equivalent
    to using the <methodname>setAutoCommit( boolean autoCommit)</methodname>
    method of the JDBC <classname>Connection</classname> object.</simpara>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>START TRANSACTION</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">START TRANSACTION</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>start transaction statement</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;start transaction statement&gt; ::= START
    TRANSACTION [ &lt;transaction characteristics&gt; ]</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>Start an SQL transaction and set its characteristics. All
    transactional SQL statements start a transaction automatically, therefore
    using this statement is not necessary. If the statement is called in the
    middle of a transaction, an exception is thrown.</simpara>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>SET TRANSACTION</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET TRANSACTION</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>set next transaction
    characteristics</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;set transaction statement&gt; ::= SET [ LOCAL ]
    TRANSACTION &lt;transaction characteristics&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>Set the characteristics of the next transaction in the current
    session. This statement has an effect only on the next transactions and
    has no effect on the future transactions after the next.</simpara>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>transaction characteristics</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">transaction
    characteristics</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>transaction characteristics</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;transaction characteristics&gt; ::= [
    &lt;transaction mode&gt; [ { &lt;comma&gt; &lt;transaction mode&gt; }... ]
    ]</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;transaction mode&gt; ::= &lt;isolation level&gt; |
    &lt;transaction access mode&gt; | &lt;diagnostics
    size&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;transaction access mode&gt; ::= READ ONLY | READ
    WRITE</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;isolation level&gt; ::= ISOLATION LEVEL &lt;level of
    isolation&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;level of isolation&gt; ::= READ UNCOMMITTED | READ
    COMMITTED | REPEATABLE READ | SERIALIZABLE</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;diagnostics size&gt; ::= DIAGNOSTICS SIZE &lt;number
    of conditions&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;number of conditions&gt; ::= &lt;simple value
    specification&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>Specify transaction characteristics.</simpara>

    <example>
      <title>Setting Transaction Characteristics</title>

      <screen>  SET TRANSACTION READ ONLY
  SET TRANSACTION ISOLATION LEVEL SERIALIZABLE
  SET TRANSACTION READ WRITE, ISOLATION LEVEL READ COMMITTED
</screen>
    </example>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>SET CONSTRAINTS</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET CONSTRAINTS</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>set constraints mode statement</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;set constraints mode statement&gt; ::= SET
    CONSTRAINTS &lt;constraint name list&gt; { DEFERRED | IMMEDIATE
    }</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;constraint name list&gt; ::= ALL | &lt;constraint
    name&gt; [ { &lt;comma&gt; &lt;constraint name&gt; }...
    ]</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>If the statement is issued during a transaction, it applies to
    the rest of the current transaction. If the statement is issued when a
    transaction is not active then it applies only to the next transaction in
    the current session. HyperSQL does not yet support this feature.</simpara>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>LOCK TABLE</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">LOCK TABLE</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>lock table statement</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;lock table statement&gt; ::= LOCK TABLE &lt;table
    name&gt; { READ | WRITE} [, &lt;table name&gt; { READ | WRITE}
    ...]}</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>In some circumstances, where multiple simultaneous transactions
    are in progress, it may be necessary to ensure a transaction consisting of
    several statements is completed, without being terminated due to possible
    deadlock. When this statement is executed, it waits until it can obtain
    all the listed locks, then returns. If obtaining the locks would result in
    a deadlock an error is raised. The SQL statements following this
    statements use the locks already obtained (and obtain new locks if
    necessary) and can proceed without waiting. All the locks are released
    when a COMMIT or ROLLBACK statement is issued.</simpara>

    <simpara>When the isolation level of a session is READ COMMITTED, read
    locks are released immediately after the execution of the statement,
    therefore you should use only WRITE locks in this mode. Alternatively, you
    can switch to the SERIALIZABLE isolation mode before locking the tables
    for the specific transaction that needs to finish consistently and without
    a deadlock. It is best to execute this statement at the beginning of the
    transaction with the complete list of required read and write
    locks.</simpara>

    <simpara>Currently, this command does not have any effect when the
    database transaction control model is MVCC.</simpara>

    <example>
      <title>Locking Tables</title>

      <screen>  LOCK TABLE table_a WRITE, table_b READ</screen>
    </example>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>SAVEPOINT</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SAVEPOINT</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>savepoint statement</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;savepoint statement&gt; ::= SAVEPOINT &lt;savepoint
    specifier&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;savepoint specifier&gt; ::= &lt;savepoint
    name&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>Establish a savepoint. This command is used during an SQL
    transaction. It establishes a milestone for the current transaction. The
    SAVEPOINT can be used at a later point in the transaction to rollback the
    transaction to the milestone.</simpara>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>RELEASE SAVEPOINT</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">RELEASE SAVEPOINT</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>release savepoint statement</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;release savepoint statement&gt; ::= RELEASE
    SAVEPOINT &lt;savepoint specifier&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>Destroy a savepoint. This command is rarely used as it is not
    very useful. It removes a SAVEPOINT that has already been
    defined.</simpara>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>COMMIT</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">COMMIT</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>commit statement</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;commit statement&gt; ::= COMMIT [ WORK ] [ AND [ NO
    ] CHAIN ]</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>Terminate the current SQL-transaction with commit. This make all
    the changes to the database permanent.</simpara>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>ROLLBACK</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">ROLLBACK</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>rollback statement</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;rollback statement&gt; ::= ROLLBACK [ WORK ] [ AND [
    NO ] CHAIN ]</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>Rollback the current SQL transaction and terminate it. The
    statement rolls back all the actions performed during the transaction. If
    NO CHAIN is specified, a new SQL transaction is started just after the
    rollback. The new transaction inherits the properties of the old
    transaction.</simpara>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>ROLLBACK TO SAVEPOINT</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">ROLLBACK TO SAVEPOINT</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>rollback statement</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;rollback statement&gt; ::= ROLLBACK [ WORK ] TO
    SAVEPOINT &lt;savepoint specifier&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>Rollback part of the current SQL transaction and continue the
    transaction. The statement rolls back all the actions performed after the
    specified SAVEPOINT was created. The same effect can be achieved with the
    <literal>rollback( Savepoint savepoint)</literal> method of the JDBC
    <classname>Connection</classname> object.</simpara>

    <example>
      <title>Rollback</title>

      <screen>  -- perform some inserts, deletes, etc.
  SAVEPOINT A
  -- perform some inserts, deletes, selects etc.
  ROLLBACK WORK TO SAVEPOINT A
  -- all the work after the declaration of SAVEPOINT A is rolled back
</screen>
    </example>

    <!-- From Foundation chapt. 18 -->

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>DISCONNECT</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">DISCONNECT</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>disconnect statement</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;disconnect statement&gt; ::=
    DISCONNECT</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>Terminate the current SQL session. Closing a JDBC connection has
    the same effect as this command.</simpara>

    <!-- From Foundation chapt. 19 -->

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>SET SESSION CHARACTERISTICS</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET SESSION
    CHARACTERISTICS</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>set session characteristics
    statement</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;set session characteristics statement&gt; ::= SET
    SESSION CHARACTERISTICS AS &lt;session characteristic
    list&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;session characteristic list&gt; ::= &lt;session
    characteristic&gt; [ { &lt;comma&gt; &lt;session characteristic&gt; }...
    ]</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;session characteristic&gt; ::= &lt;session
    transaction characteristics&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;session transaction characteristics&gt; ::=
    TRANSACTION &lt;transaction mode&gt; [ { &lt;comma&gt; &lt;transaction
    mode&gt; }... ]</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>Set one or more characteristics for the current SQL-session. This
    command is used to set the transaction mode for the session. This endures
    for all transactions until the session is closed or the next use of this
    command. The current read-only mode can be accessed with the ISREADONLY()
    function.</simpara>

    <example>
      <title>Setting Session Characteristics</title>

      <screen>  SET SESSION CHARACTERISTICS AS TRANSACTION READ ONLY
  SET SESSION CHARACTERISTICS AS TRANSACTION ISOLATION LEVEL SERIALIZABLE
  SET SESSION CHARACTERISTICS AS TRANSACTION READ WRITE, ISOLATION LEVEL READ COMMITTED
</screen>
    </example>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>SET SESSION AUTHORIZATION</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET SESSION
    AUTHORIZATION</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>set session user identifier
    statement</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;set session user identifier statement&gt; ::= SET
    SESSION AUTHORIZATION &lt;value specification&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>Set the SQL-session user identifier. This statement changes the
    current user. The user that executes this command must have the
    CHANGE_AUTHORIZATION role, or the DBA role. After this statement is
    executed, all SQL statements are executed with the privileges of the new
    user. The current authorisation can be accessed with the CURRENT_USER and
    SESSION_USER functions.</simpara>

    <example>
      <title>Setting Session Authorization</title>

      <screen>  SET SESSION AUTHORIZATION 'FELIX'
  SET SESSION AUTHORIZATION SESSION_USER
</screen>
    </example>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>SET ROLE</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET ROLE</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>set role statement</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;set role statement&gt; ::= SET ROLE &lt;role
    specification&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;role specification&gt; ::= &lt;value
    specification&gt; | NONE</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>Set the SQL-session role name and the current role name for the
    current SQL-session context. The user that executes this command must have
    the specified role. If NONE is specified, then the previous CURRENT_ROLE
    is eliminated. The effect of this lasts for the lifetime of the session.
    The current role can be accessed with the CURRENT_ROLE function.</simpara>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>SET TIME ZONE</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET TIME ZONE</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>set local time zone statement</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;set local time zone statement&gt; ::= SET TIME ZONE
    &lt;set time zone value&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;set time zone value&gt; ::= &lt;interval value
    expression&gt; | LOCAL</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>Set the current default time zone displacement for the current
    SQL-session. When the session starts, the time zone displacement is set to
    the time zone of the client. This command changes the time zone
    displacement. The effect of this lasts for the lifetime of the session. If
    LOCAL is specified, the time zone displacement reverts to the local time
    zone of the session.</simpara>

    <example>
      <title>Setting Session Time Zone</title>

      <screen>  SET TIME ZONE LOCAL
  SET TIME ZONE INTERVAL '+6:00' HOUR TO MINUTE
</screen>
    </example>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>SET CATALOG</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET CATALOG</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>set catalog statement</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;set catalog statement&gt; ::= SET &lt;catalog name
    characteristic&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;catalog name characteristic&gt; ::= CATALOG
    &lt;value specification&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>Set the default schema name for unqualified names used in SQL
    statements that are prepared or executed directly in the current sessions.
    As there is only one catalog in the database, only the name of this
    catalog can be used. The current catalog can be accessed with the
    CURRENT_CATALOG function.</simpara>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>SET SCHEMA</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET SCHEMA</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>set schema statement</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;set schema statement&gt; ::= SET &lt;schema name
    characteristic&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;schema name characteristic&gt; ::= SCHEMA &lt;value
    specification&gt; | &lt;schema name&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>Set the default schema name for unqualified names used in SQL
    statements that are prepared or executed directly in the current sessions.
    The effect of this lasts for the lifetime of the session. The SQL Standard
    form requires the schema name as a single-quoted string. HyperSQL also
    allows the use of the identifier for the schema. The current schema can be
    accessed with the CURRENT_SCHEMA function.</simpara>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>SET PATH</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET PATH</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>set path statement</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;set path statement&gt; ::= SET &lt;SQL-path
    characteristic&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;SQL-path characteristic&gt; ::= PATH &lt;value
    specification&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>Set the SQL-path used to determine the subject routine of routine
    invocations with unqualified routine names used in SQL statements that are
    prepared or executed directly in the current sessions. The effect of this
    lasts for the lifetime of the session.</simpara>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>SET MAXROWS</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET MAXROWS</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>set max rows statement</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;set max rows statement&gt; ::= SET MAXROWS
    &lt;unsigned integer literal&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>The normal operation of the session has no limit on the number of
    rows returned from a SELECT statement. This command set the maximum number
    of rows of the result returned by executing queries.</simpara>

    <simpara>This statement has a similar effect to the
    <methodname>setMaxRows(int max)</methodname> method of the JDBC
    <classname>Statement</classname> interface, but it affects the results
    returned from the next statement execution only. After the execution of
    the next statement, the MAXROWS limit is removed.</simpara>

    <simpara>Only zero or positive values can be used with this command. The
    value overrides any value specified with <methodname>setMaxRows(int
    max)</methodname> method of a JDBC statement. The statement <literal>SET
    MAXROWS 0</literal> means no limit.</simpara>

    <simpara>It is possible to limit the number of rows returned from SELECT
    statements with the FETCH &lt;n&gt; ROWS ONLY, or its alternative, LIMIT
    &lt;n&gt;. Therefore this command is not recommended for general use. The
    only legitimate use of this command is for checking and testing queries
    that may return very large numbers of rows.</simpara>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>SET SESSION RESULT MEMORY ROWS</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET SESSION RESULT MEMORY
    ROWS</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>set session result memory rows
    statement</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;set session result memory rows statement&gt; ::= SET
    SESSION RESULT MEMORY ROWS &lt;unsigned integer
    literal&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>By default the session uses memory to build result sets, subquery
    results and temporary tables. This command sets the maximum number of rows
    of the result (and temporary tables) that should be kept in memory. If the
    row count of the result or temporary table exceeds the setting, the result
    is stored on disk. The default is 0, meaning all result sets are held in
    memory.</simpara>

    <simpara>This statement applies to the current session only. The general
    database setting is:</simpara>

    <simpara><literal>SET DATABASE DEFAULT RESULT MEMORY ROWS &lt;unsigned
    integer literal&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>SET IGNORECASE</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET IGNORECASE</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>set ignore case statement</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;set ignore case statement&gt; ::= SET IGNORECASE {
    TRUE | FALSE }</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>Sets the type used for new VARCHAR table columns. By default,
    character columns in new databases are case sensitive. If <literal>SET
    IGNORECASE TRUE</literal> is used, all VARCHAR columns in new tables are
    set to <literal>VARCHAR_IGNORECASE</literal>. It is possible to specify
    the <literal>VARCHAR_IGNORECASE</literal> type for the definition of
    individual columns. So it is possible to have some columns case sensitive
    and some not, even in the same table. This statement must be switched
    before creating tables. Existing tables and their data are not
    affected.</simpara>
  </section>
</chapter>
