<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % dummy22 SYSTEM "../entities/global.ent">
%dummy22;
]>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="management-chapt"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title xml:id="management-title">System Management</title>

  <info>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <personname><firstname>Fred</firstname><surname>Toussi</surname></personname>

        <affiliation>
          <orgname>The HSQL Development Group</orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <releaseinfo>$Revision$</releaseinfo>

    <pubdate>&timestamp;</pubdate>

    <keywordset>
      <keyword>Hsqldb</keyword>

      <keyword>HyperSQL</keyword>

      <keyword>SQL</keyword>
    </keywordset>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Copyright 2002-2011 Fred Toussi. Permission is granted to
      distribute this document without any alteration under the terms of the
      HSQLDB license. Additional permission is granted to the HSQL Development
      Group to distribute this document with or without alterations under the
      terms of the HSQLDB license.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </info>

  <section xml:id="deployment_modes-sect">
    <title>Mode of Operation and Tables</title>

    <para>HyperSQL has many modes of operation and features that allow it to
    be used in very different scenarios. Levels of memory usage, speed and
    accessibility by different applications are influenced by how HyperSQL is
    deployed.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Mode of Operation</title>

      <para>The decision to run HyperSQL as a separate server process or as an
      <glossterm>in-process</glossterm> database should be based on the
      following:</para>

      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>When HyperSQL is run as a server on a separate machine, it
            is isolated from hardware failures and crashes on the hosts
            running the application.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>When HyperSQL is run as a server on the same machine, it is
            isolated from application crashes and memory leaks.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Server connections are slower than
            <glossterm>in-process</glossterm> connections due to the overhead
            of streaming the data for each JDBC call.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>You can reduce client/server traffic using SQL Stored
            procedures to reduce the number of JDBC execute calls.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>During development, it is better to use a Server with
            server.silent=false, which displays the statements sent to the
            server on the console window.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>To improve speed of execution for statements that are
            executed repeatedly, reuse a parameterized PreparedStatement for
            the lifetime of the connections.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Tables</title>

      <para>TEXT tables are designed for special applications where the data
      has to be in an interchangeable format, such as CSV (comma separated
      values). TEXT tables should not be used for routine storage of
      data.</para>

      <para>MEMORY tables and CACHED tables are generally used for data
      storage. The difference between the two is as follows:</para>

      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The data for all MEMORY tables is read from the *.script
            file when the database is started and stored in memory. In
            contrast the data for cached tables is not read into memory until
            the table is accessed. Furthermore, only part of the data for each
            CACHED table is held in memory, allowing tables with more data
            than can be held in memory.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>When the database is shutdown in the normal way, all the
            data for MEMORY tables is written out to the disk. In comparison,
            the data in CACHED tables that has changed is written out during
            operation and at shutdown.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The size and capacity of the data cache for all the CACHED
            tables is configurable. This makes it possible to allow all the
            data in CACHED tables to be cached in memory. In this case, speed
            of access is good, but slightly slower than MEMORY tables.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>For normal applications it is recommended that MEMORY tables
            are used for small amounts of data, leaving CACHED tables for
            large data sets. For special applications in which speed is
            paramount and a large amount of free memory is available, MEMORY
            tables can be used for large tables as well.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Large Objects</title>

      <para>HyperSQL 2.0 supports dedicated storage and access to BLOB and
      CLOB objects. These objects can have huge sizes. BLOB or CLOB is
      specified as the type of a column of the table. Afterwards, rows can be
      inserted into the table using a PreparedStatement for efficient transfer
      of large LOB data to the database. In <glossterm>mem:</glossterm>
      catalogs, CLOB and BLOB data is stored in memory. In
      <glossterm>file:</glossterm> catalogs, this data is stored in a single
      separate file which has the extension *.lobs. The size of this file can
      grow to huge, terabyte figures.</para>

      <para>LOB data should be store in the database using a JDBC
      PreparedStatement object. The streaming methods send the LOB to the
      database in one operation as a binary or character stream. Inside the
      database, the disk space is allocated as needed and the data is saved as
      it is being received. LOB data should be retrieved from the database
      using a JDBC ResultSet method. When a streaming method is used to
      retrieve a LOB, it is retrieved in large chunks in a transparent manner.
      LOB data can also be stored by calling a JDBC method with String or
      byte[] argument, but these methods limit the size of the LOB that can be
      stored or retrieved.</para>

      <para>LOB data is not duplicated in the database when a lob is copied
      from one table to another. The disk space is reused when a LOB is
      deleted and is no longer contained in any table. This happens only at
      the time of a CHECKPOINT.</para>

      <para>By using a dedicated LOB store, HyperSQL achieves consistently
      high speeds (usually over 20MB / s) for both storage and retrieval of
      LOBs.</para>

      <para>There is an internal LOBS schema in the database to strore the
      id's, sizes and addresses of the LOBs (but not the actual LOBS) in a few
      system tables. This schema is stored in the database as MEMORY tables.
      Therefore the amount of JVM memory should be increased when more than
      tens of thousands of LOBs are stored in the database. If your database
      contains more than a few hundreds of thousands of LOBs and memory use
      becomes an issue, you can change one or all LOB schema tables to CACHED
      tables. See statements below:</para>

      <example>
        <title>Using CACHED tables for the LOB schema</title>

        <screen>  SET TABLE SYSTEM_LOBS.BLOCKS TYPE CACHED
  SET TABLE SYSTEM_LOBS.LOBS TYPE CACHED
  SET TABLE SYSTEM_LOBS.LOB_IDS TYPE CACHED
</screen>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Deployment context</title>

      <para>The files used for storing HyperSQL database data are all in the
      same directory. New files are always created and deleted by the database
      engine. Two simple principles must be observed:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The Java process running HyperSQL must have full privileges on
          the directory where the files are stored. This include create and
          delete privileges.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The file system must have enough spare room both for the
          'permanent' and 'temporary' files. The default maximum size of the
          *.log file is 50MB. The *.data file can grow to up to 16GB (more if
          the default has been increased). The .backup file can be up to the
          size of the *.data file. The *.lobs file can grow to several
          terabytes. The temporary files created at the time of a SHUTDOWN can
          be equal in size to the *.script file and the .data file.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Readonly Databases</title>

      <para>A <glossterm>file:</glossterm> catalog can be made readonly
      permanently, or it can be opened as readonly. To make the database
      readonly, the property, value pair, readonly=true can be added to the
      .properties file of the database.</para>

      <para>It is also possible to open a normal database as readonly. For
      this, the property can be included in the URL of the first connection to
      the database.</para>

      <para>There is another option which allows MEMORY tables to be writable,
      but without persisting the changes at SHUTDOWN. This option is activated
      with the property, value pair, <literal>files_readonly= true</literal>,
      which can be added to the .properties file of the database, or included
      in the URL of the first connection to the database. This option is
      useful for running application tests which operate on a predefined
      dataset.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>ACID, Persistence and Reliability</title>

    <para>HyperSQL 2.0 uses the same persistence mechanism as version 1.8, but
    with important enhancements. The code has proven reliable, as the last
    critical issue was fixed 2 years before the release of version 2.0.</para>

    <para>There are further enhancements in version 2.2</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>More extensive locking mechanism has been added to code to
        support multithreaded access.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Incremental backup (an internal mechanism for crash protection)
        allows fast checkpoint and shutdown.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>All files are synced at checkpoints and also just before
        closing.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The data file is enlarged in block increments</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The nio implementation has been improved</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Persistence relies on the JVM, the operating system, and the
    computer hardware. A database system like HSQLDB can perform millions of
    read and write operations in an hour. As system hardware and software can
    go wrong, it is impossible to achieve zero failure rate. Therefore regular
    backups are recommended. HyperSQL 2.2 has built-in database backup and
    restore features, discussed elsewhere in this chapter.</para>

    <para>A note regarding the nio implementation: This implementation applies
    only to CACHED table data in the .data file. Other files are not accessed
    via nio. There has been an issue with some JVM implementations of nio not
    releasing the file buffers after they were closed. HyperSQL uses a
    workaround which is recommended with Sun JVM's. This does not apply to
    other JVM's. In such environments, it is therefore recommended to test the
    CHECKPOINT DEFRAG operation and the shutting down and restarting the
    database inside the same Java process extensively with nio. Use of nio can
    be turned off if necessary.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Atomicity, Consistency, Isolation, Durability</title>

      <para>Atomicity means a transaction is either fails without changing the
      data, or succeeds. HyperSQL ensures atomicity both during operations and
      in the event of a system crash.</para>

      <para>Consistency means all the implicit and explicit integrity
      constraints are always enforced. HyperSQL always enforces the
      constraints and at the same time does not allow unenforceable
      constraints (illegal forms of CHECK constraints) to be created.</para>

      <para>Isolation means transactions do not interfere with each other.
      HyperSQL enforces isolation according to strict rules of the database
      isolation model (MVCC or LOCKS).</para>

      <para>Durability means a committed transaction is protected in case of a
      system crash. HyperSQL ensures durability according to the setting for
      WRITE DELAY MILLIS. A zero delay setting results in an
      FileDescriptor#sync() call each time a transaction commits. A timed
      delay means the FileDescriptor#sync() call is executed in the given
      intervals and only the last transactions committed in the interval may
      be lost. The sync() call is also made at all critical points, including
      when a file is about to be closed. All files Durability requires a
      reliable JVM and disk storage system that stores the data safely with a
      sync() call. In practice, many systems are generally reliable in this
      respect.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="deployment_backup-sect">
    <title>Backing Up Database Catalogs</title>

    <indexterm significance="preferred">
      <primary>backup</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>The database engine saves the files containing all the data in a
    file catalog when a shutdown takes place. It automatically recovers from
    an abnormal termination and preserves the data when the catalog is opened
    next time. In an ideal operating environment, where there is no OS crash,
    disk failure, bugs in code, etc. there would be no need regularly to
    backup a database. This is meant to say, the engine performs the routine
    shutdown procedure internally, therefore backing up catalogs is an
    insurance policy against all sorts of misadventure that are not under the
    control of the database engine.</para>

    <para>The data for each catalog consists of up to 5 files in the same
    directory with the endings such as <literal>*.properties</literal>,
    <literal>*.script</literal>, etc., as detailed in previous
    chapters.</para>

    <simpara>HyperSQL 2.0 includes commands to backup the database files into
    a single <literal>.tar</literal> or <literal>.tar.gz</literal> file
    archive. The backup can be performed by a command given in a JDBC session
    if the target database catalog is running, or on the command-line if the
    target catalog has been shutdown.</simpara>

    <section>
      <title>Making Online Backups</title>

      <simpara>To back up a running catalog, obtain a JDBC connection and
      issue a <literal>BACKUP DATABASE</literal> command in SQL. In its most
      simple form, the command format below will backup the database as a
      single <literal>.tar.gz</literal> file to the given directory.</simpara>

      <programlisting>  BACKUP DATABASE TO &lt;directory name&gt; BLOCKING</programlisting>

      <simpara>The <emphasis>directory name</emphasis> must end with a slash
      to distinguish it as a directory, and the whole string must be in single
      quotes like so: <literal>'subdir/nesteddir/'</literal>.</simpara>

      <simpara>See the next section under Statements for details about the
      command and its options. See the sections below about restoring a
      backup.</simpara>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Making Offline Backups</title>

      <para>To back up an offline catalog, the catalog must be in shut down
      state. You will run a Java command like this <example>
          <title>Offline Backup Example</title>

          <screen>  java -cp path/to/hsqldb.jar org.hsqldb.lib.tar.DbBackup --save  \
  tar/path.tar db/base/path</screen>
        </example>where <filename>tar/path.tar</filename> is a file path to
      the <literal>*.tar</literal> or <literal>*.tar.gz</literal> file to be
      created, and <filename>db/base/path</filename> is the file path to the
      catalog file base name (in same fashion as in
      <varname>server.database.*</varname> settings and JDBC URLs with catalog
      type <glossterm>file:</glossterm>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Examining Backups</title>

      <para>You can list the contents of backup tar files with
      <classname>DbBackup</classname> on your operating system command line,
      or with any Pax-compliant tar or pax client (this includes GNU tar),
      <example>
          <title>Listing a Backup with DbBackup</title>

          <screen>  java -cp path/to/hsqldb.jar org.hsqldb.lib.tar.DbBackup --list tar/path.tar</screen>
        </example>You can also give regular expressions at the end of the
      command line if you are only interested in some of the file entries in
      the backup. Note that these are real regular expressions, not shell
      globbing patterns, so you would use <literal>.+script</literal> to match
      entries ending in "script", not <literal>*script</literal>.</para>

      <simpara>You can examine the contents of the backup in their entirety by
      restoring the backup, as explained in the following section, to a
      temporary directory.</simpara>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Restoring a Backup</title>

      <para>You use <classname>DbBackup</classname> on your operating system
      command line to restore a catalog from a backup. <example>
          <title>Restoring a Backup with DbBackup</title>

          <screen>  java -cp path/to/hsqldb.jar org.hsqldb.lib.tar.DbBackup --extract  \
      tar/path.tar db/dir</screen>
        </example>where <filename>tar/path.tar</filename> is a file path to
      the *.tar or *.tar.gz file to be read, and <filename>db/dir</filename>
      is the target directory to extract the catalog files into. Note that
      <filename>db/dir</filename> specifies a directory path, without the
      catalog file base name. The files will be created with the names stored
      in the tar file (and which you can see as described in the preceding
      section).</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Encrypted Databases</title>

    <para>HyperSQL supports encrypted databases. Encryption services use the
    Java Cryptography Extensions (JCE) and uses the ciphers installed with the
    JRE. HyperSQL itself does not contain any cryptography code.</para>

    <para>Three elements are involved in specifying the encryption method and
    key. A cipher, together with its configuration is identified by a string
    which includes the name of the cipher and optional parameters. A provider
    is the fully qualified class name of the cipher provider. A key is
    represented as a hexadecimal string.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Creating and Accessing an Encrypted Database</title>

      <para>First, a key must be created for the desired cipher and
      configuration. This is done by calling the function CRYPT_KEY(&lt;cipher
      spec&gt;, &lt;provider&gt;). If the default provider (the built-in JVM
      ciphers) is used, then NULL should be specified as the provider. The
      CRYPT_KEY function returns a hexadecimal key. The function call can be
      made in any HyperSQL database, so long as the provider class is on the
      classpath. This key can be used to create a new encrypted database.
      Calls to this function always return different keys, based on a
      generated random values.</para>

      <para>As an example, a call to CRYPT_KEY('Blowfish', null) returned the
      string, '604a6105889da65326bf35790a923932'. To create a new database,
      the URL below is used:</para>

      <para><literal>jdbc:hsqldb:file:&lt;database
      path&gt;;crypt_key=604a6105889da65326bf35790a923932;crypt_type=blowfish</literal></para>

      <para>The third property name is crypt_provider. This is specified only
      when the provider is not the default provider.</para>

      <para>HyperSQL works with any symmetric cipher that may be available
      from the JVM.</para>

      <para>The files that are encrypted include the .script, .data, .backup
      and .log files. The .lobs file is not encrypted by default. The property
      crypt_lobs=true must be specified to encrypt the .lobs file.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Speed Considerations</title>

      <para>General operations on an encrypted database are performed the same
      as with any database. However, some operations are significantly slower
      than with the equivalent cleartext database. With MEMORY tables, there
      is no difference to the speed of SELECT statements, but data change
      statements are slower. With CACHED tables, the speed of all statements
      is slower.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Security Considerations</title>

      <para>Security considerations for encrypted databases have been
      discussed at length in HSQLDB discussion groups. Development team
      members have commented that encryption is not a panacea for all security
      needs. The following issues should be taken into account:</para>

      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Encrypted files are relatively safe in transport, but
            because databases contain many repeated values and words,
            especially known tokens such as CREATE, INSERT, etc., breaking the
            encryption of a database may be simpler than an unknown
            file.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Only the files are encrypted, not the memory image. Poking
            into computer memory, while the database is open, will expose the
            contents of the database.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>HyperSQL is open source. Someone who has the key, can
            compile and use a modified version of the program that saves a
            full cleartext dump of an encrypted database</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>Therefore encryption is generally effective only when
      the users who have access to the crypt key are trusted.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Monitoring Database Operations</title>

    <para>Database operations can be monitored at different levels using
    internal HyperSQL capabilities or add-ons.</para>

    <section>
      <title>External Statement Level Monitoring</title>

      <para>Statement level monitoring allows you to gather statistics about
      executed statements. HyperSQL is supported by the monitoring tool JAMon
      (Java Application Monitor). JAMon is currently developed as the
      SourceForge project, jamonapi.</para>

      <para>JAMon works at the JDBC level. It can monitor and gather
      statistics on different types of executed statements or other JDBC
      calls.</para>

      <para>Early versions of JAMon were developed with HSQLDB and had to be
      integrated into HSQLDB at code level. The latest versions can be added
      on as a proxy in a much simpler fashion.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Internal Statement Level Monitoring</title>

      <para>The internally-generated, individual sql log for the database can
      be enabled with the <literal>SET DATABASE EVENT LOG SQL LEVEL</literal>
      s tatement, described in the next section. As all the executed
      statements are logged, there is an impact on speed. So you should only
      use this for debugging. Two levels of sql logging are supported.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Internal Event Monitoring</title>

      <para>HyperSQL can log important internal events of the engine. These
      events occur during the operation of the engine, and are not always
      coupled with the exact type of statement being executed. Normal events
      such as opening and closing of files, or errors such as OutOfMemory
      conditions are examples of logged events.</para>

      <para>HyperSQL supports two methods of logging. One method is specific
      to the individual database and is managed internally by HyperSQL. The
      other method is specific to JVM and is managed by a logging
      framework.</para>

      <para>The internally-generated, individual log for the database can be
      enabled with the <literal>SET DATABASE EVENT LOG LEVEL</literal>
      statement, described in the next section. This method of logging is very
      useful for desktop application deployment, as it provides an ongoing
      record of database operations.</para>

      <para>HyperSQL also supports log4J and JDK logging. The same event
      information that is passed to the internal log, is passed to external
      logging frameworks. These frameworks are configured outside HyperSQL.
      The log messages include the string "hsqldb.db." followed by the unique
      id (a 16 character string) of the database that generated the message,
      so they can be identified in a multi-database server context.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Server Operation Monitoring</title>

      <para>A Server or WebServer instance can be started with the property
      server.silent=false. This causes all the connections and their executed
      statements to be printed to stdout as the statements are submitted to
      the server.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Database Security</title>

    <para>HyperSQL has extensive security features which are implemented at
    different levels and covered in different chapters of this guide.</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The server can use SSL and IP address access control lists. See
        the <link endterm="listeners-title"
        xlink:href="#listeners-chapt"></link> chapter.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>You can define a system property to stop the database engine
        accessing the Java static functions that are on the classpath, apart
        from a limited set that you allow. See Securing Access to Classes in
        the <link endterm="sqlroutines-title"
        xlink:href="#sqlroutines-chapt"></link> chapter.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>You can define a system property to allow access to files on the
        file system outside the database directory and its children. This
        access is only necessary if you use TEXT tables. See the <link
        endterm="texttables-title" xlink:href="#texttables-chapt"></link>
        chapter.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The database files can be encrypted. Discussed in this
        chapter.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Within the database, the DBA privileges are required for system
        and maintenance jobs.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>You can define users and roles and grant them access on
        different database objects. Each user has a password and is granted a
        set of privileges. See the <link endterm="accesscontrol-title"
        xlink:href="#accesscontrol-chapt"></link> chapter.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>You can define a password complexity check function for new and
        changed passwords. This is covered below under Authentication
        Settings.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>You can use external authentication instead of internally stored
        password to authenticate users for each database. This is covered
        below under Authentication Settings.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>HyperSQL security is multi-layered and avoids any loopholes to
    circumvent security. It is however the user's responsibility to enable the
    required level of security.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Security Defaults</title>

      <para>The default setting are generally adequate for most embedded use
      of the database or for servers on the host that are accessed from the
      same machine. For servers accessed within a network, and especially for
      those accessed from outside the network, additional security settings
      must be used.</para>

      <para>The default settings for server and web server do not use SSL or
      IP access control lists. These features are enabled programatically, or
      with the properties used to start the server.</para>

      <para>The default settings allow a database user with the DBA role or
      with schema creation role to access static functions on the classpath.
      You can disable this feature or limit it to specific classes and
      methods. This can be done programatically or by setting a system
      property when you start a server.</para>

      <para>If access to specific static functions is granted, then these
      functions must be considered as part of the database program and checked
      for any security flaws before inclusion in the classpath.</para>

      <para>The default settings do not allow a user to access files outside
      the database directory. This access is for TEXT table source files. You
      can override this programatically or with a system property when you
      start a server.</para>

      <para>The encryption of database file does not utilise any user-supplied
      information for encryption keys. This level of security is outside the
      realm of users and passwords.</para>

      <para>The first user for a new database has the DBA role. This user name
      need not be SA. The name of the first DBA user and its password can be
      specified when the database is created by the first connection to the
      database. These settings are then stored in the database.</para>

      <para>The initial user with the DBA role should be used for admin
      purposes only. At least one additional role should be created for normal
      databse use in the application and at least one additional user should
      be created and granted this role. The new role should not be given the
      DBA role. It can be given the CREATE_SCHEMA role, which allows it to
      create and access multiple schemas. Alternatively, the user with the DBA
      role can create the schemas and their objects and then grant specific
      privileges on the objects to the non-DBA role.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Authentication Control</title>

      <para>Authentication is the mechanism that determines if a user can
      access the database at all. Once authentication is performed, the
      authorization mechanism is used to determine which database objects the
      particular user can access. The default authentication mechanism is
      password authentication. Each user is created with a password, which is
      stored in the database and checked each time a new database connection
      is created.</para>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>password complexity</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Password Complexity
      Check</emphasis></simpara>

      <para>HyperSQL allows you to define a function that checks the quality
      of the passwords defined in the database. The passwords are stored in
      the database. Each time a user connects, the user's name and password
      are checked against the stored list of users and passwords. The
      connection attempt is rejected if there is no match.</para>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>external authentication</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">External
      Authentication</emphasis></simpara>

      <para>You can use an external authentication mechanism instead of the
      internal authentication mechanism. HyperSQL allows you to define a
      function that checks the combination of database unique name, user name,
      and password for each connection attempt. The function can use external
      resources to authenticate the user. For example, a directory server may
      be used. The password may be ignored if the external resource can verify
      the user's credential without it.</para>

      <para>You can override external authentication for a user with the ALTER
      USER statement. See the <link endterm="accesscontrol-title"
      xlink:href="#accesscontrol-chapt"></link> chapter</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Compatibility with Other RDBMS</title>

    <para>HyperSQL is used more than any other database engine for application
    testing and development targeted at other databases. Over the years, this
    usage resulted in developers finding and reporting many obscure bugs in
    HyperSQL, which have all been fixed in the latest version. Also, HyperSQL
    2.0 has been written to the SQL Standard and avoids the traps caused by
    superficial imitation of existing RDBMS.</para>

    <para>HyperSQL has many property settings that relax conformance to the
    Standard in order to allow compatibility with other RDBMS, without
    breaking the core integrity of the database. These properties are modified
    with SET DATABASE SQL statements described in the SQL Conformance Settings
    section of this chapter</para>

    <para>The SQL Standard has existed since 1989 and has been expanded over
    the years in several revisions. Also, the X-Open specification has defined
    a number of SQL functions which are implemented by most RDBMS.</para>

    <para>Each RDBMS supports additional functions that are not covered by the
    standard. Some RDBMS use non-standard syntax for some operations.
    Fortunately, most popular RDBMS products have introduced better
    compatibility with the Standard in their recent versions, but there are
    still some portability issues. HyperSQL overcomes the potability issues
    using these strategies</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>An extensive set of functions cover the SQL Standard, X-Open,
        and most of the useful functions that other RDBMS may support.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Database properties, which can be specified on the URL or as SQL
        statements, relax conformance to the Standard in order to allow
        non-standard comparisons and assignments allowed by other
        RDBMS.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Specific SQL syntax compatibility modes allow syntax and type
        names that are supported by some popular RDBMS.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>User-defined types and functions, including aggregate functions,
        allow any type or function that is supported by some RDBMS to be
        defined and used.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>In the future, the supported compatibility modes with other RDBMS
    will be expanded further.</para>

    <section>
      <title>PostgreSQL Compatibility</title>

      <para>PostgreSQL is fairly compatible with the Standard, but uses some
      non-standard features.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use <literal>&lt;set database sql syntax PGS
          statement&gt;</literal> to enable the PostgreSQL's non-standard
          features. References to SERIAL, BIGSERIAL and TEXT data types, as
          well as sequence functions, are translated into HSQLDB
          equivalents.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Use MVCC if your application is multi-user</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>PostgreSQL functions are generally supported</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>For identity columns, PostgreSQL uses a non-standard linkage
          with an external identity sequence. In most cases, this can be
          converted to <literal>GENERATED BY DEFAULT AS IDENTITY</literal>. In
          those cases where the identity sequence needs to be shared by
          multiple tables, you can use a new HyperSQL 2.2 feature
          <literal>GENERATED BY DEFAULT AS SEQUENCE &lt;sequence
          name&gt;</literal>, which is the equivalent of the PostgreSQL
          implementation.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>In CREATE TABLE statements, the SERIAL and BIGSERIAL types are
          translated into INTEGER or BIGINT, with <literal>GENERATED BY
          DEFAULT AS IDENTITY</literal>. Usage of DEFAULT NEXTVAL(&lt;sequence
          name&gt;) is supported so long as the <literal>&lt;sequence
          name&gt;</literal> refers to an existing sequence. This usage is
          translated into <literal>GENERATED BY DEFAULT AS SEQUENCE
          &lt;sequence name&gt;</literal>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>In SELECT and other statements, the
          <literal>NEXTVAL(&lt;sequence name&gt;)</literal> and
          <literal>LASTVAL()</literal> functions are supported and translated
          into HyperSQL's <literal>NEXT VALUE FOR &lt;sequence
          name&gt;</literal> and <literal>IDENTITY()</literal>
          expressions.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>PostgreSQL uses a non-standard expression, <literal>SELECT 'A
          Test String'</literal> to return a single row table. The standard
          form is <literal>VALUES('A Test String')</literal>. In PGS syntax
          mode, this type of SELECT is supported.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>HyperSQL supports SQL Standard ARRAY types. PostgreSQL also
          supports this, but not entirely according to the Standard.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>SQL routines are poratable, but some syntax elements are
          different and require changes.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You may need to use <literal>SET DATABASE SQL TDC { DELETE |
          UPDATE }</literal> FALSE statements. </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>MySQL Compatibility</title>

      <para>MySQL had many incompatibilities with the Standard. The latest
      versions have introduced much greater compatibly, but some of these
      features have to be turned on via properties. You should therefore check
      the current Standard compatibility settings of your MySQL database and
      use the available HyperSQL properties to achieve closer results. If you
      avoid the few anti-Standard features of MySQL you can port your
      databases to HyperSQL.</para>

      <para>HyperSQL does not have the following non-standard limitations of
      MySQL.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Win HyperSQL, an UPDATE statement can update UNIQUE and
          PRIMARY KEY columns of a table without causing an exception due to
          temporary violation of constraints. These constraints are checked at
          the end of execution, therefore there is no need for an ORDER BY
          clause in an UPDATE statement.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>MySQL foreign key constraints are not enforced by the default
          MyISAM engine. Be aware of the possibility of data being rejected by
          HyperSQL due to these constraints.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>With HyperSQL INSERT or UPDATE statements either succeed or
          fail due to constraint violation. MySQL has the non-standard IGNORE
          overrides to ignore violations, which is not accepted by
          HyperSQL.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Unlike MySQL, HyperSQL allows you to modify a table with an
          INSERT, UPDATE or DELETE statement which selects from the same table
          in a subquery.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Follow the guidelines below for converting MySQL databases and
      applications.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use <literal>&lt;set database sql syntax MYS
          statement&gt;</literal> to enable support for AUTO_INCREMENT and
          TEXT data types. These type definitions are translated into HSQLDB
          equivalents.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Use MVCC with <literal>&lt;set database transaction control
          statement&gt;</literal> if your application is multi-user.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Avoid storing invalid values, for example invalid dates such
          as '0000-00-00' or '2001-00-00' which are rejected by
          HyperSQL.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Avoid the MySQL feature that trims spaces at the end of CHAR
          values.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>In MySQL, a database is the same as a schema. In HyperSQL
          several schemas can exist in the same database and accessed
          transparently. In addition a HyperSQL server supports multiple
          separate databases.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>In MySQL, older, non-standard, forms of database object name
          case-sensitivity make is difficult to port applications. Use the
          latest form which encloses case-sensitive names in double
          quotes.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>MySQL functions are generally supported, including
          GROUP_CONCAT.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>For fine control over type conversion, check the settings for
          <literal>&lt;set database sql convert truncate
          statement&gt;</literal></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you use concatenation of possibly NULL values in your
          select statements, you may need to change the setting with the
          <literal>&lt;set database sql concat nulls
          statement&gt;</literal></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>MySQL supports most SQL Standard types (except INTERVAL
          types), as well as non-standard types, which are also supported by
          HyperSQL. Supported types include SMALLINT, INT, BIGINT, DOUBLE,
          FLOAT, DECIMAL, NUMERIC, VARCHAR, CHAR, BINARY, VARBINARY, BLOB,
          DATE, TIMESTAMP (all Standard SQL) and TINYINT, DATETIME (non
          Standard).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>MySQL uses a non-standard expression, <literal>SELECT 'A Test
          String'</literal> to return a single row table. The standard form is
          <literal>VALUES('A Test String')</literal>. In MYS syntax mode, this
          type of SELECT is supported.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>SQL user-defined function and procedure syntax is very similar
          to SQL Standard syntax. A few changes may still be required.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Firebird Compatibility</title>

      <para>Firebird generally follows the SQL Standard. Applications can be
      ported to HyperSQL without difficulty.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Apache Derby Compatibility</title>

      <para>Apache Derby supports a smaller subset of the SQL Standard
      compared to HyperSQL. Applications can be ported to HyperSQL without
      difficulty.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use MVCC with <literal>&lt;set database transaction control
          statement&gt;</literal> if your application is multi-user.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>HyperSQL supports Java language functions and stored
          procedures with the standard syntax, which is similar to the way
          Derby supports these features.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Oracle Compatibility</title>

      <para>Recent versions of Oracle support Standard SQL syntax for outer
      joins and many other operations. In addition, HyperSQL features a
      setting to support Oracle syntax and semantics for the most widely used
      non-standard features.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use <literal>&lt;set database sql syntax ORA
          statement&gt;</literal> to enable support for some non-standard
          syntax of Oracle.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Use MVCC with <literal>&lt;set database transaction control
          statement&gt;</literal> if your application is multi-user.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Fine control over MVCC deadlock avoidance is provided by the
          <literal>&lt;set database transaction rollback on conflict
          statement&gt;</literal> and the corresonding
          <literal>hsqldb.tx_conflict_rollback</literal> connection
          property.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If your application relies on Oracle behaviour for nulls in
          multi-column UNIQUE constraints, use <literal>&lt;set database sql
          unique nulls statement&gt;</literal> to change the default.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you use the non-standard concatenation of possibly NULL
          values in your select statements, you may need to change the setting
          for <literal>&lt;set database sql concat nulls
          statement&gt;</literal>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Many Oracle functions are supported, including no-arg
          functions such as SYSDATE and SYSTIMESTAMP and more complex ones
          such as TO_DATE and TO_CHAR.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Non-standard data type definitions such as NUMBER, VARCHAR2,
          NVARCHAR2, BINARY_DOUBLE, BINARY_FLOAT, LONG, RAW are translated
          into the closest HyperSQL / SQL Standard equivalent in ORA
          mode.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The DATE type is interpreted as TIMESTAMP(0) in ORA syntax
          mode.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The DUAL table and the expressions, ROWNUM, CURRVAL, NEXTVAL
          are supported in ORA syntax mode.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>HyperSQL natively supports operations involving datetime and
          interval values. These features are based on the SQL
          Standard.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Many subtle automatic type conversions, syntax refinements and
          other common features are supported.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>SQL routines are generally portable, but some changes may be
          required.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>DB2 Compatibility</title>

      <para>DB2 is highly compatible with the SQL Standard (except its lack of
      support for the INFORMATION_SCHEMA). Applications can be ported to
      HyperSQL without difficulty.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use <literal>&lt;set database sql syntax DB2
          statement&gt;</literal> to enable support for some non-standard
          syntax of DB2.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Use MVCC with <literal>&lt;set database transaction control
          statement&gt;</literal> if your application is multi-user.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>HyperSQL supports almost the entire syntax of DB2 together
          with many of the functions. Even local temporary tables using the
          SESSION psudo schema are supported.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The DB2 binary type definition FOR BIT DATA, as well as empty
          definition of column default values are supported in DB2 syntax
          mode.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Many DB2 functions are supported.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The DUAL table and the expressions, ROWNUM, CURRVAL, NEXTVAL
          are supported in DB2 syntax mode.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>SQL routines are highly portable with minimal change.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>MS SQLServer and Sybase Compatibility</title>

      <para>SQLServer has some incompatibilities with the Standard syntax. The
      most significant is the use of square brackets instead of double quotes
      for case-sensitive column names.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use <literal>&lt;set database sql syntax MSS
          statement&gt;</literal> to enable support for the
          <literal>CONVERT(&lt;type definition&gt;, &lt;expression)</literal>
          function with switched order of arguments</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Use MVCC with <literal>&lt;set database transaction control
          statement&gt;</literal> if your application is multi-user.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you use the non-standard concatenation of possibly NULL
          values in your select statements, you may need to change the setting
          for &lt;set database sql concat nulls statement&gt;.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>HyperSQL supports + for string concatenation. It also supports
          many functions supported by these dialects.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>SQLServer uses a non-standard expression, <literal>SELECT 'A
          Test String'</literal> to return a single row table. The standard
          form is <literal>VALUES('A Test String')</literal>. In MSS syntax
          mode, this type of SELECT is supported.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>SQL routines need quite a lot of changes.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Statements</title>

    <para>System level statements are listed in this section. Statements that
    begin with SET DATABASE or SET FILES are for properties that have an
    effect on the normal operation of HyperSQL. The effects of these
    statements are also discussed in different chapters.</para>

    <section>
      <title>System Operations</title>

      <para>These statements perform a system level action.</para>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SHUTDOWN</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SHUTDOWN</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>shutdown statement</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;shutdown statement&gt; ::= SHUTDOWN [IMMEDIATELY |
      COMPACT | SCRIPT]</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>Shutdown the database. If the optional qualifier is not used, a
      normal SHUTDOWN is performed. A normal SHUTDOWN ensures all data is
      saved correctly and the database opens without delay on next
      use.</simpara>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>SHUTDOWN</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Normal shutdown saves all the database files, then deletes
            the .log file (and the .backup file in the default mode). The
            database opens without delay on next used.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>SHUTDOWN IMMEDIATELY</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Saves the *.log file and closes the database files. This is
            the quickest form of shutdown. This command should not be used as
            the routine method of closing the database, because when the
            database is accessed next time, it may take a long time to
            start.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>SHUTDOWN COMPACT</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This is similar to normal SHUTDOWN, but reduces the *.data
            file to its minimum size. It can take much longer than normal
            SHUTDOWN. This shouldn't be used as routine.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>SHUTDOWN SCRIPT</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This is similar to SHUTDOWN COMPACT, but it does not rewrite
            the <literal>*.data</literal> and text table files. After SHUTDOWN
            SCRIPT, only the <literal>*.script</literal> and
            <literal>*.properties</literal> files remain. At the next startup,
            these files are processed and the <literal>*.data</literal> file
            is created if there are cached tables. This command in effect
            performs part of the job of SHUTDOWN COMPACT, leaving the other
            part to be performed automatically at the next startup.</para>

            <para>This command produces a full script of the database which
            can be edited for special purposes prior to the next
            startup.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>BACKUP DATABASE</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">BACKUP DATABASE</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>backup database statement</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;backup database statement&gt; ::= BACKUP DATABASE
      TO &lt;file path&gt; {SCRIPT | [NOT] COMPRESSED}
      BLOCKING</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>Backup the database to specified <literal>&lt;file
      path&gt;</literal> for archiving purposes.</simpara>

      <simpara>The <literal>&lt;file path&gt;</literal> can be in two forms.
      If the <literal>&lt;file path&gt;</literal> ends with a forward slash,
      it specifies a directory. In this case, an automatic name for the
      archive is generated that includes the date, time and the base name of
      the database. The database is backed up to this archive file in the
      specified directory. If the <literal>&lt;file path&gt;</literal> does
      not end with a forward slash, it specifies a user-defined file name for
      the backup archive. The archive is in tar, gzip format depending on
      whether it is compressed or not.</simpara>

      <simpara>The SCRIPT option is not currently supported. If SCRIPT is
      specified, the backup will consist of two files, a
      <literal>*.properties</literal> file and a <literal>*.script</literal>
      file, which contain all the data and settings of the database. These
      files are not compressed.</simpara>

      <simpara>If COMPRESSED or NOT COMPRESSED is specified, the backup
      consists of the current snapshot of database files. During backup, a
      CHECKPOINT command is silently executed.</simpara>

      <simpara>The qualifier, BLOCKING, means all database operations are
      suspended during backup.</simpara>

      <simpara>The HyperSQL jar also contains a program that creates an
      archive of an offline database. It also contains a program to expand an
      archive into database files. These programs are documented in this
      chapter under Backing up Database Catalogs.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>CHECKPOINT</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">CHECKPOINT</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>checkpoint statement</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;checkpoint statement&gt; ::= CHECKPOINT
      [DEFRAG]</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>Closes the database files, rewrites the script file, deletes
      the log file and opens the database. If <literal>DEFRAG</literal> is
      specified, also shrinks the <literal>*.data</literal> file to its
      minumum size. Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SCRIPT</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SCRIPT</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>script statement</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;script statement&gt; ::= SCRIPT [&lt;file
      name&gt;]</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>Returns a script containing SQL statements that define the
      database, its users, and its schema objects. If <literal>&lt;file
      name&gt;</literal> is not specified, the statements are returned in a
      ResultSet, with each row containing an SQL statement. No data statements
      are included in this form. The optional file name is a single-quoted
      string. If <literal>&lt;file name&gt;</literal> is specified, then the
      script is written to the named file. In this case, all the data in all
      tables of the database is included in the script as INSERT
      statements.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Database Settings</title>

      <simpara>These statements change the database settings.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET DATABASE COLLATION</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET DATABASE
      COLLATION</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set database collation statement</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set database collation statement&gt; ::= SET
      DATABASE COLLATION &lt;collation name&gt;</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>Each database can have its own collation. Sets the collation
      from the set of collations supported by HyperSQL. Once this command has
      been issued, the database can be opened in any JVM and will retain its
      collation.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET DATABASE DEFAULT RESULT MEMORY ROWS</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET DATABASE DEFAULT RESULT MEMORY
      ROWS</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set database default result memory rows
      statement</emphasis><literal> </literal></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set database default result memory rows&gt; ::=
      SET DATABASE DEFAULT RESULT MEMORY ROWS &lt;unsigned integer
      literal&gt;</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>Sets the maximum number of rows of each result set and internal
      temporary table that is held in memory. Temporary tables includes views,
      schema-based and session-based TEMPORARY tables, transient tables for
      subqueries, and INFORMATION_SCHEMA tables.</simpara>

      <simpara>This setting applies to all sessions. Individual sessions can
      change the value with the <literal>SET SESSION RESULT MEMORY
      ROWS</literal> statement. The default is 0, meaning all result sets are
      held in memory.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>hsqldb.result_max_memory_rows</literal>.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET DATABASE DEFAULT TABLE TYPE</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET DATABASE DEFAULT TABLE
      TYPE</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set database default table type
      statement</emphasis><literal> </literal></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set database default table type&gt; ::= SET
      DATABASE DEFAULT TABLE TYPE { CACHED | MEMORY }</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>Sets the type of table created when the next CREATE TABLE
      statement is executed. The default is MEMORY.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>hsqldb.default_table_type</literal>.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET DATABASE EVENT LOG LEVEL</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET DATABASE EVENT LOG
      LEVEL</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set database event log level
      statement</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set database event log level&gt; ::= SET DATABASE
      EVENT LOG [ SQL ] LEVEL { 0 | 1 | 2 | 3 }</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>When the SQL option is not used, this statement sets the amount
      of information logged in the internal, database-specific event log.
      Level 0 means no log. Level 1 means only important (error) events. Level
      2 means more events, including both important and less important
      (normal) events. Level 3 includes even more details. For readonly and
      <glossterm>mem:</glossterm> databases, if the level is set above 0, the
      log messages are directed to stderr.</simpara>

      <simpara>The events are logged in a file with the extension
      <literal>.app.log</literal> alongside the main database files.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>hsqldb.applog</literal>.</simpara>

      <simpara>When the SQL option is used, this statement logs the SQL
      statements as they are executed. Each log line contains the timestamp
      and the session number, followed by the SQL statement and JDBC arguments
      if any.</simpara>

      <simpara>Levels 1 and 2 are supported. Level 1 only logs commits and
      rollbacks, while Level 2 logs all statements.</simpara>

      <simpara>The logged lines are stored in a file with the extension
      <literal>.sql.log</literal> alongside the main database files.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>hsqldb.sqllog</literal>.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET DATABASE GC</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET DATABASE GC</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set database gc statement</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set database gc statement&gt; ::= SET DATABASE GC
      &lt;unsigned integer literal&gt;</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>An optional property which forces calls to <literal>System.gc()
      </literal>after the specified number of row operations. The default
      value for this property is 0, which means no System.gc() calls. Usual
      values for this property range from 10000 depending on the system and
      the memory allocation. This property may be useful in some in-process
      deployments, especially with older JVM implementations.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET DATABASE UNIQUE NAME</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET DATABASE UNIQUE
      NAME</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set database unique name</emphasis><literal>
      </literal></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set database unique name statement&gt; ::= SET
      DATABASE UNIQUE NAME &lt;identifier&gt;</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>Each HyperSQL catalog (database) has an engine-generated
      internal name. This name is a 16 character long string, beginning with
      HSQLDB and based on the time of creation of the database. The name is
      used for the log events that are sent to external logging frameworks.
      The new name must be exactly 16 characters long with no
      spaces.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET DATABASE TRANSACTION CONTROL</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET DATABASE TRANSACTION
      CONTROL</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set database transaction control
      statement</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set database transaction control statement&gt; ::=
      SET DATABASE TRANSACTION CONTROL { LOCKS | MVLOCKS | MVCC
      }</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>Set the concurrency control system for the database. It can be
      issued only when all sessions have been committed or rolled back. This
      command and its modes is discussed in the <link endterm="sessions-title"
      xlink:href="#sqlroutines-chapt"></link> chapter.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>hsqldb.tx</literal>.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET DATABASE TRANSACTION ROLLBACK ON CONFLICT</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET DATABASE TRANSACTION ROLLBACK ON
      CONFLICT</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set database transaction rollback on conflict
      statement</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set database transaction rollback on conflict
      statement&gt; ::= SET DATABASE TRANSACTION ROLLBACK ON CONFLICT { TRUE |
      FALSE }</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>When a transaction deadlock or conflict is about to happen, the
      current transaction is rolled back and an exception is raised. When this
      property is set false, the transaction is not rolled back. Only the
      latest statement that would cause the conflict is undone and an
      exception is raised. The property should not be changed unless the
      application can quickly perform an alternative statement and complete
      the transaction. It is provided for compatibility with other database
      engines which do not roll back the transaction upon deadlock. This
      command is also discussed in the <link endterm="sessions-title"
      xlink:href="#sqlroutines-chapt"></link> chapter.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>hsqldb.tx_conflict_rollback</literal>.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET DATABASE DEFAULT ISOLATION LEVEL</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET DATABASE DEFAULT ISOLATION
      LEVEL</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set database default isolation level
      statement</emphasis><literal> </literal></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set database default isolation level&gt; ::= SET
      DATABASE DEFAULT ISOLATION LEVEL { READ COMMITTED | SERIALIZABLE
      }</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>Sets the transaction isolation level for new sessions. The
      default is READ COMMITTED. Each session can also set its isolation
      level.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>hsqldb.tx_level</literal>.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET DATABASE TEXT TABLE DEFAULTS</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET DATABASE TEXT TABLE
      DEFAULTS</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set database text table defaults
      statement</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set database text table defaults statement&gt; ::=
      SET DATABASE TEXT TABLE DEFAULTS &lt;character
      literal&gt;</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>An optional property to override default text table settings.
      The string literal has the same format as the string used for setting
      the data source of a text table, but without the file name. See the
      <link endterm="texttables-title" xlink:href="#texttables-chapt"></link>
      chapter.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>SQL Conformance Settings</title>

      <simpara>These statements modify the level of conformance to the SQL
      Standard in different areas. The settings that specify SQL SYNTAX are
      for compatibility with other database engines and are FALSE by default.
      For all the rest of the settings, TRUE means better conformance to the
      Standard (unless the Standard defines the behaviour as implementation
      dependent). The default value of a few of these settings is FALSE, due
      to widespread non-conforming statements that are already in use in user
      applications or statements generated by object relational tools. So long
      as it is practical, it is best to set the non-conforming defaults to
      TRUE in order to improve the quality of the database
      application.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET DATABASE SQL SIZE</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET DATABASE SQL
      SIZE</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set database sql size statement</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set database sql size statement&gt; ::= SET
      DATABASE SQL SIZE { TRUE | FALSE }</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>Enable or disable enforcement of column sizes for CHAR and
      VARCHAR columns. The default is TRUE, meaning table definition must
      contain <literal>VARCHAR(n)</literal> instead of
      <literal>VARCHAR</literal>.</simpara>

      <simpara>SQL Standard requires enforcement.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>sql.enforce_size</literal>.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET DATABASE SQL NAMES</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET DATABASE SQL
      NAMES</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set database sql names statement</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set database sql names statement&gt; ::= SET
      DATABASE SQL NAMES { TRUE | FALSE }</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>Enable or disable full enforcement of the rule that prevents
      SQL keywords being used for database object names such as columns and
      tables. The default is <literal>FALSE</literal>, meaning
      disabled.</simpara>

      <simpara>SQL Standard requires enforcement. <emphasis>It is better to
      enable this check, in order to improve the quality and correctness of
      SQL statements.</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>sql.enforce_names</literal>.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET DATABASE SQL REFERENCES</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET DATABASE SQL
      REFERENCES</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set database sql references
      statement</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set database sql references statement&gt; ::= SET
      DATABASE SQL REFERENCES { TRUE | FALSE }</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>This command can enable or disable full enforcement of the rule
      that prevents ambiguous column references in SQL statements (usually
      SELECT statements). A column reference is ambiguous when it is not
      qualified by a table name or table alias and can refer to more than one
      column in a JOIN list.</simpara>

      <simpara>The property is <literal>FALSE</literal> by default.</simpara>

      <simpara>SQL Standard requires enforcement. <emphasis>It is better to
      enable this check, in order to improve the quality and correctness of
      SQL statements.</emphasis> When false, the first matching table is used
      to resolve the column reference.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>sql.enforce_refs</literal>.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET DATABASE SQL TYPES</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET DATABASE SQL
      TYPES</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set database sql types statement</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set database sql types statement&gt; ::= SET
      DATABASE SQL TYPES { TRUE | FALSE }</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>This command can enable or disable full enforcement of the
      rules that prevents illegal type conversions and parameters or nulls
      without type in SQL statements (usually SELECT statements). For example
      an INTEGER column or a DATE column cannot be compared to a character
      string or searched with a LIKE expression when thie property is
      <literal>TRUE</literal>.</simpara>

      <simpara>The property is <literal>FALSE</literal> by default.</simpara>

      <simpara>SQL Standard requires enforcement. <emphasis>It is better to
      enable this check, in order to improve the quality and correctness of
      SQL statements.</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>sql.enforce_type</literal>.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET DATABASE SQL TDC DELETE</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET DATABASE SQL TDC
      DELETE</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set database sql tdc delete
      statement</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set database sql tdc delete statement&gt; ::= SET
      DATABASE SQL TDC DELETE { TRUE | FALSE }</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>This command can enable or disable full enforcement of the SQL
      Standard rules that prevents triggered data change exeptions caused by
      ON DELETE CASCADE clauses of foreign key constraint.</simpara>

      <simpara>When there are multiple constraints, a row may be updated by
      one constraint and deleted by another constraint in the same operation.
      This is not allowed by default. Changing this to false allows such
      violations of the Standard to pass without an exception.</simpara>

      <simpara>The property is <literal>TRUE</literal> by default.</simpara>

      <simpara>SQL Standard requires enforcement, therefore this property
      shouldn't be changed unless an application written for a non-conforming
      RDBMS needs it.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>sql.enforce_tdc_delete</literal>.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET DATABASE SQL TYPES</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET DATABASE SQL TDC
      UPDATE</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set database sql tdc update
      statement</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set database sql tdc update statement&gt; ::= SET
      DATABASE SQL TDC UPDATE { TRUE | FALSE }</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>This command can enable or disable full enforcement of the SQL
      Standard rules that prevents triggered data change exeptions caused by
      multiple ON UPDATE or ON DELETE SET clauses of foreign key constraint.
      When there are multiple constraints, a field in a row may be updated by
      two constraints to different values in the same operation. This is not
      allowed by default. Changing this to <literal>FALSE</literal> allows
      such violations of the Standard to pass without an exception.</simpara>

      <simpara>The property is <literal>TRUE</literal> by default.</simpara>

      <simpara>SQL Standard requires enforcement, therefore this property
      shouldn't be changed unless an application written for a non-conforming
      RDBMS needs it.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>sql.enforce_tdc_update</literal>.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET DATABASE SQL TRANSLATE TTI TYPES</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET DATABASE SQL TRANSLATE TTI
      TYPES</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set database sql translate tti types
      statement</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set database sql translate tti types statement&gt;
      ::= SET DATABASE SQL TRANSLATE TTI TYPES { TRUE | FALSE
      }</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>The JDBC Specification up to version 4.1 does not support some
      SQL Standard built-in types, therefore these types must be translated to
      a supported type when accessed through JDBC ResultSet and
      PreparedStatement methods.</simpara>

      <simpara>If the property is true, the TIME / TIMESTAMP WITH TIME ZONE
      types and INTERVAL types are represented in JDBC methods of
      <classname>ResultSetMetaData</classname> and
      <classname>DatabaseMetaData</classname> as JDBC datetime types without
      time zone and the VARCHAR type respectively. The original type names are
      preserved.</simpara>

      <simpara>The property is <literal>TRUE</literal> by default. If set to
      <literal>FASLE</literal>, the type codes for WITH TIME ZONE types will
      be SQL type codes as opposed to JDBC type codes.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>jdbc.translate_tti_types</literal>.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET DATABASE SQL CONCAT NULLS</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET DATABASE SQL CONCAT
      NULLS</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set database sql concat nulls
      statement</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set database sql concat nulls statement&gt; ::=
      SET DATABASE SQL CONCAT NULLS { TRUE | FALSE }</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>When the property is <literal>TRUE</literal>, concatanation of
      a null value with a not-null value results in a null value. When the
      property is <literal>FALSE</literal> this type of concatenation result
      in the not-null value.</simpara>

      <simpara>Setting this property <literal>FALSE</literal> results in
      concatenation behaviour similar to Oracle or MS SQL Server.</simpara>

      <simpara>SQL Standard requires a NULL result..</simpara>

      <simpara>The property is <literal>TRUE</literal> by default.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>sql.concat_nulls</literal>.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET DATABASE SQL UNIQUE NULLS</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET DATABASE SQL UNIQUE
      NULLS</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set database sql unique nulls
      statement</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set database sql unique nulls statement&gt; ::=
      SET DATABASE SQL UNIQUE NULLS { TRUE | FALSE }</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>When the property is <literal>TRUE</literal>, with multi-column
      UNIQUE constraints, it is possible to insert multiple rows for which one
      or more of the values for the constraint columns is NULL. When the
      property is <literal>FALSE</literal>, if there is any not-null value in
      the columns, then the set of values is compared to the existing rows and
      if there is a match, an exception is thrown. The setting
      <literal>FALSE</literal>, makes the behaviour more restrictive. For
      example, inserting (1, null) twice is possible by default, but not
      possible when the property is <literal>FALSE</literal>.</simpara>

      <simpara>Setting this property <literal>FALSE</literal> results in
      UNIQUE constraint behaviour similar to Oracle.</simpara>

      <simpara>SQL Standard requires the defual (TRUE) behaviour.</simpara>

      <simpara>The property is <literal>TRUE</literal> by default.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>sql.unique_nulls</literal>.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET DATABASE SQL CONVERT TRUNCATE</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET DATABASE SQL CONVERT
      TRUNCATE</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set database sql unique convert
      truncate</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set database sql convert truncate statement&gt;
      ::= SET DATABASE SQL CONVERT TRUNCATE { TRUE | FALSE
      }</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>When the property is <literal>TRUE</literal>, conversion from a
      floating point value (a DOUBLE value) to an integral type alwas
      truncates the fractional part. When the property is
      <literal>FALSE</literal>, rounding takes place instead of truncation.
      For example, assigning the value 123456E-2 to an ineger column will
      result in 1234 by default, but 1235 when the property is
      <literal>FALSE</literal>.</simpara>

      <simpara>Standard SQL considers this behaviour implementation
      dependent.</simpara>

      <simpara>The property is <literal>TRUE</literal> by default.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>sql.convert_trunc</literal>.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET DATABASE SQL AVG SCALE</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET DATABASE SQL AVG
      SCALE</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set database sql avg scale</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set database sql avg scale&gt; ::= SET DATABASE
      SQL AVG SCALE &lt;numeric value&gt;</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>By default, the result of division and the AVG and MEDIAN
      aggregate functions has the same type as the aggregated type of the
      values. This includes the scale. The scale specified with this property
      is used if it is larger than the scale of the operation. For example,
      the average of 5 and 10 is 7 by default, but 7.50 if the scale is
      specified as 2. The result of 7/3 is 2 by default but 2.33 if the scale
      is specified as 2.</simpara>

      <simpara>Standard SQL considers this behaviour implementation dependent.
      Some databases use a default scale larger than zero.</simpara>

      <simpara>The property is <literal>0</literal> by default.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>sql.avg_scale</literal>.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET DATABASE SQL DOUBLE NAN</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET DATABASE SQL DOUBLE
      NAN</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set database sql double nan</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set database sql double nan&gt; ::= SET DATABASE
      SQL DOUBLE NAN { TRUE | FALSE }</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>When the property is <literal>TRUE</literal>, division of a
      floating point value (a DOUBLE value) by zero raises an exception. When
      the property is <literal>FALSE</literal>, a Java
      <literal>Double.NaN</literal>, <literal>POSITIVE_INFINITY</literal> or
      <literal>NEGATIVE_INFINITY</literal> value is returned.</simpara>

      <simpara>Standard SQL requires an exception to be raised.</simpara>

      <simpara>The property is <literal>TRUE</literal> by default.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>sql.double_nan</literal>.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET DATABASE SQL NULLS FIRST</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET DATABASE SQL NULLS
      FIRST</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set database sql nulls first</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set database sql nulls first&gt; ::= SET DATABASE
      SQL NULLS FIRST { TRUE | FALSE }</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>When the property is <literal>TRUE</literal>, nulls appear
      before values in result sets with ORDER BY. When set FALSE, nulls appear
      after the values. Some databases, including PostgreSQL, Oracle and MS
      SQL Server, return nulls after the values.</simpara>

      <simpara>The property is <literal>TRUE</literal> by default.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>sql.nulls_first</literal>.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET DATABASE SQL SYNTAX DB2</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET DATABASE SQL SYNTAX
      DB2</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set database sql syntax DB2</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set database sql syntax DB2 statement&gt; ::= SET
      DATABASE SQL SYNTAX DB2 { TRUE | FALSE }</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>This property, when set TRUE, enables support for some elements
      of DB2 syntax. Single-row SELECT statements (<literal>SELECT
      &lt;expression list&gt;</literal> without the FROM clause) are supported
      and treated as the SQL Standard equivalent, <literal>VALUES
      &lt;expression list&gt;</literal>. The DUAL table is supported, as well
      as the ROWNUM psuedo-column. BINARY type definitions such as VARCHAR(L)
      FOR BIT DATA are supported. Empty DEFAULT clauses in column definitions
      are supported.</simpara>

      <simpara>The property is <literal>FALSE</literal> by default.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>sql.syntax_db2</literal>.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET DATABASE SQL SYNTAX MSS</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET DATABASE SQL SYNTAX
      MSS</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set database sql syntax MSS</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set database sql syntax MSS statement&gt; ::= SET
      DATABASE SQL SYNTAX MSS { TRUE | FALSE }</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>This property, when set TRUE, enables support for some elements
      of SQLServer syntax. Single-row SELECT statements (<literal>SELECT
      &lt;expression list&gt;</literal> without the FROM clause) are supported
      and treated as the SQL Standard equivalent, <literal>VALUES
      &lt;expression list&gt;</literal>. The parameters of CONVERT() function
      are switched in this mode.</simpara>

      <simpara>The property is <literal>FALSE</literal> by default.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>sql.syntax_mss</literal>.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET DATABASE SQL SYNTAX MYS</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET DATABASE SQL SYNTAX
      MYS</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set database sql syntax MYS</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set database sql syntax MYS statement&gt; ::= SET
      DATABASE SQL SYNTAX MYS { TRUE | FALSE }</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>This property, when set TRUE, enables support for some elements
      of MySQL syntax. The TEXT data type is translated to
      LONGVARCHAR.</simpara>

      <simpara>In CREATE TABLE statements, [NOT NULL | NULL] can be used
      immediately after the column type name and before the DEFAULT clause.
      AUTO_INCREMENT is translated to the GENERATED BY DEFAULT AS IDENTITY
      clause.</simpara>

      <simpara>Single-row SELECT statements (<literal>SELECT &lt;expression
      list&gt;</literal> without the FROM clause) are supported and treated as
      the SQL Standard equivalent, <literal>VALUES &lt;expression
      list&gt;</literal>.</simpara>

      <simpara>The property is <literal>FALSE</literal> by default.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>sql.syntax_mys</literal>.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET DATABASE SQL SYNTAX ORA</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET DATABASE SQL SYNTAX
      ORA</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set database sql syntax ORA</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set database sql syntax ORA statement&gt; ::= SET
      DATABASE SQL SYNTAX ORA { TRUE | FALSE }</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>This property, when set TRUE, enables support for some elements
      of Oracle syntax. The DUAL table is supported, together with ROWNUM,
      NEXTVAL and CURRVAL syntax and semantics.</simpara>

      <simpara>The non-standard types are translated to supported standard
      types. BINARY_DOUBLE and BINARY_FLOAT are translated to DOUBLE. LONG RAW
      and RAW are translated to VARBINARY with long or medium length limits.
      LONG and VARCHAR2 are translated to VARCHAR with long or medium length
      limits. NUMBER is translated to DECIMAL. Some extra type conversions and
      no-arg functions are also allowed in this mode.</simpara>

      <simpara>The property is <literal>FALSE</literal> by default.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>sql.syntax_ora</literal>.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET DATABASE SQL SYNTAX PGS</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET DATABASE SQL SYNTAX
      PGS</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set database sql syntax PGS</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set database sql syntax PGS statement&gt; ::= SET
      DATABASE SQL SYNTAX PGS { TRUE | FALSE }</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>This property, when set TRUE, enables support for some elements
      of PosgtreSQL syntax. The TEXT data type is transated to LONGVARCHAR,
      while the SERIAL data types is translated to BIGINT together with
      GENERATED BY DEFAULT AS IDENTITY.</simpara>

      <simpara>Single-row SELECT statements (<literal>SELECT &lt;expression
      list&gt;</literal> without the FROM clause) are supported and treated as
      the SQL Standard equivalent, <literal>VALUES &lt;expression
      list&gt;</literal>.</simpara>

      <simpara>The functions <literal>NEXTVAL(&lt;sequence name
      string&gt;)</literal>, <literal>CURRVAL(&lt;sequence name
      string&gt;)</literal> and <literal>LASTVAL()</literal> are supported in
      this compatibility mode.</simpara>

      <simpara>The property is <literal>FALSE</literal> by default.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>sql.syntax_pgs</literal>.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET REFERENTIAL INTEGRITY</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET DATABASE REFERENTIAL
      INTEGRITY</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set database referential integrity
      statement</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set database referential integrity statement&gt;
      ::= SET DATABASE REFERENTIAL INTEGRITY { TRUE | FALSE
      }</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>This command enables or disables the enforcement of referential
      integrity constraints (foreign key constraints), check constraints apart
      from NOT NULL and execution of triggers. By default, all constraints are
      checked.</simpara>

      <simpara>The only legitimate use of this statement is before importing
      large amounts of external data into tables that have existing FOREIGN
      KEY constraints. After import, the statement must be used again to
      enable constraint enforcement.</simpara>

      <simpara>If you are not sure the data conforms to the constraints, run
      queries to verify all rows conform to the FOREIGN KEY constraints and
      take appropriate actions for the rows that do not conform.</simpara>

      <simpara>A query example to return the rows in a foreign key table that
      have no parent is given below:</simpara>

      <example>
        <title>Finding foreign key rows with no parents after a bulk
        import</title>

        <screen>  SELECT * FROM foreign_key_table LEFT OUTER JOIN primary_key_table 
    ON foreign_key_table.fk_col = primary_key_table.pk_col WHERE primary_key_table.pk_col IS NULL</screen>
      </example>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Cache, Persistence and Files Settings</title>

      <simpara>These statements control the memory and other settings for
      database persistence.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET FILES BACKUP INCREMENT</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET FILES BACKUP INCREMENT
      </emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set files backup increment
      statement</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set files backup increment statement&gt; ::= SET
      FILES BACKUP INCREMENT { TRUE | FALSE }</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>Older versions of HSQLDB perform a backup of the .data file
      before its contents are modified and the whole .data file is saved in a
      compressed form when a CHECKPOINT or SHUTDOWN is performed. This takes a
      long time when the size of the database exceeds 100 MB or so (on an
      average 2010 computer, you can expect a backup speed of 20MB per second
      or more).</simpara>

      <simpara>The alternative is backup in increments, just before some part
      of the .data file is modified. In this mode, no backup is performed at
      CHECKPIONT or SHUTDOWN. This mode is preferred for large databases which
      are opened and closed frequently.</simpara>

      <simpara>The default mode is <literal>TRUE</literal>. If the old method
      of backup is preferred, the mode can be set
      <literal>FALSE</literal>.</simpara>

      <simpara>Warning: The old, non-incremental setting, FALSE, shouldn't be
      used at all when the data file is larger than 4GB. If it is used, the
      data file is not fully backed up and can result in corruption. The zip
      compression method is used in this mode and it is limited to 4GB
      size.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>hsqldb.inc_backup</literal>.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET FILES CACHE ROWS</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET FILES CACHE ROWS</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set files cache rows statement</emphasis><literal>
      </literal></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set files cache rows statement&gt; ::= SET FILES
      CACHE ROWS &lt;unsigned integer literal&gt;</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>Sets the maximum number of rows (of CACHED tables) held in the
      memory cache. The default is 50000 rows.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>hsqldb.cache_rows</literal>.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET FILES CACHE SIZE</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET FILES CACHE SIZE</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set files cache size statement</emphasis><literal>
      </literal></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set files cache size statement&gt; ::= SET FILES
      CACHE SIZE &lt;unsigned integer literal&gt;</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>Sets maximum amount of data (of CACHED tables) in kilobytes
      held in the memory cache. The default is 10000 kilobytes. Note the
      amount of memory used is larger than this amount, which does not account
      for Java object size overheads.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>hsqldb.cache_size</literal>.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET FILES DEFRAG</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET FILES DEFRAG</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set files defrag statement</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set files defrag statement&gt; ::= SET FILES
      DEFRAG &lt;unsigned integer literal&gt;</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>Sets the threshold for performing a DEFRAG during a checkpoint.
      The <literal>&lt;unsigned integer literal&gt;</literal> is the
      percentage of abandoned space in the <literal>*.data</literal> file.
      When a CHECKPOINT is performed either as a result of the
      <literal>.log</literal> file reaching the limit set by <literal>SET
      FILES LOG SIZE m</literal>, or by the user issuing a CHECKPOINT command,
      the amount of space abandoned since the database was opened is checked
      and if it is larger than specified percentage, a CHECKPOINT DEFRAG is
      performed instead of a CHECKPOINT.</simpara>

      <simpara>The default is 0, which indicates no DEFRAG. Useful values are
      between 10 to 50.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>hsqldb.defrag_limit</literal>.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET FILES LOG</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET FILES LOG</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set files log statement</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set files log statement&gt; ::= SET FILES LOG {
      TRUE | FALSE }</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>Sets logging of database operations on or off. Turning logging
      off is for special usage, such as temporary cache usage. The default is
      TRUE.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>hsqldb.log_data</literal>.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET FILES LOG SIZE</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET FILES LOG SIZE</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set files log size statement</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set files log size statement&gt; ::= SET FILES LOG
      SIZE &lt;unsigned integer literal&gt;</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>Sets the maximum size in MB of the <literal>*.log</literal>
      file to the specified value. The default maximum size is 50 MB. If the
      value is zero, no limit is used for the size of the file. When the size
      of the file reaches this value, a CHECKPOINT is performed and the the
      <literal>*.log</literal> file is cleared to size 0.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>hsqldb.log_size</literal>.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET FILES NIO</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET FILES NIO</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set files nio</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set files nio statement&gt; ::= SET FILES NIO {
      TRUE | FALSE }</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>Sets the access method of the .data file. The default is TRUE
      and uses the Java nio classes to access the file.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>hsqldb.nio_data_file</literal>.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET FILES NIO SIZE</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET FILES NIO SIZE</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set files nio size</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set files nio size statement&gt; ::= SET FILES NIO
      SIZE &lt;unsigned integer literal&gt;</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>Sets The maximum size of .data file in megabytes that can use
      the nio access method. When the file gets larger than this limit,
      non-nio access methods are used. Values 64, 128, 256, 512, 1024, 2048
      can be used. The default is 256MB.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>hsqldb.nio_max_size</literal>.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET FILES WRITE DELAY</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET FILES WRITE
      DELAY</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set files write delay statement</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set files write delay statement&gt; ::= SET FILES
      WRITE DELAY {{ TRUE | FALSE } | &lt;seconds value&gt; | &lt;milliseconds
      value&gt; MILLIS}</literal></simpara>

      <para>Set the WRITE DELAY property of the database. The WRITE DELAY
      controls the frequency of file sync for the log file. When WRITE_DELAY
      is set to FALSE or 0, the sync takes place immediately at each COMMIT.
      WRITE DELAY TRUE performs the sync once every 0.5 seconds (which is the
      default). A numeric value can be specified instead.</para>

      <para>The purpose of this command is to control the amount of data loss
      in case of a total system crash. A delay of 1 second means at most the
      data written to disk during the last second before the crash is lost.
      All data written prior to this has been synced and should be
      recoverable.</para>

      <para>A write delay of 0 impacts performance in high load situations, as
      the engine has to wait for the file system to catch up.</para>

      <para>To avoid this, you can set write delay down to 10
      milliseconds.</para>

      <para>Each time the SET FILES WRITE DELAY statement is executed with any
      value, a sync is immediately performed.</para>

      <para>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this statement.</para>

      <para>This is equivalent to the connection properties
      <literal>hsqldb.write_delay</literal> and
      <literal>hsqldb.write_delay_millis</literal>.</para>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET FILES SCALE</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET FILES SCALE</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set files scale</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set files scale statement&gt; ::= SET FILES SCALE
      &lt;scale value&gt;</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>Changes the scale factor for the .data file. The default scale
      is 8 and allows 16GB of data storage capacity. The scale can be
      increased in order to increase the maximum data storage capacity. The
      scale values 8, 16, 32, 64, 128, 256, 512, 1024 are allowed. Scale value
      1024 allows a maximum capacity of 2 TB.</simpara>

      <simpara>This command can be used only when there is no data in CACHED
      tables. This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>hsqldb.cache_file_scale</literal>.</simpara>

      <simpara>The scale factor indicates the size of the unit of storage of
      data in bytes. For example, with a scale factor of 128, a row containing
      a small amount of data will use 128 bytes. Larger rows may use multiple
      units of 128 bytes.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>hsqldb.cache_file_scale</literal>.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET FILES LOB SCALE</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET FILES LOB SCALE</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set files lob scale</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set files lob scale statement&gt; ::= SET FILES
      LOB SCALE &lt;scale value&gt;</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>Changes the scale factor for the .lobs file. The scale is
      interpreted in kilobytes. The default scale is 32 and allows 64TB of lob
      data storage capacity. The scale can be reduced in order to improve
      storage efficiency. If the lobs are a lot smaller than 32 kilobytes,
      reducing the scale will reduce wasted space. The scale values 1, 2, 4,
      8, 16, 32 are allowed. For example if the average size of lobs is 4
      kilobytes, the default scale of 32 will result in 28KB wasted space for
      each lob. Reducing the lob scale to 2 will result in average 1KB wasted
      space for each lob.</simpara>

      <simpara>This command can be used only when there is no lob in the
      database.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>This is equivalent to the connection property
      <literal>hsqldb.lob_file_scale</literal>.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET FILES SCRIPT FORMAT</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET FILES SCRIPT
      FORMAT</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set files script format</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set files script format statement&gt; ::= SET
      FILES SCRIPT FORMAT { TEXT | COMPRESSED }</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>Changes the compression setting for database scripts. The
      default is text. Using COMPRESSED results in the storage of the .script
      file in gzip compressed form. Using this command causes a
      CHECKPOINT.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Authentication Settings</title>

      <para>Two settings are available for authentication control.</para>

      <para>When the default password authentication is used, the passwords
      can be checked for complexity according to administrative rules</para>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET DATABASE PASSWORD CHECK FUNCTION</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET DATABASE PASSWORD CHECK
      FUNCTION</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set database password check
      function</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set database password check function statement&gt;
      ::= SET DATABASE PASSWORD CHECK FUNCTION { &lt;routine body&gt; | NONE
      }</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>The routine body is the body of a function that has a VARCHAR
      parameter and returns a BOOLEAN. This function checks the
      <literal>PASSWORD</literal> submitted as parameter and returns TRUE if
      it conforms to complexity checks, or FALSE, if it does not.</simpara>

      <simpara>The <literal>&lt;routine body&gt;</literal> can be an SQL block
      or an external Java function reference. This is covered in the <link
      endterm="sqlroutines-title" xlink:href="#sqlroutines-chapt"></link>
      chapter</simpara>

      <simpara>To disable this mechanism, the token <literal>NONE</literal>
      can be specified instead of the <literal>&lt;routine
      body&gt;</literal>.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara>In the examples below, an SQL function and a Java function are
      used.</simpara>

      <programlisting>SET DATABASE PASSWORD CHECK FUNCTION
  BEGIN ATOMIC
    IF CHAR_LENGTH(PASSWORD) &gt; 6 THEN
      RETURN TRUE;
    ELSE 
      RETURN FALSE;
    END IF;
  END

SET DATABASE PASSWORD CHECK FUNCTION EXTERNAL NAME 'CLASSPATH:org.anorg.access.AccessClass.accessMethod'

// the Java method is defined like this
public static boolean accessMethod(String param) {
    return param != null &amp;&amp; param.length &gt; 6;
}
</programlisting>

      <simpara>It is possible to replace the default password authentication
      completely with a function that uses external authentication servers,
      such as LDAP. This function is called each time a user connects to the
      database.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SET DATABASE AUTHENTICATION FUNCTION</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET DATABASE AUTHENTICATION
      FUNCTION</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>set database authentication
      function</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;set database authentication function statement&gt;
      ::= SET DATABASE AUTHENTICATION FUNCTION { &lt;external body
      reference&gt; | NONE }</literal></simpara>

      <simpara>The routine body is an external Java function reference. This
      function has three String parameters. The first parameter is the unique
      name of the database, the second parameter the user name, and the third
      parameter the password.</simpara>

      <simpara>External authentication can be used in two different patterns.
      In the first pattern, user names must be stored in the database. In the
      second pattern, user names shouldn't be stored in the database and any
      names that are stored in the database are ignored.</simpara>

      <simpara>In both patterns, the username and password are checked by the
      authentication function. If the function throws a runtime exception then
      authentication fails.</simpara>

      <simpara>In the first pattern, the function always returns null if
      authentication is successful.</simpara>

      <simpara>In the second pattern, the function returns a list of role
      names that have been granted to the user. These roles must match the
      ROLE objects that have been defined in the database.</simpara>

      <simpara>The Java function should return an instance of
      org.hsqldb.jdbc.JDBCArrayBasic constructed with a String[] argument that
      contains the role names.</simpara>

      <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
      statement.</simpara>

      <programlisting>SET DATABASE AUTHENTICATION FUNCTION EXTERNAL NAME 'CLASSPATH:org.anorg.access.AccessClass.accessExernalMethod'

// the Java method is defined like this
public static java.sql.Array accessExternalMethod(String database, String user, String password) {
    if (externalCheck(database, user, password) {
        return null;
    }
    throw new RuntimeException("failed to authenticate");
}
</programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
