<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % dummy22 SYSTEM "../entities/global.ent">
%dummy22;
]>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="sqlgeneral-chapt"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <!-- We declare the default namespace + those for prefixes xlink: and xi: in
       the root element, so we can use them anywhere in this file. -->

  <title xml:id="sqlgeneral-title">SQL Language</title>

  <info>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <personname><firstname>Fred</firstname><surname>Toussi</surname></personname>

        <affiliation>
          <orgname>The HSQL Development Group</orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <releaseinfo>$Revision$</releaseinfo>

    <pubdate>$Date$</pubdate>

    <keywordset>
      <keyword>Hsqldb</keyword>

      <keyword>HyperSQL</keyword>

      <keyword>SQL</keyword>
    </keywordset>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Copyright 2002-2010 Fred Toussi. Permission is granted to
      distribute this document without any alteration under the terms of the
      HSQLDB license. Additional permission is granted to the HSQL Development
      Group to distribute this document with or without alterations under the
      terms of the HSQLDB license.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </info>

  <section xml:id="sqlgeneral_standards-sect">
    <title>Standards Support</title>

    <para>HyperSQL 2.0 supports the dialect of SQL defined by SQL standards
    92, 1999, 2003 and 2008. This means where a feature of the standard is
    supported, e.g. left outer join, the syntax is that specified by the
    standard text. Almost all syntactic features of SQL-92 up to Advanced
    Level are supported, as well as SQL:2008 core and many optional features
    of this standard. Work is in progress for a formal declaration of
    conformance.</para>

    <para>At the time of this release, HyperSQL supports the widest range of
    SQL standard features among all open source RDBMS.</para>

    <para>Various chapters of this guide list the supported syntax. When
    writing or converting existing SQL DDL (Data Definition Language), DML
    (Data Manipulation Language) or DQL (Data Query Language) statements for
    HSQLDB, you should consult the supported syntax and modify the statements
    accordingly. Some statements written for older versions may have to be
    modified.</para>

    <para>Over 300 words are reserved by the standard and should not be used
    as table or column names. For example, the word POSITION is reserved as it
    is a function defined by the Standards with a similar role as
    <methodname>String.indexOf()</methodname> in Java. HyperSQL does not
    currently prevent you from using a reserved word if it does not support
    its use or can distinguish it. For example CUBE is a reserved words that
    is not currently supported by HyperSQL and is allowed as a table or column
    name. You should avoid using such names as future versions of HyperSQL are
    likely to support the reserved words and may reject your table definitions
    or queries. The full list of SQL reserved words is in the appendix <link
    endterm="lists-title" xlink:href="#lists-app"></link> .</para>

    <para>If you have to use a reserved keyword as the name of a database
    object, you can enclose it in double quotes.</para>

    <para>HyperSQL also supports enhancements with keywords and expressions
    that are not part of the SQL standard. Expressions such as <literal>SELECT
    TOP 5 FROM ..</literal>, <literal>SELECT LIMIT 0 10 FROM ...</literal> or
    <literal>DROP TABLE mytable IF EXISTS</literal> are among such
    constructs.</para>

    <para>Many print books cover SQL Standard syntax and can be consulted. For
    a well-written basic guide to SQL with examples, you can also consult
    <link
    xlink:href="http://www.postgresql.org/files/documentation/books/aw_pgsql/index.html">PostgreSQL:
    Introduction and Concepts</link> by Bruce Momjian, which is available on
    the web. Most of the core SQL coverage in the book applies also to
    HyperSQL. There are some differences in keywords supported by one and not
    the other engine (OUTER, OID's, etc.) or used differently
    (IDENTITY/SERIAL, TRIGGER, SEQUENCE, etc.).</para>

    <para>In HyperSQL version 2.0, all features of JDBC4 that apply to the
    capabilities of HSQLDB are fully supported. The relevant JDBC classes are
    thoroughly documented with additional clarifications and HyperSQL specific
    comments. See the <link xlink:href="#javadoc-link">JavaDoc</link> for the
    <classname>org.hsqldb.jdbc.*</classname> classes.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="sqlgeneral_tabletypes-sect">
    <title>SQL Data and Tables</title>

    <para>In an SQL system, all significant data is stored in tables and
    sequence generators. Therefore, the first step in creating a database is
    defining the tables and their columns. The SQL standard supports temporary
    tables, which are for temporary data, and permanent base tables, which are
    for persistent data.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Temporary Tables</title>

      <para>Data in TEMPORARY tables is not saved and lasts only for the
      lifetime of the session. The contents of each TEMP table is visible only
      from the session that is used to populate it. </para>

      <para>HyperSQL supports two types of temporary tables.</para>

      <para>The <literal>GLOBAL TEMPORARY</literal> type is a schema object.
      It is created with the <literal>CREATE LOCAL TEMPORARY TABLE</literal>
      statement. The definition of the table persists, and each session has
      access to the table. But each session sees its own copy of the table,
      which is empty at the beginning of the session. </para>

      <para>The <literal>LOCAL TEMPORARY</literal> type is not a schema
      object. It is created with the <literal>DECLARE LOCAL TEMPORARY
      TABLE</literal> statement. The table definition lasts only for the
      duration of the session and is not persisted in the database. The table
      can be declared in the middle of a transaction without committing the
      transaction.</para>

      <para>When the session commits, the contents of all temporary tables are
      cleared by default. If the table definition statements includes ON
      COMMIT PRESERVE ROWS, then the contents are kept when a commit takes
      place.</para>

      <para>The rows in temporary tables are stored in memory by default. If
      the hsqldb.max_result_memory_rows has been specified, tables with row
      count above the setting are stored on disk.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Persistent Tables</title>

      <para>HSQLDB supports the Standard definition of persistent base table,
      but defines three types according to the way the data is stored. These
      are MEMORY tables, CACHED tables and TEXT tables.</para>

      <para>Memory tables are the default type when the CREATE TABLE command
      is used. Their data is held entirely in memory but any change to their
      structure or contents is written to the <filename>*.log</filename> and
      <filename>*.script</filename> files. The <filename>*.script</filename>
      file and the <filename>*.log</filename> file are read the next time the
      database is opened, and the MEMORY tables are recreated with all their
      contents. So unlike TEMPORARY tables, MEMORY tables are persistent. When
      the database is opened, all the data for the memory tables is read and
      inserted. This process may take a long time if the database is larger
      than tens of megabytes. When the database is shutdown, all the data is
      saved. This can also take a long time.</para>

      <para>CACHED tables are created with the CREATE CACHED TABLE command.
      Only part of their data or indexes is held in memory, allowing large
      tables that would otherwise take up to several hundred megabytes of
      memory. Another advantage of cached tables is that the database engine
      takes less time to start up when a cached table is used for large
      amounts of data. The disadvantage of cached tables is a reduction in
      speed. Do not use cached tables if your data set is relatively small. In
      an application with some small tables and some large ones, it is better
      to use the default, MEMORY mode for the small tables.</para>

      <para>TEXT tables use a CSV (Comma Separated Value) or other delimited
      text file as the source of their data. You can specify an existing CSV
      file, such as a dump from another database or program, as the source of
      a TEXT table. Alternatively, you can specify an empty file to be filled
      with data by the database engine. TEXT tables are efficient in memory
      usage as they cache only part of the text data and all of the indexes.
      The Text table data source can always be reassigned to a different file
      if necessary. The commands are needed to set up a TEXT table as detailed
      in the <link endterm="texttables-title"
      xlink:href="#texttables-chapt"></link> chapter.</para>

      <para>With all-in-memory databases, both MEMORY table and CACHED table
      declarations are treated as declarations for non-persistent memory
      tables. TEXT table declarations are not allowed in these
      databases.</para>

      <para>The default type of table resulting from future CREATE TABLE
      statements can be specified with the SQL command:</para>

      <para><programlisting>    SET DATABASE DEFAULT TABLE TYPE { CACHED | MEMORY };</programlisting>The
      type of an existing table can be changed with the SQL command:</para>

      <para><programlisting>    SET TABLE &lt;table name&gt; TYPE { CACHED | MEMORY };</programlisting>SQL
      statements access different types of tables uniformly. No change to
      statements is needed to access different types of table.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Lob Data</title>

      <para>Lobs are logically stored in columns of tables. Their physical
      storage is a separate *.lobs file. In version 2.0 this file is created
      as soon as a BLOB or CLOB is inserted into the database. The file will
      grow as new lobs are inserted into the database. In version 2.0, the
      *.lobs file is never deleted even if all lobs are deleted from the
      database (In this case you can delete the .lobs file after a
      SHTUDOWN).</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="sqlgeneral_types_ops-sect">
    <title>Basic Types and Operations</title>

    <para>HyperSQL supports all the types defined by SQL-92, plus BOOLEAN,
    BINARY and LOB types that were added later to the SQL Standard. It also
    supports the non-standard OTHER type to store serializable Java
    objects.</para>

    <para>SQL is a strongly typed language. All data stored in specific
    columns of tables and other objects (such as sequence generators) have
    specific types. Each data item conforms to the type limits such as
    precision and scale for the column. It also conforms to any additional
    integrity constraints that are defined as CHECK constraints in domains or
    tables. Types can be explicitly converted using the CAST expression, but
    in most expressions they are converted automatically.</para>

    <para>Data is returned to the user (or the application program) as a
    result of executing SQL statements such as query expressions or function
    calls. All statements are compiled prior to execution and the return type
    of the data is known after compilation and before execution. Therefore,
    once a statement is prepared, the data type of each column of the returned
    result is known, including any precision or scale property. The type does
    not change when the same query that returned one row, returns many rows as
    a result of adding more data to the tables.</para>

    <para>Some SQL functions used within SQL statements are polymorphic, but
    the exact type of the argument and the return value is determined at
    compile time.</para>

    <para>When a statement is prepared, using a JDBC PreparedStatement object,
    it is compiled by the engine and the type of the columns of its ResultSet
    and / or its parameters are accessible through the methods of
    PreparedStatement.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Numeric Types</title>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>NUMERIC types</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>TINYINT, SMALLINT, INTEGER, BIGINT, NUMERIC and DECIMAL (without a
      decimal point) are the supported integral types. They correspond
      respectively to <classname>byte</classname>,
      <classname>short</classname>, <classname>int</classname>,
      <classname>long</classname>, <classname>BigDecimal</classname> and
      <classname>BigDecimal</classname> Java types in the range of values that
      they can represent (NUMERIC and DECIMAL are equivalent). The type
      TINYINT is an HSQLDB extension to the SQL Standard, while the others
      conform to the Standard definition. The SQL type dictates the maximum
      and minimum values that can be held in a field of each type. For example
      the value range for TINYINT is -128 to +127. The bit precision of
      TINYINT, SMALLINT, INTEGER and BIGINT is respectively 8, 16, 32 and 64.
      For NUMERIC and DECIMAL, decimal precision is used.</para>

      <para>DECIMAL and NUMERIC with decimal fractions are mapped to
      <classname>java.math.BigDecimal</classname> and can have very large
      numbers of digits. In HyperSQL the two types are equivalent. These
      types, together with integral types, are called exact numeric
      types.</para>

      <para>In HyperSQL, REAL, FLOAT, DOUBLE are equivalent and all mapped to
      <classname>double</classname> in Java. These types are defined by the
      SQL Standard as approximate numeric types. The bit-precision of all
      these types is 64 bits.</para>

      <para>The decimal precision and scale of NUMERIC and DECIMAL types can
      be optionally defined. For example, DECIMAL(10,2) means maximum total
      number of digits is 10 and there are always 2 digits after the decimal
      point, while DECIMAL(10) means 10 digits without a decimal point. The
      bit-precision of FLOAT can also be defined, but in this case, it is
      ignored and the default bit-precision of 64 is used. The default
      precision of NUMERIC and DECIMAL (when not defined) is 100.</para>

      <para>Note: If a database has been set to ignore type precision limits
      with the SET DATABASE SQL SIZE FALSE command, then a type definition of
      DECIMAL with no precision and scale is treated as DECIMAL(100,10). In
      normal operation, it is treated as DECIMAL(100).</para>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Integral Types</emphasis></simpara>

      <para>In expressions, TINYINT, SMALLINT, INTEGER, BIGINT, NUMERIC and
      DECIMAL (without a decimal point) are fully interchangeable, and no data
      narrowing takes place.</para>

      <para>If the SELECT statement refers to a simple column or function,
      then the return type is the type corresponding to the column or the
      return type of the function. For example:</para>

      <informalexample>
        <programlisting>    CREATE TABLE t(a INTEGER, b BIGINT);
    SELECT MAX(a), MAX(b) FROM t;</programlisting>
      </informalexample>

      <para>will return a <classname>ResultSet</classname> where the type of
      the first column is <classname>java.lang.Integer</classname> and the
      second column is <classname>java.lang.Long</classname>. However,</para>

      <informalexample>
        <programlisting>    SELECT MAX(a) + 1, MAX(b) + 1 FROM t;</programlisting>
      </informalexample>

      <para>will return <classname>java.lang.Long</classname> and
      <classname>BigDecimal</classname> values, generated as a result of
      uniform type promotion for all the return values. Note that type
      promotion to <classname>BigDecimal</classname> ensures the correct value
      is returned if <literal>MAX(b)</literal> evaluates to
      <literal>Long.MAX_VALUE</literal>.</para>

      <para>There is no built-in limit on the size of intermediate integral
      values in expressions. As a result, you should check for the type of the
      <classname>ResultSet</classname> column and choose an appropriate
      <methodname>getXXXX()</methodname> method to retrieve it. Alternatively,
      you can use the <methodname>getObject()</methodname> method, then cast
      the result to <classname>java.lang.Number</classname> and use the
      <methodname>intValue()</methodname> or
      <methodname>longValue()</methodname> methods on the result.</para>

      <para>When the result of an expression is stored in a column of a
      database table, it has to fit in the target column, otherwise an error
      is returned. For example when <literal>1234567890123456789012 /
      12345687901234567890</literal> is evaluated, the result can be stored in
      any integral type column, even a TINYINT column, as it is a small
      value.</para>

      <para>In SQL Statements, an integer literal is treated as INTEGER,
      unless its value does not fit. In this case it is treated as BIGINT or
      DECIMAL, depending on the value.</para>

      <para>Depending on the types of the operands, the result of the
      operations is returned in a JDBC <classname>ResultSet</classname> in any
      of related Java types: <classname>Integer</classname>,
      <classname>Long</classname> or <classname>BigDecimal</classname>. The
      <methodname>ResultSet.getXXXX()</methodname> methods can be used to
      retrieve the values so long as the returned value can be represented by
      the resulting type. This type is deterministically based on the query,
      not on the actual rows returned.</para>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Other Numeric Types</emphasis></simpara>

      <para>In SQL statements, number literals with a decimal point are
      treated as DECIMAL unless they are written with an exponent. Thus
      <literal>0.2</literal> is considered a DECIMAL value but
      <literal>0.2E0</literal> is considered a DOUBLE value.</para>

      <para>When an approximate numeric type, REAL, FLOAT or DOUBLE (all
      synonymous) is part of an expression involving different numeric types,
      the type of the result is DOUBLE. DECIMAL values can be converted to
      DOUBLE unless they are beyond the <literal>Double.MIN_VALUE -
      Double.MAX_VALUE</literal> range. For example, A * B, A / B, A + B, etc.
      will return a DOUBLE value if either A or B is a DOUBLE.</para>

      <para>Otherwise, when no DOUBLE value exists, if a DECIMAL or NUMERIC
      value is part an expression, the type of the result is DECIMAL or
      NUMERIC. Similar to integral values, when the result of an expression is
      assigned to a table column, the value has to fit in the target column,
      otherwise an error is returned. This means a small, 4 digit value of
      DECIMAL type can be assigned to a column of SMALLINT or INTEGER, but a
      value with 15 digits cannot.</para>

      <para>When a DECIMAL values is multiplied by a DECIMAL or integral type,
      the resulting scale is the sum of the scales of the two terms. When they
      are divided, the result is a value with a scale (number of digits to the
      right of the decimal point) equal to the larger of the scales of the two
      terms. The precision for both operations is calculated (usually
      increased) to allow all possible results.</para>

      <para>The distinction between DOUBLE and DECIMAL is important when a
      division takes place. For example, <literal>10.0/8.0</literal> (DECIMAL)
      equals <literal>1.2</literal> but <literal>10.0E0/8.0E0</literal>
      (DOUBLE) equals <literal>1.25</literal>. Without division operations,
      DECIMAL values represent exact arithmetic.</para>

      <para>REAL, FLOAT and DOUBLE values are all stored in the database as
      <classname>java.lang.Double</classname> objects. Special values such as
      NaN and +-Infinity are also stored and supported. These values can be
      submitted to the database via JDBC
      <classname>PreparedStatement</classname> methods and are returned in
      <classname>ResultSet</classname> objects. The result can be retrieved
      from a <classname>ResultSet</classname> in the required type so long as
      it can be represented. When
      <methodname>PreparedStatement.setDouble()</methodname> or
      <methodname>setFloat()</methodname> is used, the value is treated as a
      DOUBLE automatically.</para>

      <para>In short,</para>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;numeric type&gt; ::= &lt;exact numeric type&gt; |
      &lt;approximate numeric type&gt;</literal></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;exact numeric type&gt; ::= NUMERIC [ &lt;left
      paren&gt; &lt;precision&gt; [ &lt;comma&gt; &lt;scale&gt; ] &lt;right
      paren&gt; ] | { DECIMAL | DEC } [ &lt;left paren&gt; &lt;precision&gt; [
      &lt;comma&gt; &lt;scale&gt; ] &lt;right paren&gt; ] | SMALLINT | INTEGER
      | INT | BIGINT</literal></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;approximate numeric type&gt; ::= FLOAT [ &lt;left
      paren&gt; &lt;precision&gt; &lt;right paren&gt; ] | REAL | DOUBLE
      PRECISION</literal></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;precision&gt; ::= &lt;unsigned
      integer&gt;</literal></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;scale&gt; ::= &lt;unsigned
      integer&gt;</literal></simpara>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Boolean Type</title>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>BOOLEAN types</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>The BOOLEAN type conforms to the SQL Standard and represents the
      values <literal>TRUE</literal>, <literal>FALSE</literal> and
      <literal>UNKNOWN</literal>. This type of column can be initialised with
      Java boolean values, or with <literal>NULL</literal> for the
      <literal>UNKNOWN</literal> value.</para>

      <para>The three-value logic is sometimes misunderstood. For example, x
      IN (1, 2, NULL) does not return true if x is NULL.</para>

      <para>In previous versions of HyperSQL, BIT was simply an alias for
      BOOLEAN. In version 2.0, BIT is a single-bit bit map.</para>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;boolean type&gt; ::= BOOLEAN</literal></simpara>

      <para>The SQL Standard does not support type conversion to BOOLEAN apart
      from character strings that consists of boolean literals. Because the
      BOOLEAN type is relatively new to the Standard, several database
      products used other types to represent boolean values. For improved
      compatibility, HyperSQL allows some type conversions to boolean.</para>

      <para>Values of BIT and BIT VARYING types with length 1 can be converted
      to BOOLEAN. If the bit is set, the result of conversion is the TRUE
      value, otherwise it is FALSE.</para>

      <para>Values of TINYINT, SMALLINT, INTEGER and BIGINT types can be
      converted to BOOLEAN. If the value is zero, the result is the FALSE
      value, otherwise it is TRUE.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Character String Types</title>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>CHARACTER types</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>The CHARACTER, CHARACTER VARYING and CLOB types are the SQL
      Standard character string types. CHAR, VARCHAR and CHARACTER LARGE
      OBJECT are synonyms for these types. HyperSQL also supports LONGVARCHAR
      as a synonym for VARCHAR. If LONGVARCHAR is used without a length, then
      a length of 1M is assigned.</para>

      <para>HyperSQL's default character set is Unicode, therefore all
      possible character strings can be represented by these types.</para>

      <para>The SQL Standard behaviour of the CHARACTER type is a remnant of
      legacy systems in which character strings are padded with spaces to fill
      a fixed width. These spaces are sometimes significant while in other
      cases they are silently discarded. It would be best to avoid the
      CHARACTER type altogether. With the rest of the types, the strings are
      not padded when assigned to columns or variables of the given type. The
      trailing spaces are still considered discardable for all character
      types. Therefore if a string with trailing spaces is too long to assign
      to a column or variable of a given length, the spaces beyond the type
      length are discarded and the assignment succeeds (provided all the
      characters beyond the type length are spaces).</para>

      <para>The VARCHAR and CLOB types have length limits, but the strings are
      not padded by the system. Note that if you use a large length for a
      VARCHAR or CLOB type, no extra space is used in the database. The space
      used for each stored item is proportional to its actual length.</para>

      <para>If CHARACTER is used without specifying the length, the length
      defaults to 1. For the CLOB type, the length limit can be defined in
      units of kilobyte (K, 1024), megabyte (M, 1024 * 1024) or gigabyte (G,
      1024 * 1024 * 1024), using the <literal>&lt;multiplier&gt;</literal>. If
      CLOB is used without specifying the length, the length defaults to
      1M.</para>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;character string type&gt; ::= { CHARACTER | CHAR }
      [ &lt;left paren&gt; &lt;character length&gt; &lt;right paren&gt; ] | {
      CHARACTER VARYING | CHAR VARYING | VARCHAR } &lt;left paren&gt;
      &lt;character length&gt; &lt;right paren&gt; | LONGVARCHAR [ &lt;left
      paren&gt; &lt;character length&gt; &lt;right paren&gt; ] | &lt;character
      large object type&gt;</literal></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;character large object type&gt; ::= { CHARACTER
      LARGE OBJECT | CHAR LARGE OBJECT | CLOB } [ &lt;left paren&gt;
      &lt;character large object length&gt; &lt;right paren&gt;
      ]</literal></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;character length&gt; ::= &lt;unsigned integer&gt;
      [ &lt;char length units&gt; ]</literal></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;large object length&gt; ::= &lt;length&gt; [
      &lt;multiplier&gt; ] | &lt;large object length
      token&gt;</literal></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;character large object length&gt; ::= &lt;large
      object length&gt; [ &lt;char length units&gt; ]</literal></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;large object length token&gt; ::= &lt;digit&gt;...
      &lt;multiplier&gt;</literal></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;multiplier&gt; ::= K | M | G </literal></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;char length units&gt; ::= CHARACTERS |
      OCTETS</literal></simpara>

      <programlisting>CHAR(10)
CHARACTER(10)
VARCHAR(2)
CHAR VARYING(2)
CLOB(1000)
CLOB(30K)
CHARACTER LARGE OBJECT(1M)
LONGVARCHAR
</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Binary String Types</title>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>BINARY types</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>The BINARY, BINARY VARYING and BLOB types are the SQL Standard
      binary string types. VARBINARY and BINARY LARGE OBJECT are synonyms for
      BINARY VARYING and BLOB types. HyperSQL also supports LONGVARBINARY as a
      synonym for VARBINARY.</para>

      <para>Binary string types are used in a similar way to character string
      types. There are several built-in functions that are overloaded to
      support character, binary and bit strings.</para>

      <para>The BINARY type represents a fixed width-string. Each shorter
      string is padded with zeros to fill the fixed width. Similar to the
      CHARACTER type, the trailing zeros in the BINARY string are simply
      discarded in some operations. For the same reason, it is best to avoid
      this particular type.</para>

      <para>If BINARY is used without specifying the length, the length
      defaults to 1. For the BLOB type, the length limit can be defined in
      units of kilobyte (K, 1024), megabyte (M, 1024 * 1024) or gigabyte (G,
      1024 * 1024 * 1024), using the <literal>&lt;multiplier&gt;</literal>. If
      BLOB is used without specifying the length, the length defaults to
      1M.</para>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;binary string type&gt; ::= BINARY [ &lt;left
      paren&gt; &lt;length&gt; &lt;right paren&gt; ] | { BINARY VARYING |
      VARBINARY } &lt;left paren&gt; &lt;length&gt; &lt;right paren&gt; |
      LONGVARBINARY [ &lt;left paren&gt; &lt;length&gt; &lt;right paren&gt; ]
      | &lt;binary large object string type&gt;</literal></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;binary large object string type&gt; ::= { BINARY
      LARGE OBJECT | BLOB } [ &lt;left paren&gt; &lt;large object length&gt;
      &lt;right paren&gt; ]</literal></simpara>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;length&gt; ::= &lt;unsigned
      integer&gt;</literal></simpara>

      <programlisting>BINARY(10)
VARBINARY(2)
BINARY VARYING(2)
BLOB(1000)
BLOB(30K)
BINARY LARGE OBJECT(1M)
LONGVARBINARY
</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Bit String Types</title>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>BIT types</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>The BIT and BIT VARYING types are the supported bit string types.
      These types were defined by SQL:1999 but were later removed from the
      Standard. Bit types represent bit maps of given lengths. Each bit is 0
      or 1. The BIT type represents a fixed width-string. Each shorter string
      is padded with zeros to fill the fixed with. If BIT is used without
      specifying the length, the length defaults to 1. The BIT VARYING type
      has a maximum width and shorter strings are not padded.</para>

      <para>Before the introduction of the BOOLEAN type to the SQL Standard, a
      sigle-bit string of the type BIT(1) was commonly used. For compatibility
      with other products that do not conform to, or extend, the SQL Standard,
      HyperSQL allows values of BIT and BIT VARYING types with length 1 to be
      converted to and from the BOOLEAN type. BOOLEAN TRUE is considered equal
      to B'1', BOOLEAN FALSE is considered equal to B'0'.</para>

      <para>For the same reason, numeric values can be assigned to columns and
      variables of the type BIT(1). For assignment, the numeric value zero is
      converted to B'0', while all other values are converted to B'1'. For
      comparison, numeric values 1 is considered equal to B'1' and numeric
      value zero is considered equal to B'0'.</para>

      <para>It is not allowed to perform other arithmetic or boolean
      operations involving BIT(1) and BIT VARYING(1). The kid of operations
      allowed on bit strings are analogous to those allowed on BINARY and
      CHARACTER strings. Several built-in functions support all three types of
      string.</para>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;bit string type&gt; ::= BIT [ &lt;left paren&gt;
      &lt;length&gt; &lt;right paren&gt; ] | BIT VARYING &lt;left paren&gt;
      &lt;length&gt; &lt;right paren&gt;</literal></simpara>

      <programlisting>BIT
BIT(10)
BIT VARYING(2)
</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Storage and Handling of Java Objects</title>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>OTHER type</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>Any serializable JAVA Object can be inserted directly into a
      column of type OTHER using any variation of
      <methodname>PreparedStatement.setObject()</methodname> methods.</para>

      <para>For comparison purposes and in indexes, any two Java Objects are
      considered equal unless one of them is NULL. You cannot search for a
      specific object or perform a join on a column of type OTHER.</para>

      <para>Please note that HSQLDB is not an object-relational database. Java
      Objects can simply be stored internally and no operations should be
      performed on them other than assignment between columns of type OTHER or
      tests for NULL. Tests such as <literal>WHERE object1 = object2
      </literal>do not mean what you might expect, as any non-null object
      would satisfy such a tests. But <literal>WHERE object1 IS NOT
      NULL</literal> is perfectly acceptable.</para>

      <para>The engine does not allow normal column values to be assigned to
      Java Object columns (for example, assigning an INTEGER or STRING to such
      a column with an SQL statement such as <literal>UPDATE mytable SET
      objectcol = intcol WHERE ...</literal>).</para>

      <simpara><literal>&lt;java object type&gt; ::= OTHER</literal></simpara>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Type Length, Precision and Scale</title>

      <para>In older version of HyperSQL, all table column type definitions
      with a column length, precision or scale qualifier were accepted and
      ignored. HSQLDB 1.8 enforced correctness but included an option to
      enforce the length, precision or scale.</para>

      <para>In HyperSQL 2.0, length, precision and scale qualifiers are always
      enforced. For backward compatibility, when older databases which had the
      property hsqldb.enforce_strict_size=false are converted to version 2.0,
      this property is retained. However, this is a temporary measure. You
      should test your application to ensure the length, precision and scale
      that is used for column definitions is appropriate for the application
      data. You can test with the default database setting, which enforces the
      sizes.</para>

      <para>String types, including all BIT, BINARY and CHAR string types plus
      CLOB and BLOB, are generally defined with a length. If no length is
      specified for BIT, BINARY and CHAR, the default length is 1. For CLOB
      and BLOB an implementation defined length of 1M is used.</para>

      <para>TIME and TIMESTAMP types can be defined with a fractional second
      precision between 0 and 9. INTERVAL type definition may have precision
      and, in some cases, fraction second precision. DECIMAL and NUMERIC types
      may be defined with precision and scale. For all of these types a
      default precision or scale value is used if one is not specified. The
      default scale is 0. The default fractional precision for TIME is 0,
      while it is 6 for TIMESTAMP.</para>

      <para>Values can be converted from one type to another in two different
      ways: by using explicit CAST expression or by implicit conversion used
      in assignment, comparison and aggregation.</para>

      <para>String values cannot be assigned to VARCHAR columns if they are
      longer than the defined type length. For CHARACTER columns, a long
      string can be assigned (with truncation) only if all the characters
      after the length are spaces. Shorter strings are padded with the space
      character when inserted into a CHARACTER column. Similar rules are
      applied to VARBINARY and BINARY columns. For BINARY columns, the padding
      and truncation rules are applied with zero bytes, instead of
      spaces.</para>

      <para>Explicit CAST of a value to a CHARACTER or VARCHAR type will
      result in forced truncation or padding. So a test such as <literal>CAST
      (mycol AS VARCHAR(2)) = 'xy'</literal> will find the values beginning
      with 'xy'. This is the equivalent of <literal>SUBSTRING(mycol FROM 1 FOR
      2)= 'xy'</literal>.</para>

      <para>For all numeric types, the rules of explicit cast and implicit
      conversion are the same. If cast or conversion causes any digits to be
      lost from the fractional part, it can take place. If the non-fractional
      part of the value cannot be represented in the new type, cast or
      conversion cannot take place and will result in a data exception.</para>

      <para>There are special rules for DATE, TIME, TIMESTAMP and INTERVAL
      casts and conversions.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Datetime types</title>

    <para>HSQLDB fully supports datetime and interval types and operations,
    including all relevant optional features, as specified by the SQL Standard
    since SQL-92. The two groups of types are complementary.</para>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>DATETIME types</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>The DATE type represents a calendar date with YEAR, MONTH and DAY
    fields.</para>

    <para>The TIME type represents time of day with HOUR, MINUTE and SECOND
    fields, plus an optional SECOND FRACTION field.</para>

    <para>The TIMESTAMP type represents the combination of DATE and TIME
    types.</para>

    <para>TIME and TIMESTAMP types can include WITH TIME ZONE or WITHOUT TIME
    ZONE (the default) qualifiers. They can have fractional second parts. For
    example, TIME(6) has six fractional digits for the second field.</para>

    <para>If fractional second precision is not specified, it defaults to 0
    for TIME and to 6 for TIMESTAMP.</para>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;datetime type&gt; ::= DATE | TIME [ &lt;left
    paren&gt; &lt;time precision&gt; &lt;right paren&gt; ] [ &lt;with or
    without time zone&gt; ] | TIMESTAMP [ &lt;left paren&gt; &lt;timestamp
    precision&gt; &lt;right paren&gt; ] [ &lt;with or without time zone&gt;
    ]</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;with or without time zone&gt; ::= WITH TIME ZONE |
    WITHOUT TIME ZONE</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;time precision&gt; ::= &lt;time fractional seconds
    precision&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;timestamp precision&gt; ::= &lt;time fractional
    seconds precision&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;time fractional seconds precision&gt; ::=
    &lt;unsigned integer&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <programlisting>DATE
TIME(6)
TIMESTAMP(2) WITH TIME ZONE
</programlisting>

    <para>Examples of the string literals used to represent date time values,
    some with time zone, some without, are below:</para>

    <programlisting>DATE '2008-08-22'
TIMESTAMP '2008-08-08 20:08:08'
TIMESTAMP '2008-08-08 20:08:08+8:00' /* Beijing */
TIME '20:08:08.034900'
TIME '20:08:08.034900-8:00' /* US Pacific */</programlisting>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>Time Zone</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Time Zone</emphasis></simpara>

    <para>DATE values do not take time zones. For example United Nations
    designates 5 June as World Environment Day, which was observed on DATE
    '2008-06-05' in different time zones.</para>

    <para>TIME and TIMESTAMP values without time zone, usually have a context
    that indicates some local time zone. For example, a database for college
    course timetables usually stores class dates and times without time zones.
    This works because the location of the college is fixed and the time zone
    displacement is the same for all the values. Even when the events take
    place in different time zones, for example international flight times, it
    is possible to store all the datetime information as references to a
    single time zone, usually GMT. For some databases it may be useful to
    store the time zone displacement together with each datetime value. SQL’s
    TIME WITH TIME ZONE and TIMESTAMP WITH TIME ZONE values include a time
    zone displacement value.</para>

    <para>The time zone displacement is of the type INTERVAL HOUR TO MINUTE.
    This data type is described in the next section. The legal values are
    between '–14:00' and   '+14:00'.</para>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>Datetime Operations</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Operations on Datetime
    Types</emphasis></simpara>

    <para>The expression <literal>&lt;datetime expression&gt; AT TIME ZONE
    &lt;time displacement&gt;</literal> evaluates to a datetime value
    representing exactly the same point of time in the specified
    <literal>&lt;time displacement&gt;</literal>. The expression, <literal>AT
    LOCAL</literal> is equivalent to <literal>AT TIME ZONE &lt;local time
    displacement&gt;</literal>. If <literal>AT TIME ZONE</literal> is used
    with a datetime operand of type WITHOUT TIME ZONE, the operand is first
    converted to a value of type WITH TIME ZONE at the session’s time
    displacement, then the specified time zone displacement is set for the
    value. Therefore, in these cases, the final value depends on the time zone
    of the session in which the statement was used.</para>

    <para>AT TIME ZONE, modifies the field values of the datetime operand.
    This is done by the following procedure:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>determine the corresponding datetime at UTC.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>find the datetime value at the given time zone that corresponds
        with the UTC value from step 1.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>Example a:</para>

    <programlisting>TIME '12:00:00' AT TIME ZONE INTERVAL '1:00' HOUR TO MINUTE
</programlisting>

    <para>If the session’s time zone displacement is -'8:00', then in step 1,
    TIME '12:00:00' is converted to UTC, which is TIME '20:00:00+0:00'. In
    step 2, this value is expressed as TIME '21:00:00+1:00'.</para>

    <para>Example b:</para>

    <programlisting>TIME '12:00:00-5:00' AT TIME ZONE INTERVAL '1:00' HOUR TO MINUTE
</programlisting>

    <para>Because the operand has a time zone, the result is independent of
    the session  time zone displacement. Step 1 results in TIME
    '17:00:00+0:00', and step 2 results in TIME '18:00:00+1:00'</para>

    <para>Note that the operand is not limited to datetime literals used in
    these examples. Any valid expression that evaluates to a datetime value
    can be the operand.</para>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Type Conversion</emphasis></simpara>

    <para>CAST is used to for all other conversions. Examples:</para>

    <programlisting>CAST (&lt;value&gt; AS TIME WITHOUT TIME ZONE)
CAST (&lt;value&gt; AS TIME WITH TIME ZONE)</programlisting>

    <para>In the first example, if <literal>&lt;value&gt;</literal> has a time
    zone component, it is simply dropped. For example TIME '12:00:00-5:00' is
    converted to TIME '12:00:00'</para>

    <para>In the second example, if <literal>&lt;value&gt;</literal> has no
    time zone component, the current time zone displacement of the session is
    added. For example TIME '12:00:00' is converted to TIME '12:00:00-8:00'
    when the session time zone displacement is '-8:00'.</para>

    <para>Conversion between DATE and TIMESTAMP is performed by removing the
    TIME component of a TIMESTAMP value or by setting the hour, minute and
    second fields to zero. TIMESTAMP '2008-08-08 20:08:08+8:00' becomes DATE
    '2008-08-08', while DATE '2008-08-22' becomes TIMESTAMP '2008-08-22
    00:00:00'.</para>

    <para>Conversion between TIME and TIMESTAMP is performed by removing the
    DATE field values of a TIMESTAMP value or by appending the fields of the
    TIME value to the fields of the current session date value.</para>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Assignment</emphasis></simpara>

    <para>When a value is assigned to a datetime target, e.g., a value is used
    to update a row of a table, the type of the value must be the same as the
    target, but the WITH TIME ZONE or WITHOUT TIME ZONE characteristics can be
    different. If the types are not the same, an explicit CAST must be used to
    convert the value into the target type.</para>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Comparison</emphasis></simpara>

    <para>When values WITH TIME ZONE are compared, they are converted to UTC
    values before comparison. If a value WITH TIME ZONE is compared to another
    WITHOUT TIME ZONE, then the WITH TIME ZONE value is converted to AT LOCAL,
    then converted to WITHOUT TIME ZONE before comparison.</para>

    <para>It is not recommended to design applications that rely on
    comparisons and conversions between TIME values WITH TIME ZONE. The
    conversions may involve normalisation of the time value, resulting in
    unexpected results. For example, the expression: BETWEEN(TIME
    '12:00:00-8:00', TIME '22:00:00-8:00') is converted to BETWEEN(TIME
    '20:00:00+0:00', TIME '06:00:00+0:00') when it is evaluated in the UTC
    zone, which is always FALSE.</para>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Functions</emphasis></simpara>

    <para>Several functions return the current session timestamp in different
    datetime types:</para>

    <informaltable frame="all">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><para>CURRENT_DATE</para></entry>

            <entry><para>DATE</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>CURRENT_TIME</para></entry>

            <entry><para>TIME WITH TIME ZONE</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>CURRENT_TIMESTAMP</para></entry>

            <entry><para>TIMESTAMP WITH TIME ZONE</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>LOCALTIME</para></entry>

            <entry><para>TIMESTAMP WITHOUT TIME ZONE</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>LOCALTIMESTAMP</para></entry>

            <entry><para>TIMESTAMP WITHOUT TIME ZONE</para></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Session Time Zone
    Displacement</emphasis></simpara>

    <para>When an SQL session is started (with a JDBC connection) the local
    time zone of the client JVM (including any seasonal time adjustments such
    as daylight saving time) is used as the session time zone displacement.
    Note that the SQL session time displacement is not changed when a seasonal
    time adjustment takes place while the session is open. To change the SQL
    session time zone displacement use the following commands:</para>

    <simpara><literal>SET TIME ZONE &lt;time
    displacement&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>SET TIME ZONE LOCAL</literal></simpara>

    <para>The first command sets the displacement to the given value. The
    second command restores the original, real time zone displacement of the
    session.</para>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Datetime Values and
    Java</emphasis></simpara>

    <para>When datetime values are sent to the database using the
    <classname>PreparedStatement</classname> or
    <classname>CallableStatement</classname> interfaces, the Java object is
    converted to the type of the prepared or callable statement parameter.
    This type may be DATE, TIME, or TIMESTAMP (with or without time zone). The
    time zone displacement is the time zone of the JDBC session.</para>

    <para>When datetime values are retrieved from the database using the
    <literal>ResultSet</literal> interface, there are two representations. The
    <methodname>getString(…)</methodname> methods of the
    <classname>ResultSet</classname> interface, return an exact representation
    of the value in the SQL type as it is stored in the database. This
    includes the correct number of digits for the fractional second field, and
    for values with time zone displacement, the time zone displacement.
    Therefore if TIME '12:00:00' is stored in the database, all users in
    different time zones will get '12:00:00' when they retrieve the value as a
    string. The <methodname>getTime(…)</methodname> and
    <methodname>getTimestamp(…)</methodname> methods of the
    <classname>ResultSet</classname> interface return Java objects that are
    corrected for the session time zone. The UTC millisecond value contained
    the <classname>java.sql.Time</classname> or
    <classname>java.sql.Timestamp</classname> objects will be adjusted to the
    time zone of the session, therefore the
    <methodname>toString()</methodname> method of these objects return the
    same values in different time zones.</para>

    <para>If you want to store and retrieve UTC values that are independent of
    any session's time zone, you can use a TIMESTAMP WITH TIME ZONE column.
    The setTime(...) and setTimestamp(...) methods of the PreparedStatement
    interface which have a Calendar parameter can be used to assign the
    values. The time zone of the given Calendar argument is used as the time
    zone. Conversely, the getTime(...) and getTimestamp(...) methods of the
    ResultSet interface which have a Calendar parameter can be used with a
    Calendar argument to retrieve the values.</para>

    <para>JDBC has an unfortunate limitation and does not include type codes
    for SQL datetime types that have a TIME ZONE property. Therefore, for
    compatibility with database tools that are limited to the JDBC type codes,
    HyperSQL reports these types by default as datetime types without TIME
    ZONE. You can use the URL property
    <literal>hsqldb.translate_dti_types=false</literal> to override the
    default behaviour.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Interval Types</title>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>INTERVAL types</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>Interval types are used to represent differences between date time
    values. The difference between two date time values can be measured in
    seconds or in months. For measurements in months, the units YEAR and MONTH
    are available, while for measurements in seconds, the units DAY, HOUR,
    MINUTE, SECOND are available. The units can be used individually, or as a
    range. An interval type can specify the precision of the most significant
    field and the second fraction digits of the SECOND field (if it has a
    SECOND field). The default precision is 2. The default second precision is
    0.</para>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;interval type&gt; ::= INTERVAL &lt;interval
    qualifier&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;interval qualifier&gt; ::= &lt;start field&gt; TO
    &lt;end field&gt; | &lt;single datetime field&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;start field&gt; ::= &lt;non-second primary datetime
    field&gt; [ &lt;left paren&gt; &lt;interval leading field precision&gt;
    &lt;right paren&gt; ]</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;end field&gt; ::= &lt;non-second primary datetime
    field&gt; | SECOND [ &lt;left paren&gt; &lt;interval fractional seconds
    precision&gt; &lt;right paren&gt; ]</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;single datetime field&gt; ::= &lt;non-second primary
    datetime field&gt; [ &lt;left paren&gt; &lt;interval leading field
    precision&gt; &lt;right paren&gt; ] | SECOND [ &lt;left paren&gt;
    &lt;interval leading field precision&gt; [ &lt;comma&gt; &lt;interval
    fractional seconds precision&gt; ] &lt;right paren&gt;
    ]</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;primary datetime field&gt; ::= &lt;non-second
    primary datetime field&gt; | SECOND</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;non-second primary datetime field&gt; ::= YEAR |
    MONTH | DAY | HOUR | MINUTE</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;interval fractional seconds precision&gt; ::=
    &lt;unsigned integer&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;interval leading field precision&gt; ::=
    &lt;unsigned integer&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <para>Examples of INTERVAL type definition:</para>

    <programlisting>INTERVAL YEAR TO MONTH
INTERVAL YEAR(3)
INTERVAL DAY(4) TO HOUR
INTERVAL MINUTE(4) TO SECOND(6)
INTERVAL SECOND(4,6)
</programlisting>

    <para>The word INTERVAL indicates the general type name. The rest of the
    definition is called an <literal>&lt;interval qualifier&gt;</literal>.
    This designation is important, as in most expressions
    <literal>&lt;interval qualifier&gt;</literal> is used without the word
    INTERVAL.</para>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Interval Values</emphasis></simpara>

    <para>An interval value can be negative, positive or zero. An interval
    type has all the datetime fields in the specified range. These fields are
    similar to those in the TIMESTAMP type. The differences are as
    follows:</para>

    <para>The first field of an interval value can hold any numeric value up
    to the specified precision. For example, the hour field in HOUR(2) TO
    SECOND can hold values above 23 (up to 99). The year and month fields can
    hold zero (unlike a TIMESTAMP value) and the maximum value of a month
    field that is not the most significant field, is 11.</para>

    <para>The standard function <literal>ABS(&lt;interval value
    expression&gt;)</literal> can be used to convert a negative interval value
    to a positive one.</para>

    <para>The literal representation of interval values consists of the type
    definition, with a string representing the interval value inserted after
    the word INTERVAL. Some examples of interval literal below:</para>

    <programlisting>INTERVAL '145 23:12:19.345' DAY(3) TO SECOND(3)
INTERVAL '3503:12:19.345' HOUR TO SECOND(3) /* equal to the first value */
INTERVAL '19.345' SECOND(4,3) /* maximum number of digits for the second value is 4, and each value is expressed with three fraction digits. */
INTERVAL '-23-10' YEAR(2) TO MONTH
</programlisting>

    <para>Interval values of the types that are based on seconds can be cast
    into one another. Similarly those that are based on months can be cast
    into one another. It is not possible to cast or convert a value based on
    seconds to one based on months, or vice versa.</para>

    <para>When a cast is performed to a type with a smaller least-significant
    field, nothing is lost from the interval value. Otherwise, the values for
    the missing least-significant fields are discarded. Examples:</para>

    <programlisting>CAST ( INTERVAL '145 23:12:19' DAY TO SECOND AS INTERVAL DAY TO HOUR ) = INTERVAL '145 23' DAY TO HOUR
CAST(INTERVAL '145 23' DAY TO HOUR AS INTERVAL DAY TO SECOND) = INTERVAL '145 23:00:00' DAY TO SECOND
</programlisting>

    <para>A numeric value can be cast to an interval type. In this case the
    numeric value is first converted to a single-field INTERVAL type with the
    same field as the least significant field of the target interval type.
    This value is then converted to the target interval type For example CAST(
    22 AS INTERVAL YEAR TO MONTH) evaluates to INTERVAL '22' MONTH and then
    INTERVAL '1 10' YEAR TO MONTH. Note that SQL Standard only supports casts
    to single-field INTERVAL types, while HyperSQL allows casting to
    multi-field types as well.</para>

    <para>An interval value can be cast to a numeric type. In this case the
    interval value is first converted to a single-field INTERVAL type with the
    same field as the least significant filed of the interval value. The value
    is then converted to the target type. For example CAST (INTERVAL '1-11'
    YEAR TO MONTH AS INT) evaluates to INTERVAL '23' MONTH, and then
    23.</para>

    <para>An interval value can be cast into a character type, which results
    in an INTERVAL literal. A character value can be cast into an INTERVAL
    type so long as it is a string with a format compatible with an INTERVAL
    literal.</para>

    <para>Two interval values can be added or subtracted so long as the types
    of both are based on the same field, i.e., both are based on MONTH or
    SECOND. The values are both converted to a single-field interval type with
    same field as the least-significant field between the two types. After
    addition or subtraction, the result is converted to an interval type that
    contains all the fields of the two original types.</para>

    <para>An interval value can be multiplied or divided by a numeric value.
    Again, the value is converted to a numeric, which is then multiplied or
    divided, before converting back to the original interval type.</para>

    <para>An interval value is negated by simply prefixing with the minus
    sign.</para>

    <para>Interval values used in expressions are either typed values,
    including interval literals, or are interval casts. The expression:
    <literal>&lt;expression&gt; &lt;interval qualifier&gt;</literal> is a cast
    of the result of the <literal>&lt;expression&gt;</literal> into the
    INTERVAL type specified by the <literal>&lt;interval qualifier&gt;. The
    cast can be formed by adding the keywords and parentheses as follows: CAST
    ( &lt;expression&gt; AS INTERVAL &lt;interval qualifier&gt;
    ).</literal></para>

    <para><literal>The examples below feature different forms of expression
    that represent an interval value, which is then added to the given date
    literal.</literal></para>

    <programlisting>DATE '2000-01-01' + INTERVAL '1-10' YEAR TO MONTH /* interval literal */
DATE '2000-01-01' + '1-10' YEAR TO MONTH /* the string '1-10' is cast into INTERVAL YEAR TO MONTH */
DATE '2000-01-01' + 22 MONTH /* the integer 22 is cast into INTERVAL MONTH, same value as above */
DATE '2000-01-01' - 22 DAY /* the integer 22 is cast into INTERVAL DAY */
DATE '2000-01-01' + COL2 /* the type of COL2 must be an INTERVAL type */
DATE '2000-01-01' + COL2 MONTH /* COL2 may be a number, it is cast into a MONTH interval */
</programlisting>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Datetime and Interval
    Operations</emphasis></simpara>

    <para>An interval can be added to or subtracted from a datetime value so
    long as they have some fields in common. For example, an INTERVAL MONTH
    cannot be added to a TIME value, while an INTERVAL HOUR TO SECOND can. The
    interval is first converted to a numeric value, then the value is added
    to, or subtracted from, the corresponding field of the datetime
    value.</para>

    <para>If the result of addition or subtraction is beyond the permissible
    range for the field, the field value is normalised and carried over to the
    next significant field until all the fields are normalised. For example,
    adding 20 minutes to TIME '23:50:10' will result successively in
    '23:70:10', '24:10:10' and finally TIME '00:10:10'. Subtracting 20 minutes
    from the result is performed as follows: '00:-10:10', '-1:50:10', finally
    TIME '23:50:10'. Note that if DATE or TIMESTAMP normalisation results in
    the YEAR field value out of the range (1,1000), then an exception
    condition is raised.</para>

    <para>If an interval value based on MONTH is added to, or subtracted from
    a DATE or TIMESTAMP value, the result may have an invalid day (30 or 31)
    for the given result month. In this case an exception condition is
    raised.</para>

    <para>The result of subtraction of two datetime expressions is an interval
    value. The two datetime expressions must be of the same type. The type of
    the interval value must be specified in the expression, using only the
    interval field names. The two datetime expressions are enclosed in
    parentheses, followed by the <literal>&lt;interval qualifier&gt;</literal>
    fields. In the first example below, COL1 and COL2 are of the same datetime
    type, and the result is evaluated in INTERVAL YEAR TO MONTH type.</para>

    <programlisting>(COL1 – COL2) YEAR TO MONTH /* the difference between two DATE or two TIEMSTAMP values in years and months */
(CURRENT_DATE – COL3) DAY /* the number of days between the value of COL3 and the current date */
(CURRENT_DATE - DATE '2000-01-01') YEAR TO MONTH /* the number of years and months since the beginning of this century */
CURRENT_DATE - 2 DAY /* the date of the day before yesterday */
(CURRENT_TIMESTAMP - TIMESTAMP '2009-01-01 00:00:00') DAY(4) TO SECOND(2) /* days to seconds since the given date */
</programlisting>

    <para>The individual fields of both datetime and interval values can be
    extracted using the EXTRACT function. The same function can also be used
    to extract the time zone displacement fields of a datetime value.</para>

    <simpara><literal>EXTRACT ({YEAR | MONTH | DAY | HOUR | MINUTE | SECOND |
    TIMEZONE_HOUR | TIMEZONE_MINUTE | DAY_OF_WEEK | WEEK_OF_YEAR } FROM
    {&lt;datetime value&gt; | &lt;interval value&gt;})</literal></simpara>

    <para>The dichotomy between interval types based on seconds, and those
    based on months, stems from the fact that the different calendar months
    have different numbers of days. For example, the expression, “nine months
    and nine days since an event” is not exact when the date of the event is
    unknown. It can represent a period of around 284 days give or take one.
    SQL interval values are independent of any start or end dates or times.
    However, when they are added to or subtracted from certain date or
    timestamp values, the result may be invalid and cause an exception (e.g.
    adding one month to January 30 results in February 30, which is
    invalid).</para>

    <para>JDBC has an unfortunate limitation and does not include type codes
    for SQL INTERVAL types. Therefore, for compatibility with database tools
    that are limited to the JDBC type codes, HyperSQL reports these types by
    default as VARCHAR. You can use the URL property
    <literal>hsqldb.translate_dti_types=false</literal> to override the
    default behaviour.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Arrays</title>

    <para>Array are a powerful feature of SQL:2008 and can help solve many
    common problems. Arrays should not be used as a substitute for
    tables.</para>

    <para>HyperSQL supports arrays of values according to the SQL:2008
    Standard.</para>

    <para>Elements of the array are either NULL, or of the same data type. It
    is possible to define arrays of all supported types, including the types
    covered in this chapter and user defined types, except LOB types. An SQL
    array is one dimensional and is addressed from position 1. An empty array
    can also be used, which has no element.</para>

    <para>Arrays can be stored in the database, as well as being used as
    temporary containers of values for simplifying SQL statements. They
    facilitate data exchange between the SQL engine and the user's
    application.</para>

    <para>The full range of supported syntax allows array to be created, used
    in SELECT or other statements, combined with rows of tables and used in
    routine calls.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Array Definition</title>

      <para>The type of a table column, a routine parameter, a variable, or
      the return value of a function can be defined as an array.</para>

      <para><literal>&lt;array type&gt; ::= &lt;data type&gt; ARRAY [ &lt;left
      bracket or trigraph&gt; &lt;maximum cardinality&gt; &lt;right bracket or
      trigraph&gt; ]</literal></para>

      <para>The word ARRAY is added to any valid type definition except BLOB
      and CLOB type definitions. If the optional <literal>&lt;maximum
      cardinality&gt;</literal> is not used, the default value is 1024. The
      size of the array cannot be extended beyond maximum cardinality.</para>

      <para>In the example below, the table contains a column of integer
      arrays and a column of varchar arrays. The VARCHAR array has an explicit
      maximum size of 10, which means each array can have between 0 and 10
      elements. The INTEGER array has the default maximum size of 1024. The id
      column has a default clause with an empty array. The default clause can
      be defined only as DEFAULT NULL or DEFAULT ARRAY[] and does not allow
      arrays containing elements.</para>

      <informalexample>
        <programlisting>CREATE TABLE t (id INT PRIMARY KEY, scores INT ARRAY DEFAULT ARRAY[], names VARCHAR(20) ARRAY[10])</programlisting>
      </informalexample>

      <para>An array can be constructed from value expressions or a query
      expression.</para>

      <para><literal>&lt;array value constructor by enumeration&gt; ::= ARRAY
      &lt;left bracket or trigraph&gt; &lt;array element list&gt; &lt;right
      bracket or trigraph&gt;</literal></para>

      <para><literal>&lt;array element list&gt; ::= &lt;value expression&gt; [
      { &lt;comma&gt; &lt;value expression&gt; }... ]</literal></para>

      <para><literal>&lt;array value constructor by query&gt; ::= ARRAY
      &lt;left paren&gt; &lt;query expression&gt; [ &lt;order by clause&gt; ]
      &lt;right paren&gt;</literal></para>

      <para>In the examples below, arrays are constructed from values, column
      references or variables, function calls, or query expressions.</para>

      <informalexample>
        <programlisting>ARRAY [ 1, 2, 3 ]
ARRAY [ 'HOT', 'COLD' ]
ARRAY [ var1, var2, CURRENT_DATE ]
ARRAY (SELECT lastname FROM namestable ORDER BY id)
</programlisting>
      </informalexample>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Array Reference</title>

      <para>The most common operations on an array element reference and
      assignment, which are used when reading or writing an element of the
      array. Unlike Java and many other languages, arrays are extended if an
      element is assigned to an index beyond the current length. This can
      result in gaps containing NULL elements. Array length cannot exceed the
      maximum cardinality.</para>

      <para>Elements of all arrays, including those that are the result of
      function calls or other operations can be referenced for reading.</para>

      <para><literal>&lt;array element reference&gt; ::= &lt;array value
      expression&gt; &lt;left bracket&gt; &lt;numeric value expression&gt;
      &lt;right bracket&gt;</literal></para>

      <para>Elements of arrays that are table columns or routine variables can
      be referenced for writing. This is done in a SET statement, either
      inside an UPDATE statement, or as a separate statement in the case of
      routine variables, OUT and INOUT parameters.</para>

      <para><literal>&lt;target array element specification&gt; ::= &lt;target
      array reference&gt; &lt;left bracket or trigraph&gt; &lt;simple value
      specification&gt; &lt;right bracket or trigraph&gt;</literal></para>

      <para><literal>&lt;target array reference&gt; ::= &lt;SQL parameter
      reference&gt; | &lt;column reference&gt;</literal></para>

      <para>Note that only simple values or variables are allowed for the
      array index when an assignment is performed. The examples below
      demonstrates how elements of the array are referenced in SELECT and an
      UPDATE statement.</para>

      <para><informalexample>
          <programlisting>SELECT scores[ranking], names[ranking] FROM t JOIN t1 on (t.id = t1.tid)
UPDATE t SET scores[2] = 123, names[2] = 'Reds' WHERE id = 10
</programlisting>
        </informalexample></para>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Array Operations</title>

      <para>Several SQL operations and functions can be used with
      arrays.</para>

      <para><emphasis>CONCATENATION</emphasis></para>

      <para>Array concatenation is performed similar to string concatenation.
      All elements of the array on the right are appended to the array on
      left.</para>

      <para><literal>&lt;array concatenation&gt; ::= &lt;array value
      expression 1&gt; &lt;concatenation operator&gt; &lt;array value
      expression 2&gt;</literal></para>

      <para><literal>&lt;concatenation operator&gt; ::= ||</literal></para>

      <para><emphasis>FUNCTIONS</emphasis></para>

      <para>Three functions operate on arrays. Details are described in the
      <link endterm="builtinfunctions-title"
      xlink:href="#builtinfunctions-chapt"></link> chapter.</para>

      <para><literal>CARDINALITY &lt;left paren&gt; &lt;array value
      expression&gt; &lt;right paren&gt;</literal></para>

      <para><literal>MAX_CARDINALITY &lt;left paren&gt; &lt;array value
      expression&gt; &lt;right paren&gt;</literal></para>

      <para>Array cardinality and max cardinality are functions that return an
      integer. CARDINALITY returns the element count, while MAX_CARDINALITY
      returns the maximum declared cardinality of an array.</para>

      <para><literal>TRIM_ARRAY &lt;left paren&gt; &lt;array value
      expression&gt; &lt;comma&gt; &lt;numeric value expression&gt; &lt;right
      paren&gt;</literal></para>

      <para>The TRIM_ARRAY function returns a copy of an array with the
      specified number of elements removed from the end of the array. The
      <literal>&lt;array value expression&gt;</literal> can be any expression
      that evaluates to an array.</para>

      <para><emphasis>CAST</emphasis></para>

      <para>An array can be cast into an array of a different type. Each
      element of the array is cast into the element type of the target array
      type.</para>

      <para><emphasis>UNNEST</emphasis></para>

      <para>Arrays can be converted into table references with the UNNEST
      keyword.</para>

      <para><literal>UNNEST(&lt;array value expression&gt;) [ WITH ORDINALITY
      ]</literal></para>

      <para>The <literal>&lt;array value expression&gt;</literal> can be any
      expression that evaluates to an array. A table is returned that contains
      one column when WITH ORDINALITY is not used, or two columns when WITH
      ORDINALITY is used. The first column contains the elements of the array
      (including all the nulls). When the table has two columns, the second
      column contains the ordinal position of the element in the array. When
      UNNEST is used in the FROM clause of a query, it implies the LATERAL
      keyword, which means the array that is converted to table can belong to
      any table that precedes the UNNEST in the FROM clause. This is explained
      in the <link endterm="dataaccess-title" xlink:arcrole=""
      xlink:href="#dataaccess-chapt"></link> chapter.</para>

      <para><emphasis>COMPARISON</emphasis></para>

      <para>Arrays can be compared for equality, but they cannot be compared
      for ordering or ranges. Array expressions are therefore not allowed in
      an ORDER BY clause, or in a comparison expression such as GREATER THAN.
      Two arrays are equal if they have the same length and the values at each
      index position are either equal or both NULL.</para>

      <para><emphasis>USER DEFINED FUNCTIONS and PROCEDURES</emphasis></para>

      <para>Array parameters, variables and return values can be specified in
      user defined functions and procedures, including aggregate functions. An
      aggregate function can return an array that contains all the scalar
      values that have been aggregated. These capabilities allow a wider range
      of applications to be covered by user defined functions and easier data
      exchange between the engine and the user's application.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="sqlgeneral_constr_indexes-sect">
    <title>Indexes and Query Speed</title>

    <para>HyperSQL supports PRIMARY KEY, UNIQUE and FOREIGN KEY constraints,
    which can span multiple columns.</para>

    <para>The engine creates indexes internally to support PRIMARY KEY, UNIQUE
    and FOREIGN KEY constraints: a unique index is created for each PRIMARY
    KEY or UNIQUE constraint; an ordinary index is created for each FOREIGN
    KEY constraint.</para>

    <para>HyperSQL allows defining indexes on single or multiple columns. You
    should not create duplicate user-defined indexes on the same column sets
    covered by constraints. This would result in unnecessary memory and speed
    overheads. See the discussion in the <link endterm="deployment-title"
    xlink:arcrole="" xlink:href="#deployment-chapt"></link> chapter for more
    information.</para>

    <para>Indexes are crucial for adequate query speed. When range or equality
    conditions are used e.g. <literal>SELECT ... WHERE acol &gt; 10 AND bcol =
    0</literal>, an index should exist on one of the columns that has a
    condition. In this example, the <literal>bcol</literal> column is the best
    candidate. HyperSQL always uses the best condition and index. If there are
    two indexes, one on acol, and another on bcol, it will choose the index on
    bcol.</para>

    <para>Queries always return results whether indexes exist or not, but they
    return much faster when an index exists. As a rule of thumb, HSQLDB is
    capable of internal processing of queries at over 100,000 rows per second.
    Any query that runs into several seconds is clearly accessing thousands of
    rows. The query should be checked and indexes should be added to the
    relevant columns of the tables if necessary. The EXPLAIN PLAN
    &lt;query&gt; statement can be used to see which indexes are used to
    process the query.</para>

    <para>When executing a DELETE or UPDATE statement, the engine needs to
    find the rows that are to be deleted or updated. If there is an index on
    one of the columns in the WHERE clause, it is often possible to start
    directly from the first candidate row. Otherwise all the rows of the table
    have to be examined.</para>

    <para>Indexes are even more important in joins between multiple tables.
    <literal>SELECT ... FROM t1 JOIN t2 ON t1.c1 = t2.c2 </literal> is
    performed by taking rows of t1 one by one and finding a matching row in
    t2. If there is no index on t2.c2 then for each row of t1, all the rows of
    t2 must be checked. Whereas with an index, a matching row can be found in
    a fraction of the time. If the query also has a condition on t1, e.g.,
    <literal>SELECT ... FROM t1 JOIN t2 ON t1.c1 = t2.c2 WHERE t1.c3 =
    4</literal> then an index on t1.c3 would eliminate the need for checking
    all the rows of t1 one by one, and will reduce query time to less than a
    millisecond per returned row. So if t1 and t2 each contain 10,000 rows,
    the query without indexes involves checking 100,000,000 row combinations.
    With an index on t2.c2, this is reduced to 10,000 row checks and index
    lookups. With the additional index on t2.c2, only about 4 rows are checked
    to get the first result row.</para>

    <para>Note that in HSQLDB an index on multiple columns can be used
    internally as a non-unique index on the first column in the list. For
    example: <literal>CONSTRAINT name1 UNIQUE (c1, c2, c3); </literal> means
    there is the equivalent of <literal>CREATE INDEX name2 ON
    atable(c1);</literal>. So you do not need to specify an extra index if you
    require one on the first column of the list.</para>

    <para>In HyperSQL 2.0, a multi-column index will speed up queries that
    contain joins or values on the first n columns of the index. You need NOT
    declare additional individual indexes on those columns unless you use
    queries that search only on a subset of the columns. For example, rows of
    a table that has a PRIMARY KEY or UNIQUE constraint on three columns or
    simply an ordinary index on those columns can be found efficiently when
    values for all three columns, or the first two columns, or the first
    column, are specified in the WHERE clause. For example, <literal>SELECT
    ... FROM t1 WHERE t1.c1 = 4 AND t1.c2 = 6 AND t1.c3 = 8 </literal>will use
    an index on <literal>t1(c1,c2,c3)</literal> if it exists.</para>

    <para>A multi-column index will not speed up queries on the second or
    third column only. The first column must be specified in the JOIN .. ON or
    WHERE conditions.</para>

    <para>Sometimes query speed depends on the order of the tables in the JOIN
    .. ON or FROM clauses. For example the second query below should be faster
    with large tables (provided there is an index on
    <literal>TB.COL3</literal>). The reason is that <literal>TB.COL3</literal>
    can be evaluated very quickly if it applies to the first table (and there
    is an index on <literal>TB.COL3</literal>):</para>

    <informalexample>
      <programlisting>    (TB is a very large table with only a few rows where TB.COL3 = 4)

    SELECT * FROM TA JOIN TB ON TA.COL1 = TB.COL2 AND TB.COL3 = 4;

    SELECT * FROM TB JOIN TA ON TA.COL1 = TB.COL2 AND TB.COL3 = 4;</programlisting>
    </informalexample>

    <para>The general rule is to put first the table that has a narrowing
    condition on one of its columns.</para>

    <para>HyperSQL features automatic, on-the-fly indexes for views and
    subselects that are used in a query.</para>

    <para>Indexes have no effect on some LIKE conditions.</para>

    <para>Indexes are used for ORDER BY clauses if the same index is used for
    selection and ordering of rows.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Query Processing and Optimisation</title>

    <para>HyperSQL does not change the order of tables in a query in order to
    optimise processing. As mentioned in the previous section, the table that
    has a narrowing condition should be the first table in the query.</para>

    <para>HyperSQL optimises queries to use indexes, for all types of range
    and equality conditions, including IS NULL and NOT NULL conditions.
    Conditions can be in join or WHERE clauses, including all types of
    joins.</para>

    <para>In addition, HyperSQL will always use an index (if one exists) for
    IN conditions, whether constants, variable, or subqueries are used on the
    right hand side of the IN predicate.</para>

    <para>HyperSQL can always use indexes when several conditions are combined
    with the AND operator, choosing a conditions which can use an index. This
    now extended to all equality conditions on multiple columns that are part
    of an index.</para>

    <para>HyperSQL will also use indexes when several conditions are combined
    with the OR operator and each condition can use an index (each condition
    may use a different index). For example, if a huge table has two separate
    columns for first name and last name, and both columns are indexed, a
    query such as the following example will use the indexes and complete in a
    short time:</para>

    <informalexample>
      <programlisting>    (TC is a very large table)

    SELECT * FROM TC WHERE TC.FIRSTNAME = 'John' OR TC.LASTNAME = 'Smith' OR TC.LASTNAME = 'Williams'
</programlisting>
    </informalexample>

    <para>HyperSQL optimises simple row count queries in the form of
    <literal>SELECT COUNT(*) FROM &lt;table&gt;</literal> and returns the
    result immediately (this optimisation does not take place in MVCC
    mode).</para>

    <para>HyperSQL can use an index on a column for <literal>SELECT
    MAX(&lt;column&gt;) FROM &lt;table&gt;</literal> and <literal>SELECT
    MIN(&lt;column&gt;) FROM &lt;table&gt;</literal> queries. There should be
    an index on the &lt;column&gt; and the query can have a WHERE condition on
    the same column. In the example below the maximum value for the TB.COL3
    below 1000000 is returned.</para>

    <informalexample>
      <programlisting>    SELECT MAX(TB.COL3) FROM TB WHERE TB.COL &lt; 1000000
</programlisting>
    </informalexample>

    <para>HyperSQL can use an index on an ORDER BY clause if all the columns
    in ORDER BY are in a single-column or multi-column index (in the exact
    order). This is important if there is a LIMIT n (or FETCH n ROWS ONLY)
    clause. In this situation, the use of index allows the query processor to
    access only the number of rows specified in the LIMIT clause, instead of
    building the whole result set, which can be huge. This also works for
    joined tables when the ORDER BY clause is on the columns of the first
    table in a join. Indexes are used in the same way when ORDER BY ... DESC
    is specified in the query. Note that unlike other RDBMS, HyperSQL does not
    create DESC indexes. It can use any index for ORDER BY ... DESC.</para>

    <para>If there is an equality or range condition (e.g. EQUALS, GREATER
    THAN) condition on the columns specified in the ORDER BY clause, the index
    is still used. But if the query contains an equality condition on another
    indexed column in the table, this may take precedence and no index may be
    used for ORDER BY.</para>

    <para>In the two examples below, the index on TB.COL3 is used and only up
    to 1000 rows are processed and returned.</para>

    <informalexample>
      <programlisting>    (TB is a very large table with an index on TB.COL3

    SELECT * FROM TB JOIN TA ON TA.COL1 = TB.COL2 WHERE TB.COL3 &gt; 40000 ORDER BY TB.COL3 LIMIT 1000;
    SELECT * FROM TB JOIN TA ON TA.COL1 = TB.COL2 WHERE TB.COL3 &gt; 40000 AND TB.COL3 &lt; 100000 ORDER BY TB.COL3 DESC LIMIT 1000;
</programlisting>
    </informalexample>
  </section>
</chapter>
