<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="triggers-chapt"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title xml:id="triggers-title">Triggers</title>

  <info>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <personname><firstname>Fred</firstname><surname>Toussi</surname></personname>

        <affiliation>
          <orgname>The HSQL Development Group</orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <releaseinfo>$Revision: 3042 $</releaseinfo>

    <pubdate>$Date: 2009-07-14 17:55:19 +0100 (Tue, 14 Jul 2009) $</pubdate>

    <keywordset>
      <keyword>Hsqldb</keyword>

      <keyword>HyperSQL</keyword>

      <keyword>SQL</keyword>
    </keywordset>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Copyright 2010-11 Fred Toussi. Permission is granted to distribute
      this document without any alteration under the terms of the HSQLDB
      license. Additional permission is granted to the HSQL Development Group
      to distribute this document with or without alterations under the terms
      of the HSQLDB license.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </info>

  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <simpara>Trigger functionality first appeared in SQL:1999. Triggers embody
    the <emphasis>live database</emphasis> concept, where changes in SQL data
    can be monitored and acted upon. This means each time a DELETE, UPDATE or
    INSERT is performed, additional actions are taken by the declared
    triggers. SQL Standard triggers are <glossterm>imperative</glossterm>
    while the <glossterm>relational</glossterm> aspects of SQL are
    <glossterm>declarative</glossterm>. Triggers allow performing an arbitrary
    transformation of data that is being updated or inserted, or to prevent
    insert, updated or deletes, or to perform additional operations.</simpara>

    <simpara>Some bad examples of SQL triggers in effect enforce an “integrity
    constraint” which would better be expressed as a CHECK constraint. A
    trigger that causes an exception if the value inserted in a column is
    negative is such an example. A check constraint that declares
    <literal>CHECK VALUE &gt;= 0</literal> (declarative) is a better way of
    expressing an integrity constraint than a trigger that throws an exception
    if the same condition is false.</simpara>

    <simpara>Usage constraints cannot always be expressed by SQL’s integrity
    constraint statements. Triggers can enforce these constraints. For
    example, it is not possible to use a check constraint to prevent inserts
    or deletes on weekends. A trigger can be used to enforce the time when
    each operation is allowed.</simpara>

    <simpara>A trigger is declared to activate when an UPDATE, INSERT or
    DELETE action is performed on a table. These actions may be direct or
    indirect. Indirect actions may arise from CASCADE actions of FOREIGN KEY
    constraints, or from data change statements performed on a VIEW that is
    based on the table that in.</simpara>

    <simpara>It is possible to declare multiple triggers on a single table.
    The triggers activate one by one according to the order in which they were
    defined. HyperSQL supports an extension to the CREATE TRIGGER statement,
    which allows the user to specify the execution order of the new
    trigger.</simpara>

    <simpara>A row level trigger allows access to the deleted or inserted
    rows. For UPDATE actions there is both an old and new version of each row.
    A trigger can be specified to activate before or after the action has been
    performed.</simpara>

    <section>
      <title>BEFORE Triggers</title>

      <simpara>A trigger that is declared as BEFORE DELETE cannot modify the
      deleted row. In other words, it cannot decide to delete a different row
      by changing the column values of the row. A trigger that is declared as
      BEFORE INSERT and BEFORE UPDATE can modify the values that are inserted
      into the database. For example, a badly formatted string can be cleaned
      up by a trigger before INSERT or UPDATE.</simpara>

      <simpara>BEFORE triggers cannot modify the other tables of the database.
      All BEFORE triggers can veto the action by throwing an
      exception.</simpara>

      <simpara>Because BEFORE triggers can modify the inserted or updated
      rows, all constrainst checks are performed after the execution of the
      BEFORE triggers. The checks include NOT NULL constraints, length of
      strings, CHECK constraints, and FOREIGN key constraints.</simpara>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>AFTER Triggers</title>

      <simpara>AFTER triggers can also perform additional data changes, for
      example inserting an additional row into a different table for data
      audits. These triggers cannot modify the rows that have been modified by
      the INSERT or UPDATE action.</simpara>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>INSTEAD OF Triggers</title>

      <simpara>A trigger that is declared on a VIEW, is an INSTEAD OF trigger.
      This term means when an INSERT, UPDATE or DELETE statement is executed
      with the view as the target, the trigger action is all that is
      performed, and no further data change takes place on the view. The
      trigger action can include all the statements that are necessary to
      change the data in the tables that underlie the view, or even other
      tables, such as audit tables. With the use of INSTEAD OF triggers a
      read-only view can effectively become updatable or
      insertable-into.</simpara>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Trigger Properties</title>

    <para>A trigger is declared on a specific table or view. Various trigger
    properties determine when the trigger is executed and how.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Trigger Event</title>

      <para>The trigger event specifies the type of SQL statement that causes
      the trigger to execute. Each trigger is specified to execute when an
      INSERT, DELETE or UPDATE takes place.</para>

      <para>The event can be filtered by two separate means. For all triggers,
      the WHEN clause can specify a condition against the rows that are the
      subject of the trigger, together with the data in the database. For
      example, a trigger can activate when the size of a table becomes larger
      than a certain amount. Or it can activate when the values in the rows
      being modified satisfy certain conditions.</para>

      <para>An UPDATE trigger can be declared to execute only when certain
      columns are the subject of an update statement. For example, a trigger
      declared as AFTER UPDATE OF (datecolumn) will activate only when the
      UPDATE statement that is executed includes the column, datecolumn, as
      one of the columns specified in its SET statements.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Granularity</title>

      <para>A statement level trigger is performed once for the executed SQL
      statement and is declared as FOR EACH STATEMENT.</para>

      <para>A row level trigger is performed once for each row that is
      modified during the execution of an SQL statement and is declared as FOR
      EACH ROW. Note that an SQL statement can INSERT, UPDATE or DELETE zero
      or more rows.</para>

      <para>If a statement does not apply to any row, then the trigger is not
      executed.</para>

      <para>If FOR EACH ROW or FOR EACH STATEMENT is not specified, then the
      default is FOR EACH STATEMENT.</para>

      <para>The granularity dictates whether the REFERENCING clause can
      specify OLD ROW, NEW ROW, or OLD TABLE, NEW TABLE.</para>

      <para>A trigger declared as FOR EACH STATEMENT can only be an AFTER
      trigger.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Trigger Action Time</title>

      <para>A trigger is executed BEFORE, AFTER or INSTEAD OF the trigger
      event.</para>

      <para>INSTEAD OF triggers are allowed only when the trigger is declared
      on a VIEW. With this type of trigger, the event (SQL statement) itself
      is not executed, only the trigger.</para>

      <para>BEFORE or AFTER triggers are executed just before or just after
      the execution of the event. For example, just before a row is inserted
      into a table, the BEFORE trigger is activated, and just after the row is
      inserted, the AFTER trigger is executed.</para>

      <para>BEFORE triggers can modify the row that is being inserted or
      updated. AFTER triggers cannot modify rows. They are usually used to
      perform additional operations, such as inserting rows into other
      tables.</para>

      <para>A trigger declared as FOR EACH STATEMENT can only be an AFTER
      trigger.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>References to Rows</title>

      <para>If the old rows or new rows are referenced in the SQL statements
      in the trigger action, they must have names. The REFERENCING clause is
      used to give names to the old and new rows. The clause, REFERENCING OLD
      | NEW TABLE is used for statement level triggers. The clause,
      REFERENCING OLD | NEW ROW is used for row level triggers. If the old
      rows or new rows are referenced in the SQL statements in the trigger
      action, they must have names. In the SQL statements, the columns of the
      old or new rows are qualified with the specified names.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Trigger Condition</title>

      <para>The WHEN clause can specify a condition for the columns of the row
      that is being changed. Using this clause you can simply avoid
      unnecessary trigger activation for rows that do not need it.</para>

      <para>For UPDATE trigger, you can specify a list of columns of the
      table. If a list of columns is specified, then if the UPDATE statement
      does not change the columns with SET clauses, then the trigger is not
      activated at all.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Trigger Action in SQL</title>

      <para>The trigger action specifies what the trigger does when it is
      activated. This is usually written as one or more SQL statements.</para>

      <para>When a row level trigger is activated, there is an OLD ROW, or a
      NEW ROW, or both. An INSERT statement supplies a NEW ROW row to be
      inserted into a table. A DELETE statement supplies an OLD ROW be
      deleted. An UPDATE statement supplies both OLD ROW and NEW ROW that
      represent the updated rows before and after the update. The REFERENCING
      clause gives names to these rows, so that the rows can be referenced in
      the trigger action.</para>

      <para>In the example below, a name is given to the NEW ROW and it is
      used both in the WHEN clause and in the trigger action SQL to insert a
      row into a triglog table after each row insert into the testtrig
      table.</para>

      <programlisting>  CREATE TRIGGER trig AFTER INSERT ON testtrig 
    REFERENCING NEW ROW AS newrow
    FOR EACH ROW WHEN (newrow.id &gt; 1)
    INSERT INTO TRIGLOG VALUES (newrow.id, newrow.data, 'inserted')
</programlisting>

      <para>In the example blow, the trigger code modifies the updated data if
      a condition is true. This type of trigger is useful when the application
      does not perform the necessary checks and modifications to data. The
      statement block that starts with BEGIN ATOMIC is similar to an SQL/PSM
      block and can contain all the SQL statements that are allowed in an
      SQL/PSM block.</para>

      <programlisting>  CREATE TRIGGER t BEFORE UPDATE ON customer
    REFERENCING NEW AS newrow FOR EACH ROW
    BEGIN ATOMIC
      IF LENGTH(newrow.firstname) &gt; 10 THEN
        SET newrow.firstname = LOWER(newrow.firstname);
      END IF;
    END
</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Trigger Action in Java</title>

      <para>A trigger action can be written as a Java class that implements
      the <classname>org.hsqldb.Trigger</classname> interface. This interface
      has a single method which is called when the trigger is activated,
      either before or after the event. When the method is called by the
      engine, it supplies the type of trigger as an int value defined by the
      interface(as type argument), the name of the trigger (as trigName
      argument), the name of the table (as tabName argument), the OLD ROW (as
      oldRow argument) and the NEW ROW (as newRow argument). The oldRow
      argument is null for row level INSERT triggers. The newRow argument is
      null for row level DELETE triggers. For table level triggers, both
      arguments are null (that is, there is no access to the data). The
      triggerType argument is one of the constants in the org.hsqldb.Trigger
      interface which indicate the type of trigger, for example,
      INSERT_BEFORE_ROW or UPDATE_AFTER_ROW.</para>

      <para>The Java class for the trigger can be reused for several triggers
      on different tables. The method code can distinguish between the
      different tables and triggers using the supplied arguments and take
      appropriate action.</para>

      <programlisting>    fire (int triggerType, String name, String table, Object row1[], Object row2[])
</programlisting>

      <para>The Java method for a synchronous trigger (see below) can modify
      the values in newRow2 in a BEFORE trigger. Such modifications are
      reflected in the row that is being inserted or updated. Any other
      modifications are ignored by the engine.</para>

      <para>A Java trigger that uses an instance of
      <classname>org.hsqldb.Trigger</classname> has two forms, synchronous, or
      asynchronous (immediate or queued). By default, or when QUEUE 0 is
      specified, the action is performed immediately by calling the Java
      method. This is similar to SQL trigger actions.</para>

      <para>When QUEUE n is specified with n larger than 0, the engine uses a
      separate thread to execute the Java method, using a queue with the size
      n. For certain applications, such as real-time systems this allows
      asynchronous notifications to be sent by the trigger event, without
      introducing delays in the engine. With asynchronous triggers, an extra
      parameter, NOWAIT can be used in trigger definition. This overcomes the
      queue full condition. In this mode, old calls that are still in the
      queue are discarded one by one and replaced with new calls.</para>

      <para>Java row level triggers that are declared with BEFORE trigger
      action time can modify the row data. Triggers with AFTER trigger action
      time can modify the database, e.g. insert new rows. If the trigger needs
      to access the database, the same method as in Java Language Routines
      SQL/JRT can be used with <literal>"jdbc:default:connection"</literal> to
      get the connection to the database.</para>

      <para>For sample trigger classes and test code see,
      <classname>org.hsqldb.sample.TriggerSample</classname>,
      <classname>org.hsqldb.test.TestTriggers</classname>,
      <classname>org.hsqldb.test.TriggerClass</classname> and the associated
      text script <filename>TestTriggers.txt</filename> in the
      <literal>/testrun/hsqldb/</literal> directory. In the example below, the
      trigger is activated only if the update statement includes SET clauses
      that modify any of the specified columns (c1, c2, c3). Furthermore, the
      trigger is not activated if the c2 column in the updated row is
      null.</para>

      <programlisting>  CREATE TRIGGER TRIGBUR BEFORE UPDATE OF c1, c2, c3 ON testtrig 
    referencing NEW ROW AS newrow
    FOR EACH ROW WHEN (newrow.c2 IS NOT NULL)
    CALL "org.hsqldb.test.TriggerClass"
</programlisting>

      <para>Java functions can be called from an SQL trigger. So it is
      possible to define the Java function to perform any external
      communication that are necessary for the trigger, and use SQL code for
      checks and alterations to data.</para>

      <programlisting>  CREATE TRIGGER t BEFORE UPDATE ON customer
    REFERENCING NEW AS newrow FOR EACH ROW
    BEGIN ATOMIC
      IF LENGTH(newrow.firstname) &gt; 10 THEN
        CALL my_java_function(newrow.firstname, newrow.lastname);
      END IF;
    END
</programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Trigger Creation</title>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>CREATE TRIGGER</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">CREATE TRIGGER</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>trigger definition</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;trigger definition&gt; ::= CREATE TRIGGER
    &lt;trigger name&gt; &lt;trigger action time&gt; &lt;trigger event&gt; ON
    &lt;table name&gt; [BEFORE &lt;other trigger name&gt;] [ REFERENCING
    &lt;transition table or variable list&gt; ] &lt;triggered
    action&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;trigger action time&gt; ::= BEFORE | AFTER | INSTEAD
    OF</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;trigger event&gt; ::= INSERT | DELETE | UPDATE [ OF
    &lt;trigger column list&gt; ]</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;trigger column list&gt; ::= &lt;column name
    list&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;triggered action&gt; ::= [ FOR EACH { ROW |
    STATEMENT } ] [ &lt;triggered when clause&gt; ] &lt;triggered SQL
    statement&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;triggered when clause&gt; ::= WHEN &lt;left
    paren&gt; &lt;search condition&gt; &lt;right paren&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;triggered SQL statement&gt; ::= &lt;SQL procedure
    statement&gt; | BEGIN ATOMIC { &lt;SQL procedure statement&gt;
    &lt;semicolon&gt; }... END | [QUEUE &lt;integer literal&gt;] [NOWAIT] CALL
    &lt;HSQLDB trigger class FQN&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;transition table or variable list&gt; ::=
    &lt;transition table or variable&gt;...</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;transition table or variable&gt; ::= OLD [ ROW ] [
    AS ] &lt;old transition variable name&gt; | NEW [ ROW ] [ AS ] &lt;new
    transition variable name&gt; | OLD TABLE [ AS ] &lt;old transition table
    name&gt; | NEW TABLE [ AS ] &lt;new transition table
    name&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;old transition table name&gt; ::= &lt;transition
    table name&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;new transition table name&gt; ::= &lt;transition
    table name&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;transition table name&gt; ::=
    &lt;identifier&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;old transition variable name&gt; ::= &lt;correlation
    name&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;new transition variable name&gt; ::= &lt;correlation
    name&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>Trigger definition is a relatively complex statement. The
    combination of <literal>&lt;trigger action time&gt;</literal> and
    <literal>&lt;trigger event&gt;</literal> determines the type of the
    trigger. Examples include BEFORE DELETE, AFTER UPDATE, INSTEAD OF INSERT.
    If the optional <literal>[ OF &lt;trigger column list&gt; ]</literal> is
    specified for an UPDATE trigger, then the trigger is activated only if one
    of the columns that is in the <literal>&lt;trigger column
    list&gt;</literal> is specified in the UPDATE statement that activates the
    trigger.</simpara>

    <simpara>If a trigger is <literal>FOR EACH ROW</literal>, which is the
    default option, then the trigger is activated for each row of the table
    that is affected by the execution of an SQL statement. Otherwise, it is
    activated once only per statement execution. For <literal>FOR EACH
    ROW</literal> triggers, there is an OLD and NEW state for each row. For
    UPDATE triggers, both OLD and NEW states exist, representing the row
    before the update, and after the update. For DELETE, triggers, there is
    only an OLD state. For INSERT triggers, there is only the NEW state. If a
    trigger is <literal>FOR EACH STATEMENT</literal>, then a transient table
    is created containing all the rows for the OLD state and another transient
    table is created for the NEW state.</simpara>

    <simpara>The <literal>[ REFERENCING &lt;transition table or variable&gt;
    ]</literal> is used to give a name to the OLD and NEW data row or table.
    This name can be referenced in the <literal>&lt;SQL procedure
    statement&gt;</literal> to access the data.</simpara>

    <simpara>The optional <literal>&lt;triggered when clause&gt;</literal> is
    a search condition, similar to the search condition of a DELETE or UPDATE
    statement. If the search condition is not TRUE for a row, then the trigger
    is not activated for that row.</simpara>

    <simpara>The <literal>&lt;SQL procedure statement&gt;</literal> is limited
    to INSERT, DELETE, UPDATE and MERGE statements.</simpara>

    <simpara>The <literal>&lt;HSQLDB trigger class FQN&gt;</literal> is a
    delimited identifer that contains the fully qualified name of a Java class
    that implements the <classname>org.hsqldb.Trigger</classname>
    interface.</simpara>

    <simpara>Early releases of HyperSQL version 2.0 do not allow the use of
    OLD TABLE or NEW TABLE in statement level triggers.</simpara>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>TRIGGERED SQL STATEMENT</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">TRIGGERED SQL
    STATEMENT</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>triggered SQL statement</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>The &lt;triggered SQL statement&gt;</literal> has three
    forms.</simpara>

    <simpara>The first form is a single SQL procedure statement. This
    statement can reference the OLD ROW and NEW ROW variables. For example, it
    can reference these variables and insert a row into a separate
    table.</simpara>

    <simpara>The second form is enclosed in a BEGIN ... END block and can
    include one or more SQL procedure statements. In BEFORE triggers, you can
    include SET statements to modify the inserted or updated rows. In AFTER
    triggers, you can include INSERT, DELETE and UPDATE statements to change
    the data in other database tables. SELECT and CALL statements are allowed
    in BEFORE and AFTER triggers. CALL statements in BEFORE triggers should
    not modify data.</simpara>

    <simpara>The third form specifies a call to a Java method.</simpara>

    <simpara>Two examples of a trigger with a block are given below. The block
    can include elements discussed in the <link endterm="sqlroutines-title"
    ns2:href="#sqlroutines-chapt" ns2:title=""></link> chapter, including
    local variables, loops and conditionals. You can also raise an exception
    in such blocks in order to terminate the execution of the SQL statement
    that caused the trigger to execute.</simpara>

    <programlisting>/* the trigger throws an exception if a customer with the given last name already exists */
  CREATE TRIGGER trigone BEFORE INSERT ON customer 
    REFERENCING NEW ROW AS newrow
    FOR EACH ROW WHEN (newrow.id &gt; 100)
    BEGIN ATOMIC
      IF EXISTS (SELECT * FROM CUSTOMER WHERE CUSTOMER.LASTNAME = NEW.LASTNAME) THEN
        SIGNAL SQLSTATE '45000';
      END IF;
    END
</programlisting>

    <programlisting>/* for each row inserted into the target, the trigger insert a row into the table used for logging */
  CREATE TRIGGER trig AFTER INSERT ON testtrig 
    BEFORE othertrigger  
    REFERENCING NEW ROW AS newrow
    FOR EACH ROW WHEN (newrow.id &gt; 1)
    BEGIN ATOMIC
      INSERT INTO triglog VALUES (newrow.id, newrow.data, 'inserted');
      /* more statements can be included */
    END
</programlisting>

    <simpara></simpara>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>TRIGGER EXECUTION ORDER</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">TRIGGER EXECUTION
    ORDER</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>trigger execution order</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;trigger execution order&gt; ::= BEFORE &lt;other
    trigger name&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>HyperSQL extends the SQL Standard to allow the order of execution
    of a trigger to be specified by using [BEFORE &lt;other trigger name&gt;]
    in the definition. The newly defined trigger will be executed before the
    specified other trigger. If this clause is not used, the new trigger is
    executed after all the previously defined triggers of the same scope
    (BEFORE, AFTER, EACH ROW, EACH STATEMENT).</simpara>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>DROP TRIGGER</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">DROP TRIGGER</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>drop trigger statement</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;drop trigger statement&gt; ::= DROP TRIGGER
    &lt;trigger name&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>Destroy a trigger.</simpara>
  </section>
</chapter>
