<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->
<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % dummy22 SYSTEM "../entities/global.ent">
%dummy22;
<!ENTITY % dummy25 SYSTEM "entities/versions.ent">
%dummy25;
]>
<book version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
      xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <!-- We declare the default namespace + those for prefixes xlink: and xi: in
       the root element, so we can use them anywhere in this file. -->

  <info>
    <title>HyperSQL Utilities Guide</title>

    <authorgroup>
      <editor>
        <orgname>The HSQLB Development Group</orgname>
      </editor>

      <editor>
        <personname><firstname>Blaine</firstname><surname>Simpson</surname></personname>

        <affiliation>
          <orgname>The HSQL Development Group</orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </editor>

      <editor>
        <personname><firstname>Fred</firstname><surname>Toussi</surname></personname>

        <affiliation>
          <orgname>The HSQL Development Group</orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </editor>
    </authorgroup>

    <releaseinfo>$Revision$</releaseinfo>

    <pubdate>&timestamp;</pubdate>

    <keywordset>
      <keyword>HyperSQL</keyword>

      <keyword>Hsqldb</keyword>

      <keyword>Hypersonic</keyword>

      <keyword>Database</keyword>

      <keyword>JDBC</keyword>

      <keyword>Java</keyword>
    </keywordset>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Copyright 2002-2009 The HSQL Development Group. Permission is
      granted to distribute this document without any alteration under the
      terms of the HSQLDB license.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </info>

  <preface xml:id="book-pref">
    <title>Preface</title>

    <para>If you notice any mistakes in this document, please email the author
    listed at the beginning of the chapter. If you have problems with the
    procedures themselves, please use the HSQLDB support facilities which are
    listed at <link
    xlink:href="http://hsqldb.org/web/hsqlSupport.html"></link>.</para>

    <xi:include href="../altformats-sect.xml" />
  </preface>

  <xi:include href="sqltool-chapt.xml" />

  <chapter xml:id="test-utility-chapt">
    <title>Hsqldb Test Utility</title>

    <info>
      <keywordset>
        <keyword>Hsqldb</keyword>

        <keyword>Test</keyword>

        <keyword>Utility</keyword>
      </keywordset>
    </info>

    <para>The <classname>org.hsqldb.test</classname> package contains a number
    of tests for various functions of the database engine. Among these, the
    <classname>TestUtil</classname> class performs the tests that are based on
    scripts. To run the tests, you should compile the
    <filename>hsqldbtest.jar</filename> target with Ant and JUnit.</para>

    <para>The <classname>TestUtil</classname> class should be run in the
    /testrun/hsqldb directory of the distributed files. It then runs the set
    of TestSelf*.txt files in the directory. To start the application in
    Windows, change to the directory and type:</para>

    <screen> java org.hsqldb.test.TestUtil</screen>

    <para>All files in the working directory with names matching TestSelf*.txt
    are processed in alphabetical order.</para>

    <para>You can add your own scripts to test different series of SQL
    queries. The format of the TestSelf*.txt file is simple text, with some
    indentation and prefixes in the form of Java-style comments. The prefixes
    indicate what the expected result should be.</para>

    <para>The class <classname>org.hsqldb.test.TestScriptRunner</classname> is
    a more general program which you can use to test any script files which
    you specify (with scripts of the same exact format as described below).
    For example, <screen>java org.hsqldb.test.TestScriptRunner --urlid=mem script1.tsql script2.sql</screen>
    You must have the HSQLDB classes, including the util and test classes, in
    your <varname>CLASSPATH</varname>. The urlid must be set up in an RC file
    as explained in the <link endterm="auth-title"
    xlink:href="#sqltool_auth-sect"></link> section. Use the
    <literal>rcfile=</literal> argument to specify an RC file other than the
    default of <filename>testscriptrunner.rc</filename> in the current
    directory. To see all invocation possibilities, just run TestScriptRunner
    with no arguments at all. TestScriptRunner can run tests sequentially (the
    default) or in simultaneous asynchronous threads.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Comment lines must start with -- and are ignored</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Lines starting with spaces are the continuation of the previous
        line (for long SQL statements)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>SQL statements with no prefix are simply executed.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>The remaining items in this list exemplify use of the
        available command line-prefixes.</emphasis></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <informalexample>
          <simpara>The /*s*/ option stands for silent. It is used for
          executing quries regardless of results. Used for preparation of
          tests, not for actual tests.</simpara>

          <programlisting>/*s*/ Any SQL statement - errors are ignored</programlisting>
        </informalexample>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <informalexample>
          <simpara>The /*c&lt;rows&gt;*/ option is for SELECT queries and
          asserts the number of rows in the result matches the given
          count.</simpara>

          <programlisting>/*c&lt;rows&gt;*/ SQL statement returning count of &lt;rows&gt;</programlisting>
        </informalexample>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <informalexample>
          <simpara>The /*u*/ option is for queries that return an update
          count, such as DELETE and UPDATE. It asserts the update count
          matches.</simpara>

          <programlisting>/*u&lt;count&gt;*/ SQL statement returning an update count equal to &lt;count&gt;</programlisting>
        </informalexample>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <informalexample>
          <simpara>The /*e*/ option asserts that the given query results in an
          erros. It is mainly used for testing the error detection
          capabilities of the engine. The SQL State of the expected error can
          be defined, for example /*e42578*/, to verify the returned error.
          This option can be used with syntactically valid queries to assert a
          certain state in the database. For example a CREATE TABLE can be
          used to assert the table of the same name already exists.</simpara>

          <programlisting>/*e*/ SQL statement that should produce an error when executing</programlisting>
        </informalexample>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <informalexample>
          <simpara>The /*r....*/ option asserts the SELECT query returns a
          single row containing the given set of field values.</simpara>

          <programlisting>/*r&lt;string1&gt;,&lt;string2&gt;*/ SQL statement returning a single row ResultSet equal to the specified value</programlisting>
        </informalexample>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <informalexample>
          <simpara>The extended /*r...*/ option asserts the SELECT query
          returns the given rows containing the given set of field
          values.</simpara>

          <programlisting>/*r
    &lt;string1&gt;,&lt;string2&gt;
    &lt;string1&gt;,&lt;string2&gt;
    &lt;string1&gt;,&lt;string2&gt;
*/ SQL statement returning a multiple row ResultSet equal to the specified values</programlisting>
        </informalexample>

        <simpara>(note that the result set lines are indented).</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>The /*d*/ directive just displays the supplied
        text.</simpara>

        <informalexample>
          <programlisting>/*d*/ Some message</programlisting>
        </informalexample>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>The /*w MILLIS*/ directive causes the test to Wait for a
        specified number of millisedonds.</simpara>

        <informalexample>
          <programlisting>/*w 1000*/ Optional message</programlisting>
        </informalexample>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>The /*w ENFORCE_SEQUENCE WAITER_NAME*/ directive causes the
        test to Wait for the specified <emphasis>Waiter</emphasis>. A waiter
        is just name that is used to associate a /*w*/ directive to its
        corresponding /*p*/ directive. The ENFORCE_SEQUENCE argument must be
        set to <literal>true</literal> or <literal>false</literal> to specify
        whether to fail unless the /*p*/ command runs after the /*w*/ command
        is waiting.</simpara>

        <informalexample>
          <programlisting>/*w true script4*/ Optional message</programlisting>
        </informalexample>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>The /*p ENFORCE_SEQUENC WAITER_NAME*/ directive is the peer
        directive to /*w*/, which causes a waiting thread to
        Proceed.</simpara>

        <informalexample>
          <programlisting>/*p true script4*/ Optional message</programlisting>
        </informalexample>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>All the options are lowercase letters. During development, an
        uppercase can be used for a given test to exclude a test from the test
        run. The utility will just report the test blocks that have been
        excluded without running them. Once the code has been developed, the
        option can be turned into lowercase to perform the actual test.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <simpara>See the TestSelf*.txt files in the /testrun/hsqldb/ directory for
    actual examples.</simpara>

    <para>The String <literal>${timestamp}</literal> may be used in script
    messages (like in /*d*/, /*w*/, /*p*/). It expands to the current time,
    down to the second. For example, <informalexample>
        <programlisting>/*d*/ It is now ${timestamp}</programlisting>
      </informalexample></para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter xml:id="dbm-chapt">
    <title>Database Manager</title>

    <info>
      <authorgroup>
        <author>
          <personname><firstname>Fred</firstname>
          <surname>Toussi</surname></personname>

          <affiliation>
            <orgname>The HSQL Development Group</orgname>
          </affiliation>
        </author>

        <author>
          <personname><firstname>Blaine</firstname>
          <surname>Simpson</surname></personname>

          <affiliation>
            <orgname>The HSQL Development Group</orgname>
          </affiliation>
        </author>
      </authorgroup>

    <releaseinfo>$Revision$</releaseinfo>

    <pubdate>&timestamp;</pubdate>

      <keywordset>
        <keyword>Hsqldb</keyword>

        <keyword>Database</keyword>

        <keyword>Manager</keyword>
      </keywordset>
    </info>

    <section xml:id="dbm_intro-sect">
      <title>Brief Introduction</title>

      <para>The Database Manager tool is a simple GUI database query tool with
      a tree display of the tables. Both AWT and SWING versions of the tool
      are available and work almost identically. The AWT version class name is
      org.hsqldb.util.DatabaseManager; the SWING version,
      org.hsqldb.util.DatabaseManagerSwing. The SWING version has more
      refinements than the AWT version.</para>

      <para>The AWT version of the database manager can be deployed as an
      applet in a browser. A demo HTML file with an embedded Database Manager
      is included in the /demo directory.</para>

      <para>When the Database Manager is started, a dialogue allows you to
      enter the JDBC driver, URL, user and password for the new connection. A
      drop-down box, Type, offers preset values for JDBC driver and URL for
      most popular database engines, including HSQLDB. Once you have selected
      an item from this drop-down box, you should edit the URL to specify the
      details of the database or any additional properties to pass. You should
      also enter the username and password before clicking on the OK
      button.</para>

      <para>The connection dialogue allows you to save the settings for the
      connection you are about to make. You can then access the connection in
      future sessions. To save a connection setting, enter a name in the
      Setting Name box before clicking on the OK button. Next time the
      connection dialogue is displayed, the drop-down box labeled Recent will
      include the name for all the saved connection settings. When you select
      a name, the individual settings are displayed in the appropriate
      boxes.</para>

      <para>The small Clr button next to the drop-down box allows you to clear
      all the saved settings. If you want to modify an existing setting, first
      select it from the drop-down box then modify any of the text boxes
      before making the connection. The modified values will be saved.</para>

      <simpara>Most SWING menu items have context-sensitive tool tip help text
      which will appear if you hold the mouse cursor still over the desired
      menu item. (Assuming that you don't turn Tooltips off under the
      <guimenu>Help</guimenu> menu.</simpara>

      <simpara>The database object tree in the SWING version allows you to
      right click on the name of a table or column and choose from common SQL
      statements for the object, for example SELECT * FROM thistable ... If
      you click on one of the given choices, the sample statement is copied to
      the command window, where you can modify and complete it.</simpara>

      <simpara>The DatabaseManagers do work with HSQLDB servers serving
      TLS-encrypted JDBC data. See the TLS section of the Listeners chapter of
      the <link xlink:href="distro_baseurl_DEFAULTVAL/guide/index.html">
      HyperSQL User Guide</link></simpara>

      <tip>
        <simpara>If you are using DatabaseManagerSwing with Oracle, you will
        want to make sure that <guimenuitem>Show row counts</guimenuitem> and
        <guimenuitem>Show row counts</guimenuitem> are both off
        <emphasis>before connecting to the database</emphasis>. You may also
        want to turn off Auto tree-update, as described in the next
        section.</simpara>
      </tip>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="dbm_tree-sect">
      <title>Auto tree-update</title>

      <simpara>By default, the object tree in the left panel is refreshed when
      you execute DDL which may update those objects. If you are on a slow
      network or performance-challenged PC, use the <guimenu>view</guimenu> /
      <guimenuitem>Auto-refresh tree</guimenuitem> menu item to turn it off.
      You will then need to use the
      <guimenu>view</guimenu><guimenuitem>Refresh tree</guimenuitem> menu item
      every time that you want to refresh the tree.</simpara>

      <note>
        <simpara>Auto-refresh tree does not automatically show all updates to
        database objects, it only refreshes when you submit DDL which may
        update database objects. (This behavior is a compromise between
        utility and performance).</simpara>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="dbm-autoconn-sect">
      <title>Automatic Connection</title>

      <para>You can use command-line switches to supply connection
      information. If you use these switch(es), then the connection dialog
      window will be skipped and a JDBC connection will be established
      immediately. Assuming that the <filename>hsqldb.jar</filename> (or an
      alternative jar) are in your <varname>CLASSPATH</varname>, this command
      will list the available command-line options. <informalexample>
          <screen>    java org.hsqldb.util.DatabaseManagerSwing --help</screen>
        </informalexample></para>

      <simpara>It's convenient to skip the connection dialog window if you
      always work with the same database account.</simpara>

      <warning>
        <simpara>Use of the --password switch is not secure. Everything typed
        on command-lines is generally available to other users on the
        computer. The problem is compounded if you use a network connection to
        obtain your command line. The RC File section explains how you can set
        up automatic connections without supplying a password on the command
        line.</simpara>
      </warning>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="dbm_rcfile-sect">
      <title>RC File</title>

      <simpara>You can skip the connection dialog window securely by putting
      the connection information into an RC file and then using the
      <literal>--urlid</literal> switch to DatabaseManager or
      DatabaseManagerSwing. This strategy is great for adding launch menu
      items and/or launch icons to your desktop. You can set up one icon for
      each of the database accounts which you regularly use.</simpara>

      <simpara>The default location for the RC file is
      <filename>dbmanager.rc</filename> in your home directory. The <link
      endterm="auth-title" xlink:href="#sqltool_auth-sect"></link> section
      explains how to put the connection information into this text file. If
      you also run <link endterm="sqltool-title"
      xlink:href="#sqltool-chapt"></link>, then you can share the RC file with
      SqlTool by using a sym-link (if your operating system supports sym
      links), or by using the <literal>--rcfile</literal> switch for either
      SqlTool or DatabaseManagerSwing.</simpara>

      <warning>
        <simpara>Use your operating system facilities to prevent others from
        reading your RC file, since it contains passwords.</simpara>
      </warning>

      <para>To set up launch items/icons, first experiment on your command
      line to find exactly what command works. For example, <informalexample>
          <screen>java -cp /path/to/hsqldb.jar org.hsqldb.util.DatabaseManagerSwing --urlid mem</screen>
        </informalexample> Then, use your window manager to add an item that
      runs this command.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="dbm_wold-sect">
      <title>Using the current DatabaseManagers with an older HSQLDB
      distribution.</title>

      <simpara>This procedure will allow users of a legacy version of HSQLDB
      to use all of the new features of the DatabaseManagers. You will also
      get the new version of the SqlTool! This procedure works for distros
      going back to 1.7.3.3 at least, probably much farther.</simpara>

      <simpara>These instructions assume that you are capable of running an
      Ant build. See the Building Appendix of the <link
      xlink:href="distro_baseurl_DEFAULTVAL/guide/index.html"> HyperSQL User
      Guide</link>.</simpara>

      <procedure>
        <step>
          <simpara>Download and extract a current HSQLDB distribution. If you
          don't want to use the source code, documentation, etc., you can use
          a temporary directory and remove it afterwards.</simpara>
        </step>

        <step>
          <simpara>Cd to the build directory under the root directory where
          you extracted the distribution to.</simpara>
        </step>

        <step>
          <simpara>Run <literal>ant hsqldbutil</literal>.</simpara>
        </step>

        <step>
          <simpara>If you're going to wipe out the build directory, copy
          <filename>hsqldbutil.jar</filename> to a safe location
          first.</simpara>
        </step>

        <step>
          <simpara>For now on, whenver you are going to run DatabaseManager*,
          make sure that you have this <filename>hsqldbutil.jar</filename> as
          the first item in your <varname>CLASSPATH</varname>.</simpara>
        </step>
      </procedure>

      <para>Here's a UNIX example where somebody wants to use the new
      DatabaseManagerSwing with their older HSQLDB database, as well as with
      Postgresql and a local application. <informalexample>
          <screen>CLASSPATH=/path/to/hsqldbutil.jar:/home/bob/myapp/classes:/usr/local/lib/pg.jdbc3.jar
export CLASSPATH
java org.hsqldb.util.DatabaseManagerSwing --urlid urlid</screen>
        </informalexample></para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="dbm_applet-sect">
      <title>DatabaseManagerSwing as an Applet</title>

      <simpara>DatabaseManagerSwing is also an applet. You can use it in HTML,
      JSPs, etc. Be aware that in Applet mode, actions to load or save local
      files will be disabled, and attempts to access any server other than the
      HTML-serving-host will fail.</simpara>

      <para>Since the Applet can not store or load locally saved preferences,
      the only way to have persistent preference settings is by using Applet
      parameters. <variablelist>
          <title>DatabaseManagerSwing Applet Parameters</title>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>jdbcUrl</term>

            <listitem>
              <simpara>URL of a data source to auto-connect to. String
              value.</simpara>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>jdbcDriver</term>

            <listitem>
              <simpara>URL of a data source to auto-connect to. String value.
              Defaults to
              <classname>org.hsqldb.driver.JDBCDriver</classname>.</simpara>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>jdbcUser</term>

            <listitem>
              <simpara>User name for data source to auto-connect to. String
              value.</simpara>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>jdbcPassword</term>

            <listitem>
              <simpara>Password for data source to auto-connect to. String
              value. Defaults to zero-length string.</simpara>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>schemaFilter</term>

            <listitem>
              <simpara>Display only object from this schema in the object
              navigator. String value.</simpara>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>laf</term>

            <listitem>
              <simpara>Look-and-feel. String value.</simpara>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>loadSampleData</term>

            <listitem>
              <simpara>Auto-load sample data. Boolean value. Defaults to
              false.</simpara>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>autoRefresh</term>

            <listitem>
              <simpara>Auto-refresh the object navigator when DDL
              modifications detected in user SQL commands. Boolean value.
              Defaults to true.</simpara>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>showRowCounts</term>

            <listitem>
              <simpara>Show number of rows in each table in the object
              navigator. Boolean value. Defaults to false.</simpara>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>showSysTables</term>

            <listitem>
              <simpara>Show system tables in the object navigator. Boolean
              value. Defaults to false.</simpara>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>showSchemas</term>

            <listitem>
              <simpara>Show object names like schema.name in object navigator.
              Boolean value. Defaults to true.</simpara>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>resultGrid</term>

            <listitem>
              <simpara>Show query results in Gui grid (as opposed to in plain
              text). Boolean value. Defaults to true.</simpara>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>showToolTips</term>

            <listitem>
              <simpara>Show help hover-text. Boolean value. Defaults to
              true.</simpara>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist></para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter xml:id="transfer-tool-chapt">
    <title>Transfer Tool</title>

    <info>
      <authorgroup>
        <author>
          <personname><firstname>Fred</firstname>
          <surname>Toussi</surname></personname>

          <affiliation>
            <orgname>The HSQL Development Group</orgname>
          </affiliation>
        </author>
      </authorgroup>

    <releaseinfo>$Revision$</releaseinfo>

    <pubdate>&timestamp;</pubdate>

      <keywordset>
        <keyword>Hsqldb</keyword>

        <keyword>Transfer</keyword>
      </keywordset>
    </info>

    <section xml:id="trantool_intro-sect">
      <title>Brief Introduction</title>

      <para>Transfer Tool is a GUI program for transferring SQL schema and
      data from one JDBC source to another. Source and destination can be
      different database engines or different databases on the same
      server.</para>

      <para>Transfer Tool works in two different modes. Direct transfer
      maintains a connection to both source and destination and performs the
      transfer. Dump and Restore mode is invoked once to transfer the data
      from the source to a text file (Dump), then again to transfer the data
      from the text file to the destination (Restore). With Dump and Restore,
      it is possible to make any changes to database object definitions and
      data prior to restoring it to the target.</para>

      <para>Dump and Restore modes can be set via the command line with -d
      (--dump) or -r (--restore) options. Alternatively the Transfer Tool can
      be started with any of the three modes from the Database Manager's Tools
      menu.</para>

      <para>The connection dialogue allows you to save the settings for the
      connection you are about to make. You can then access the connection in
      future sessions. These settings are shared with those from the Database
      Manager tool. See the appendix on Database Manager for details of the
      connection dialogue box.</para>

      <para>From version 1.8.0 Transfer Tool is no longer part of the
      <filename>hsqldb.jar</filename>. You can build the
      <filename>hsqldbutil.jar</filename> using the Ant command of the same
      name, to build a jar that includes Transfer Tool and the Database
      Manager.</para>

      <para>When collecting meta-data, Transfer Tool performs SELECT * FROM
      &lt;table&gt; queries on all the tables in the source database. This may
      take a long time with some database engines. When the source database is
      HSQLDB, this means memory should be available for the result sets
      returned from the queries. Therefore, the memory allocation of the java
      process in which Transfer Tool is executed may have to be high.</para>

      <para>The current version of Transfer is far from ideal, as it has not
      been actively developed for several years. The program also lacks the
      ability to create UNIQUE constraints and creates UNIQUE indexes instead.
      However, some bugs have been fixed in the latest version and the program
      can be used with most of the supported databases. The best way to use
      the program is the DUMP and RESTORE modes, which allow you to manually
      change the SQL statements in the dump file before restoring to a
      database. A useful idea is to dump and restore the database definition
      separately from the database data.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <xi:include href="filelinks-app.xml" />

  <!--  Enable the index as soon as mark some index terms.
  <index xml:id="book-ind"/>
  -->
</book>
