<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="accesscontrol-chapt"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title xml:id="accesscontrol-title">Access Control</title>

  <info>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <personname><firstname>Fred</firstname><surname>Toussi</surname></personname>

        <affiliation>
          <orgname>The HSQL Development Group</orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <releaseinfo>$Revision: 3096 $</releaseinfo>

    <pubdate>$Date: 2009-08-09 17:50:39 +0100 (Sun, 09 Aug 2009) $</pubdate>

    <keywordset>
      <keyword>Hsqldb</keyword>

      <keyword>HyperSQL</keyword>

      <keyword>SQL</keyword>
    </keywordset>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Copyright 2010-11 Fred Toussi. Permission is granted to distribute
      this document without any alteration under the terms of the HSQLDB
      license. Additional permission is granted to the HSQL Development Group
      to distribute this document with or without alterations under the terms
      of the HSQLDB license.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </info>

  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>This chapter is about access control to database objects such as
    tables, inside the database engine. Other issues related to security
    include user authentication, password complexity and secure connections
    are covered in the <link endterm="deployment-title" xlink:arcrole=""
    xlink:href="#deployment-chapt"></link> chapter and the <link
    endterm="listeners-title" xlink:href="#listeners-chapt"></link>
    chapter.</para>

    <para>Apart from schemas and their object, each HyperSQL catalog has USER
    and ROLE objects. These objects are collectively called
    <emphasis>authorizations</emphasis>. Each AUTHORIZATION has some access
    rights on some of the schemas or the objects they contain. The persistent
    elements of an SQL environment are database objects</para>

    <para>Each database object has a name. A name is an identifier and is
    unique within its name-space. Authorizations names follow the rules
    described below and the case-normal form is stored in the database. When
    connecting to a database, the user name and password must match the case
    of the case-normal form.</para>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>identifier definition</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">identifier</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>definition of identifier</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;identifier&gt; ::= &lt;regular identifier&gt; |
    &lt;delimited identifier&gt; | &lt;SQL language identifier&gt;
    </literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;delimited identifier&gt; ::= &lt;double quote&gt;
    &lt;character sequence&gt; &lt;double quote&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;regular identifier&gt; ::= &lt;special character
    sequence&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;SQL language identifier&gt; ::= &lt;special
    character sequence&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>A <literal>&lt;delimited identifier&gt;</literal> is a sequence
    of characters enclosed with double-quote symbols. All characters are
    allowed in the character sequence.</simpara>

    <simpara>A <literal>&lt;regular identifier&gt;</literal> is a special
    sequence of characters. It consists of letters, digits and the underscore
    characters. It must begin with a letter.</simpara>

    <simpara>A <literal>&lt;SQL language identifier&gt;</literal> is similar
    to <literal>&lt;regular identifier&gt;</literal> but the letters can range
    only from A-Z in the ASCII character set. This type of identifier is used
    for names of CHARACTER SET objects.</simpara>

    <simpara>If the character sequence of a delimited identifier is the same
    as an undelimited identifier, it represents the same identifier. For
    example "JOHN" is the same identifier as JOHN. In a <literal>&lt;regular
    identifier&gt;</literal> the case-normal form is considered for
    comparison. This form consists of the upper-case of equivalent of all the
    letters.</simpara>

    <simpara>The character sequence length of all identifiers must be between
    1 and 128 characters.</simpara>

    <simpara>A reserved word is one that is used by the SQL Standard for
    special purposes. It is similar to a <literal>&lt;regular
    identifier&gt;</literal> but it cannot be used as an identifier for user
    objects. If a reserved word is enclosed in double quote characters, it
    becomes a quoted identifier and can be used for database
    objects.</simpara>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Authorizations and Access Control</title>

    <para>In general, ROLE and USER objects simply control access to schema
    objects. This is the scope of the SQL Standard. However, there are special
    roles that allow the creation of USER and ROLE objects and also allow some
    special operations on the database as a whole. These roles are not defined
    by the Standard, which has left it to implementors to define such roles as
    they are needed for the particular SQL implementation.</para>

    <para>A ROLE has a name a collection of zero or more other roles, plus
    some privileges (access rights). A USER has a name and a password. It
    similarly has a collection of zero or more roles plus some
    privileges.</para>

    <para>USER objects existed in the SQL-92, but ROLE objects were introduced
    in SQL:1999. Originally it was intended that USER objects would normally
    be the same as the operating system USER objects and their authentication
    would be handled outside the SQL environment. The co-existence of ROLE and
    USER objects results in complexity. With the addition of ROLE objects,
    there is no rationale, other than legacy support, for granting privileges
    to USER objects directly. It is better to create roles and grant
    privileges to them, then grant the roles to USER objects.</para>

    <para>The Standard effectively defines a special ROLE, named PUBLIC. All
    authorization have the PUBLIC role, which cannot be removed from them.
    Therefore any access right assigned to the PUBLIC role applies to all
    authorizations in the database. For many simple databases, it is adequate
    to create a single, non-admin user, then assign access rights to the
    pre-existing PUBLIC role. Access to INFORMATION_SCHEMA views is granted to
    PUBLIC, therefore these views are accessible to all. However, the contents
    of each view depends on the ROLE or USER (AUTHORIZATION) that is in force
    while accessing the view.</para>

    <para>Each schema has a single AUTHORIZATION. This is commonly known as
    the <emphasis>owner</emphasis> of the schema. All the objects in the
    schema inherit the schema owner. The schema owner can add objects to the
    schema, drop them or alter them.</para>

    <para>By default, the objects in a schema can only be accessed by the
    schema owner. The schema owner can grant access rights on the objects to
    other users or roles.</para>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>AUTHORIZATION IDENTIFIER</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">authorization
    identifier</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>authorization identifier</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;authorization identifier&gt; ::= &lt;role name&gt; |
    &lt;user name&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>Authorization identifiers share the same name-space within the
    database. The same name cannot be used for a USER and a ROLE.</simpara>

    <section>
      <title>Built-In Roles and Users</title>

      <para>There are some pre-defined roles in each database; some defined by
      the SQL Standard, some by HyperSQL. These roles can be assigned to users
      (directly or via other, user-defined roles). In addition, there is the
      default initial user, SA, created with each new database.</para>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>PUBLIC ROLE</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">PUBLIC</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>the PUBLIC role</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara>The role that is assigned to all authorizations (roles and
      users) in the database. This role has access rights to all objects in
      the INFORMATION_SCHEMA. Any roles or rights granted to this role, are in
      effect granted to all users of the database.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>_SYSTEM ROLE</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">_SYSTEM</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>the _SYSTEM role</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara>This role is the authorization for the pre-defined (system)
      objects in the database, including the INFORMATION_SCHEMA. This role
      cannot be assigned to any authorization.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>DBA ROLE</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">DBA</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>the DBA role (HyperSQL-specific)</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara>This is a special role in HyperSQL. A user that has this role
      can perform all possible administrative tasks on the database. The DBA
      role can also act as a proxy for all the roles and users in the
      database. This means it can do everything the authorization for a schema
      can do, including dropping the schema or its objects, or granting rights
      on the schema objects to a grantee.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>CREATE_SCHEMA ROLE</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">CREATE_SCHEMA</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>the CREATE_SCHEMA role
      (HyperSQL-specific)</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara>An authorization that has this role, can create schemas. The
      DBA authorization has this role and can grant it to other
      authorizations.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>CHANGE_AUTHORIZATION</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">CHANGE_AUTHORIZATION</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>the CHANGE_AUTHORIZATION role
      (HyperSQL-specific)</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara>A user that has this role, can change the authorization for the
      current session to another user. The other user cannot have the DBA role
      (otherwise, the original user would gain DBA provileges). The DBA
      authorization has this role and can grant it to other
      authorizations.</simpara>

      <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
        <primary>SA USER</primary>
      </indexterm>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SA</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis>the SA user (HyperSQL-specific)</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara>This user is automatically created with a new database and has
      the DBA role. Initially, the password for this user is an empty string.
      After connecting to the new database as this user, it is possible to
      change the password, create other users and created new schema objects.
      The SA user can be dropped by another user that has the DBA
      role.</simpara>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Access Rights</title>

      <para>By default, the objects in a schema can only be accessed by the
      schema owner. But the schema owner can grant privileges (access rights)
      on the objects to other users or roles.</para>

      <para>Things can get far more complex, because the grant of privileges
      can be made WITH GRANT OPTION. In this case, the role or user that has
      been granted the privilege can grant the privilege to other roles and
      users.</para>

      <para>Privileges can also be revoked from users or roles.</para>

      <para>The statements for granting and revoking privileges normally
      specify which privileges are granted or revoked. However, there is a
      shortcut, ALL PRIVILEGES, which means all the privileges that the
      <literal>&lt;grantor&gt;</literal> has on the schema object. The
      <literal>&lt;grantor&gt;</literal> is normally the CURRENT_USER of the
      session that issues the statement.</para>

      <para>The user or role that is granted privileges is referred to as
      <literal>&lt;grantee&gt;</literal> for the granted privileges.</para>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Table</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara>For tables, including views, privileges can be granted with
      different degrees of granularity. It is possible to grant a privilege on
      all columns of a table, or on specific columns of the table.</simpara>

      <simpara>The DELETE privilege applies to the table, rather than its
      columns. It applies to all DELETE statements.</simpara>

      <simpara>The SELECT, INSERT and UPDATE privileges may apply to all
      columns or to individual columns. These privileges determine whether the
      <literal>&lt;grantee&gt;</literal> can execute SQL data statements on
      the table.</simpara>

      <simpara>The SELECT privilege designates the columns that can be
      referenced in SELECT statements, as well as the columns that are read in
      a DELETE or UPDATE statement, including the search condition.</simpara>

      <simpara>The INSERT privilege designates the columns into which explicit
      values can be inserted. To be able to insert a row into the table, the
      user must therefore have the INSERT privilege on the table, or at least
      all the columns that do not have a default value.</simpara>

      <simpara>The UPDATE privilege simply designates the table or the
      specific columns that can be updated.</simpara>

      <simpara>The REFERENCES privilege allows the
      <literal>&lt;grantee&gt;</literal> to define a FOREIGN KEY constraint on
      a different table, which references the table or the specific columns
      designated for the REFERENCES privilege.</simpara>

      <simpara>The TRIGGER privilege allows adding a trigger to the
      table.</simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Sequence, Type, Domain, Character Set,
      Collation, Transliteration,</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara>For these objects, only USAGE can be granted. The USAGE
      privilege is needed when object is referenced directly in an SQL
      statement.</simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Routine</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara>For routines, including procedures or functions, only EXECUTE
      privilege can be granted. This privilege is needed when the routine is
      used directly in an SQL statement.</simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Other Objects</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara>Other objects such as constraints and assertions are not used
      directly and there is no grantable privilege that refers to
      them.</simpara>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title xml:id="accesscontrol-statements-title">Statements for
    Authorization and Access Control</title>

    <para>The statements listed below allow creation and destruction of USER
    and ROLE objects. The GRANT and REVOKE statements allow roles to be
    assigned to other roles or to users. The same statements are also used in
    a different form to assign privileges on schema objects to users and
    roles.</para>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>CREATE USER</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara xml:id="create_user-sql"><emphasis role="bold">CREATE
    USER</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>user definition (HyperSQL)</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;user definition&gt; ::= CREATE USER &lt;user
    name&gt; PASSWORD &lt;password&gt; [ ADMIN ]</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>Define a new user and its password. <literal>&lt;user
    name&gt;</literal> is an SQL identifier. If it is double-quoted it is
    case-sensitive, otherwise it is turned to uppercase.
    <literal>&lt;password&gt;</literal> is a string enclosed with single quote
    characters and is case-sensitive. If <literal>ADMIN</literal> is
    specified, the DBA role is granted to the new user. Only a user with the
    DBA role can execute this statement.</simpara>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>DROP USER</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">DROP USER</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>drop user statement (HyperSQL)</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;drop user statement&gt; ::= DROP USER &lt;user
    name&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>Drop (destroy) an existing user. If the specified user is the
    authorization for a schema, the schema is destroyed.</simpara>

    <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
    statement.</simpara>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>ALTER USER ... SET PASSWORD</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">ALTER USER ... SET
    PASSWORD</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>set the password for a user
    (HyperSQL)</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;alter user set password statement&gt; ::= ALTER USER
    &lt;user name&gt; SET PASSWORD &lt;password&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>Change the password of an existing user. <literal>&lt;user
    name&gt;</literal> is an SQL identifier. If it is double-quoted it is
    case-sensitive, otherwise it is turned to uppercase.
    <literal>&lt;password&gt;</literal> is a string enclosed with single quote
    characters and is case-sensitive.</simpara>

    <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this command.</simpara>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>ALTER USER ... SET INITIAL SCHEMA</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">ALTER USER ... SET INITIAL
    SCHEMA</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>set the initial schema for a user
    (HyperSQL)</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;alter user set initial schema statement&gt; ::=
    ALTER USER &lt;user name&gt; SET INITIAL SCHEMA &lt;schema name&gt; |
    DEFAULT</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>Change the initial schema for a user. The initial schema is the
    schema used by default for SQL statements issued during a session. If
    <literal>DEFAULT</literal> is used, the default initial schema for all
    users is used as the initial schema for the user. The SET SCHEMA command
    allows the user to change the schema for the duration of the
    session.</simpara>

    <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
    statement.</simpara>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>ALTER USER ... SET LOCAL</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">ALTER USER ... SET
    LOCAL</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>set the user authentication as local
    (HyperSQL)</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;alter user set local&gt; ::= ALTER USER &lt;user
    name&gt; SET LOCAL { TRUE | FALSE }</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>Sets the authentication method for the user as local. This
    statement has an effect only when external authentication with role names
    is enabled. In this method of authentication, users created in the
    database are ignored and an external authentication mechanism, such as
    LDAP is used. This statement is used if you want to use local, password
    authentication for a specific user. </simpara>

    <simpara>Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
    statement.</simpara>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>SET PASSWORD</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara xml:id="set_password-sql"><emphasis role="bold">SET
    PASSWORD</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>set password statement (HyperSQL)</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;set password statement&gt; ::= SET PASSWORD
    &lt;password&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>Set the password for the current user.
    <literal>&lt;password&gt;</literal> is a string enclosed with single quote
    characters and is case-sensitive.</simpara>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>SET INITIAL SCHEMA*</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET INITIAL SCHEMA</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>set the initial schema for the current user
    (HyperSQL)</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;set initial schema statement&gt; ::= SET INITIAL
    SCHEMA &lt;schema name&gt; | DEFAULT</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>Change the initial schema for the current user. The initial
    schema is the schema used by default for SQL statements issued during a
    session. If <literal>DEFAULT</literal> is used, the default initial schema
    for all users is used as the initial schema for the current user. The
    separate SET SCHEMA command allows the user to change the schema for the
    duration of the session. See also the <link endterm="sessions-title"
    xlink:arcrole="" xlink:href="#sessions-chapt"></link> chapter.</simpara>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>SET DATABASE DEFAULT INITIAL SCHEMA</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">SET DATABASE DEFAULT INITIAL
    SCHEMA</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>set the default initial schema for all users
    (HyperSQL)</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;set database default initial schema statement&gt;
    ::= SET DATABASE DEFAULT INITIAL SCHEMA &lt;schema
    name&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>Sets the initial schema for new users. This schema can later be
    changed with the <literal>&lt;set initial schema statement&gt;</literal>
    command.</simpara>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>CREATE ROLE</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">CREATE ROLE</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>role definition</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;role definition&gt; ::= CREATE ROLE &lt;role
    name&gt; [ WITH ADMIN &lt;grantor&gt; ]</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>Defines a new role. Initially the role has no rights, except
    those of the PUBLIC role. Only a user with the DBA role can execute this
    command.</simpara>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>DROP ROLE</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">DROP ROLE</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>drop role statement</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;drop role statement&gt; ::= DROP ROLE &lt;role
    name&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>Drop (destroy) a role. If the specified role is the authorization
    for a schema, the schema is destroyed. Only a user with the DBA role can
    execute this statement.</simpara>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>GRANTED BY</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">GRANTED BY</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>grantor determination</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>GRANTED BY &lt;grantor&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;grantor&gt; ::= CURRENT_USER |
    CURRENT_ROLE</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>The authorization that is granting or revoking a role or
    privileges. The optional <literal>GRANTED BY &lt;grantor&gt;</literal>
    clause can be used in various statements that perform GRANT or REVOKE
    actions. If the clause is not used, the authorization is CURRENT_USER.
    Otherwise, it is the specified authorization.</simpara>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>GRANT privilege</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">GRANT</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>grant privilege statement</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;grant privilege statement&gt; ::= GRANT
    &lt;privileges&gt; TO &lt;grantee&gt; [ { &lt;comma&gt; &lt;grantee&gt;
    }... ] [ WITH GRANT OPTION ] [ GRANTED BY &lt;grantor&gt;
    ]</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>Assign privileges on schema objects to roles or users. Each
    <literal>&lt;grantee&gt;</literal> is a role or a user. If <literal>[ WITH
    GRANT OPTION ]</literal> is specified, then the
    <literal>&lt;grantee&gt;</literal> can assign the privileges to other
    <literal>&lt;grantee&gt;</literal> objects.</simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;privileges&gt; ::= &lt;object privileges&gt; ON
    &lt;object name&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;object name&gt; ::= [ TABLE ] &lt;table name&gt; |
    DOMAIN &lt;domain name&gt; | COLLATION &lt;collation name&gt; | CHARACTER
    SET &lt;character set name&gt; | TRANSLATION &lt;transliteration name&gt;
    | TYPE &lt;user-defined type name&gt; | SEQUENCE &lt;sequence generator
    name&gt; | &lt;specific routine designator&gt; | ROUTINE &lt;routine
    name&gt; | FUNCTION &lt;function name&gt; | PROCEDURE &lt;procedure
    name&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;object privileges&gt; ::= ALL PRIVILEGES |
    &lt;action&gt; [ { &lt;comma&gt; &lt;action&gt; }... ]</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;action&gt; ::= SELECT | SELECT &lt;left paren&gt;
    &lt;privilege column list&gt; &lt;right paren&gt; | DELETE | INSERT [
    &lt;left paren&gt; &lt;privilege column list&gt; &lt;right paren&gt; ] |
    UPDATE [ &lt;left paren&gt; &lt;privilege column list&gt; &lt;right
    paren&gt; ] | REFERENCES [ &lt;left paren&gt; &lt;privilege column
    list&gt; &lt;right paren&gt; ] | USAGE | TRIGGER |
    EXECUTE</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;privilege column list&gt; ::= &lt;column name
    list&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;grantee&gt; ::= PUBLIC | &lt;authorization
    identifier&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>The <literal>&lt;object privileges&gt;</literal> that can be used
    depend on the type of the <literal>&lt;object name&gt;</literal>. These
    are discussed in the previous section. For a table, if
    <literal>&lt;privilege column list&gt;</literal> is not specified, then
    the privilege is granted on the table, which includes all of its columns
    and any column that may be added to it in the future. For routines, the
    name of the routine can be specified in two ways, either as the generic
    name as the specific name. HyperSQL allows referencing all overloaded
    versions of a routine at the same time, using its name. This differs from
    the SQL Standard which requires the use of <literal>&lt;specific routine
    designator&gt;</literal> to grant privileges separately on each different
    signature of the routine.</simpara>

    <simpara>Each <literal>&lt;grantee&gt;</literal> is the name of a role or
    a user. Examples of GRANT statement are given below:</simpara>

    <informalexample>
      <programlisting>GRANT ALL ON SEQUENCE aSequence TO roleOrUser 
GRANT SELELCT ON aTable TO roleOrUser  
GRANT SELECT, UPDATE ON aTABLE TO roleOrUser1, roleOrUser2
GRANT SELECT(columnA, columnB), UPDATE(columnA, columnB) ON TABLE aTable TO roleOrUser
GRANT EXECUTE ON SPECIFIC ROUTINE aroutine_1234 TO rolOrUser
</programlisting>
    </informalexample>

    <simpara>As mentioned in the general discussion, it is better to define a
    role for the collection of all the privileges required by an application.
    This role is then granted to any user. If further changes are made to the
    privileges of this role, they are automatically reflected in all the users
    that have the role.</simpara>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>GRANT role</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">GRANT</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>grant role statement</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;grant role statement&gt; ::= GRANT &lt;role name&gt;
    [ { &lt;comma&gt; &lt;role name&gt; }... ] TO &lt;grantee&gt; [ {
    &lt;comma&gt; &lt;grantee&gt; }... ] [ WITH ADMIN OPTION ] [ GRANTED BY
    &lt;grantor&gt; ]</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>Assign roles to roles or users. One or more roles can be assigned
    to one or more <literal>&lt;grantee&gt;</literal> objects. A
    <literal>&lt;grantee&gt;</literal> is a user or a role. If the <literal>[
    WITH ADMIN OPTION ]</literal> is specified, then each
    <literal>&lt;grantee&gt;</literal> can grant the newly assigned roles to
    other grantees. An example of user and role creation with grants is given
    below:</simpara>

    <informalexample>
      <programlisting>CREATE USER appuser
CREATE ROLE approle
GRANT approle TO appuser
GRANT SELECT, UPDATE ON TABLE atable TO approle
GRANT USAGE ON SEQUENCE asequence to approle
GRANT EXECUTE ON ROUTINE aroutine TO approle
</programlisting>
    </informalexample>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>REVOKE</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">REVOKE privilege</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>revoke statement</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;revoke privilege statement&gt; ::= REVOKE [ GRANT
    OPTION FOR ] &lt;privileges&gt; FROM &lt;grantee&gt; [ { &lt;comma&gt;
    &lt;grantee&gt; }... ] [ GRANTED BY &lt;grantor&gt; ] RESTRICT |
    CASCADE</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>Revoke privileges from a user or role.</simpara>

    <indexterm significance="preferred" type="sql">
      <primary>REVOKE ROLE</primary>
    </indexterm>

    <simpara><emphasis role="bold">REVOKE role</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><emphasis>revoke role statement</emphasis></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;revoke role statement&gt; ::= REVOKE [ ADMIN OPTION
    FOR ] &lt;role revoked&gt; [ { &lt;comma&gt; &lt;role revoked&gt; }... ]
    FROM &lt;grantee&gt; [ { &lt;comma&gt; &lt;grantee&gt; }... ] [ GRANTED BY
    &lt;grantor&gt; ] RESTRICT | CASCADE</literal></simpara>

    <simpara><literal>&lt;role revoked&gt; ::= &lt;role
    name&gt;</literal></simpara>

    <simpara>Revoke a role from users or roles.</simpara>
  </section>
</chapter>
